<!-- $Id$
     PHPlot Advanced Programming Topics
     Note: The "callbacks" section used to be its own chapter. Other material
     was moved from the "concepts" chapter. The IDs (for cross-references) for
     relocated text were left alone (conc-*), to avoid changing all xrefs.
     New sections added after the changes use the prefix "adv-*" in IDs.
-->
<chapter id="advanced">
<title>PHPlot Advanced Topics</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This chapter documents advanced PHPlot programming topics, going beyond the
material in <xref linkend="concepts"/>.
  </para>
</abstract>

<sect1 id="adv-customclass">
<title>Custom PHPlot Class</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This section describes how to create a custom PHPlot class.
  </para>
</abstract>
<para>
If you have a number of applications that use PHPlot, and you want to
standardize some of the PHPlot default settings, you can define your
own class which extends the PHPlot class and changes the default settings.
Here is a short example of a custom PHPlot class, which changes the
following defaults:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Use a TrueType font for all text</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Change the default image size to 800 x 600</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Change the default title colors to red</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
To extend the PHPlot class, declare your class as shown below. Make sure
your class constructor calls the PHPlot class constructor before changing
any settings.
<programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
# Define a custom PHPlot class

// Load the PHPlot class first
require_once 'phplot.php';

// Define a class which extends PHPlot:
class my_phplot extends PHPlot {
  function __construct($width=800, $height=600, $out=NULL, $in=NULL)
  {
    parent::__construct($width, $height, $out, $in);
    $this->SetDefaultTTFont('LiberationSans-Bold'); // System dependent
    $this->SetTitleColor('red');
  }
}
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
To use this custom PHPlot class, use <literal>require_once</literal> to
include the file containing the class definition, then create an instance
of the custom class.
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot = new my_phplot();
]]></programlisting>
You can then use the <literal>$plot</literal> object exactly the same as
you might use any other PHPlot object.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="adv-serialize">
<title>PHPlot Object Serialization</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This section contains information about serializing and unserializing
a PHPlot object.
  </para>
</abstract>
<para>
<emphasis>Serializing</emphasis> a PHP variable, array, or object
with the PHP function <function>serialize()</function>
generates a string representation of the value which can be stored or
transmitted.
<emphasis>Unserialization</emphasis> with the PHP function
<function>unserialize()</function> re-creates the variable, array, or
object from the string representation.
</para>

<para>
Starting with PHPlot-5.8.0, PHPlot objects can be serialized and
unserialized, subject to these limitations:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
A PHPlot object can only be serialized until <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>
is used.
However, you can serialize the object, then call
<function>DrawGraph</function>, if you want both the serialization and the
actual plot.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Serialization and unserialization will not work when an input file is
specified in the <xref linkend="PHPlot"/> or
<xref linkend="PHPlot-truecolor"/> constructors.
Consider using <xref linkend="SetBgImage"/> instead.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
You must serialize and unserialize with the exact same version of PHPlot.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Here is an example of serializing a PHPlot object:
<programlisting><![CDATA[require_once 'phplot.php';
$plot = new PHPlot(800, 600);
... // Configure the PHPlot object: Set plot type, data values, etc.
// Do not use DrawGraph (yet)
$str = serialize($plot);
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
The corresponding unserialization looks like this:
<programlisting><![CDATA[require_once 'phplot.php';
$newplot = unserialize($str);
// You can do additional plot setup here if desired.
$newplot->DrawGraph(); // Draw it
]]></programlisting>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="adv-truecolor">
<title>Truecolor Images</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This section contains information about using
<link linkend="def-truecolor">Truecolor images</link> in PHPlot.
This material supplements the text in the <xref linkend="conc-colors"/>.
  </para>
</abstract>
<para>
Truecolor image support was added to PHPlot-5.1.1. With Truecolor image
support, you can:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Create images with a larger number of colors</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Control color transparency with alpha blending</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Perform advanced image processing operations</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
An example of using Truecolor with PHPlot can be found in
<xref linkend="ex-truecolor-histogram"/>.
</para>

<sect2 id="adv-truecolor-overview">
<title>Using Truecolor Images in PHPlot</title>
<para>
To make a Truecolor image in PHPlot, create an object of the derived class
<literal>PHPlot_truecolor</literal> instead of the class
<literal>PHPlot</literal>.
For example, replace this:
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot = new PHPlot(800, 600);
]]></programlisting>
with this:
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot = new PHPlot_truecolor(800, 600);
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
That is all you need to do in order to create truecolor images. All PHPlot
methods are compatible with PHPlot_truecolor objects. An image file
produced from a PHPlot_truecolor object with no other programming changes
will be the same as an image file produced from a PHPlot object except as
described under <xref linkend="adv-truecolor-fileformats"/>.
</para>

<para>
One of the advantages of truecolor images is the ability to use
variable transparency. This is described in the next two sections.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-truecolor-alpha">
<title>Understanding Variable Transparency (Alpha)</title>
<para>
Colors in a truecolor image have four components: red, green, blue, and
alpha. The alpha component corresponds to the transparency of a color.
An alpha value of zero means the color is opaque, and an alpha value
of 127 means the color is transparent, or clear.<footnote>
  <para>
PHPlot follows the GD Library convention here. Other systems use alpha=0 to
mean transparent, and a maximum alpha value to mean opaque.
  </para></footnote>
In between values, from 1 to 126, correspond to various amounts of
transparency.
</para>

<para>
Transparency is only meaningful when drawing objects on top of objects, or
objects on top of the image background. An object drawn with an
opaque color (alpha=0) will replace whatever was in the image before the
object was drawn at that position. An object drawn with an transparent
color (alpha=127) is invisible and does not affect the appearance of the
image. An object drawn with a color that has an alpha value between 1 and
126 will be combined with whatever was in the image before the object was
drawn using alpha blending.
</para>

<para>
The PHP Manual explains alpha blending like this: "In blending mode, the
alpha channel component of the color supplied to all drawing functions
determines how much of the underlying color should be allowed to shine
through. As a result, gd automatically blends the existing color at that
point with the drawing color, and stores the result in the image. The
resulting pixel is opaque."<footnote><para>From the PHP Reference Manual,
imagealphablending</para></footnote>
</para>

<note>
  <para>
Note that the PHP Manual says the resulting pixel is opaque. This means
that objects drawn with alpha above 0 are partially or completely transparent
only relative to other objects in that same image. This does not result
in an image with transparent portions which would show through to a browser
or desktop background, for example.
(Read the PHP Manual page for <function>imagesavealpha</function> for more
about this behavior and how to change it.)
Use <xref linkend="SetTransparentColor"/> to make portions of an image
transparent to web page or desktop backgrounds.
  </para>
</note>

<para>
<?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
The following figure shows the effect of alpha blending when drawing lines.
The left side shows the normal overlaying of lines, and the right side
shows alpha-blended overlaying of lines with alpha = 60 (that is, 60/127
transparency).
The effect of alpha blending can be seen where the data lines cross.
Note: These plots use wide lines (3 pixels) and the portions of
the images are magnified 2x to show detail.
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/alpha-blending.png" scale="58" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Line intersections without and with alpha blending.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-truecolor-using-alpha">
<title>Using Variable Transparency (Alpha) in PHPlot</title>
<para>
To use partially transparent colors (that is, colors with an alpha channel)
with a PHPlot_truecolor object, you can specify an alpha value as part of a
color specification, and you can specify a default alpha value for all data
colors.
</para>

<para>
Use of alpha values with a color specification is described below,
in <xref linkend="adv-truecolor-forms"/>.
Here are some examples of using colors with an alpha specification.
</para>

<para><?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
This sets the color used for labels to red=192, green=192, blue=33, and
alpha=50 (that is, 50/127 transparency).
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot->SetTextColor(array(192, 192, 33, 50));
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para><?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
This sets the color used for tick marks to the color 'blue' from the color
map, with alpha value 64 (64/127 transparency).
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot->SetTickColor('blue:64');
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para><?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
This sets colors for the first three data sets to red, green, and blue with
different alpha values. The three colors are represented using
different formats for illustration purposes.
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot->SetDataColors(array(
      array(255, 0, 0, 60), // Red with alpha=60
      '#00ff0050',          // Green with alpha=80 (0x50)
      'blue:70'));          // Blue with alpha=70
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para><?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
Instead of specifying the alpha value for each data set color, you can
provide a default alpha value for all data colors using the third argument to
This uses the colors specified in $my_color_array with a default alpha of
50. The default is applied to any color definition which does not already
have an alpha value.
<xref linkend="SetDataColors"/>.
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot->SetDataColors($my_color_array, NULL, 50);
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para><?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
This can also be used to apply an alpha value to the default data colors.
This retains the default data colors, but applies alpha = 50 (50/127
transparency) to all the colors. This is a quick way to get partially
transparent data colors without re-specifying all the colors.
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot->SetDataColors(NULL, NULL, 50);
]]></programlisting>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-truecolor-forms">
<title>Color Parameter Form Extensions</title>
<para>
In addition to the forms specified in <xref linkend="conc-colors-forms"/>,
colors specifications can include an alpha value. Although this works with
palette images as well as truecolor images, specifying alpha values
with palette images provides limited value.
<orderedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
A color name, as defined by <xref linkend="SetRGBArray" /> or from a built-in
color map if SetRGBArray was not called, followed by a colon and an alpha
value as a decimal number, for example: 'red:60'. The alpha value is
between 0 (opaque) and 127 (transparent).
Note that colors in the color map can be defined with or without an alpha
value. An alpha value appended to the color name overrides any specified
in the color map. For example, if the color 'red2' is defined in the color
map as array(255,0,0,80) - that is, red with 80/127 transparency - then
'red2' has alpha of 80, and 'red2:40' has alpha of 40.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Numeric color component values, in the form <literal>#rrggbbaa</literal>.
Here rr is red, gg is green, and bb is blue, and each component
value is represented as a 2-digit hexadecimal number between 00 and ff.
Also aa is alpha, represented as a 2 digit hexadecimal number between 00 and 7f.
For example, <literal>#00ff0010</literal> is green with 16/127 transparency.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
A PHP array of red, green, blue, and alpha color component values.
Each value of red, green, and blue are in the range 0 to 255 inclusive,
and the alpha component is in the range 0 to 127 inclusive.
For example,
<literal>array(0,255,0,16)</literal> is the same green with 16/127 transparency.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-truecolor-fileformats">
<title>Image Formats and File Formats, Palette and Truecolor</title>
<para>
PHPlot can produce JPEG, PNG, and GIF image files (and possibly others).
You select the PHPlot output image file format with
<xref linkend="SetFileFormat"/>.
</para>

<para>
PHPlot works with GD images before producing an image file. There are two
types of GD images: truecolor and palette. Truecolor images represent
pixels as 32 bit values, combining 8 bits each of red, green, and blue
components with a 7 bit alpha (transparency) value. Palette images use a
color table with at most 256 entries, and represent pixels as 8 bit indexes
into the color table. The palette image color table entries have 32 bit
values, with the same components as truecolor image pixel values. So
palette images in GD can have at most 256 unique colors, but there is no
limitation on the number of unique colors in truecolor images.
</para>

<para>
As long as you don't specify a background image when creating your plot object,
truecolor images are created with the <literal>PHPlot_truecolor</literal> class,
and palette images are created with the <literal>PHPlot</literal> class.
If you specify a background image, the GD image created by PHPlot matches the
type - truecolor or palette - of your background image file.
More on background image files can be found in
<xref linkend="adv-truecolor-background"/> below.
</para>

<para>
What happens when you output the GD image to an image file depends on the
image file format you select.
</para>

<para>
JPEG image files are always truecolor. Whether you have a GD palette image
or truecolor image, you will get a truecolor image file.  Note: You are
discouraged from using JPEG images with PHPlot, because they are not
optimal for this type of graphical information due to use of lossy
compression.
</para>

<para>
GIF image files are always palette type, limited to 256 colors. If
you have a GD palette image, you will get a palette GIF image file with the
colors you used in your plot. If you have a a GD truecolor image, GD will
convert your image to palette format, reducing the number of colors to 256
if necessary. This may change the appearance of your plot. Note that some
versions of the PHP manual for <function>imagecreatetruecolor()</function>
incorrectly state that you cannot output a GIF file from a truecolor GD image.
</para>

<para>
PNG image files support truecolor images and palette images of various
color depths.  If you have a GD palette image, you will get a palette PNG
image file. If you have a GD truecolor image, you will get a truecolor PNG
image file. Note that by default, even though PNG truecolor image files
support an alpha channel, GD eliminates the alpha channel when producing a
PNG file. The visual effects of alpha blending are reproduced using opaque
colors. GD apparently does this due to poor support in viewers for alpha
channels. Refer to the PHP Manual page on
<function>imagesavealpha()</function> for details.
</para>

<para>
The following figure shows the relationship between constructor, background
image format, GD image type, and image file format.
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/truecolor-formats.png" scale="62" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Constrictor, GD image type, and image file formats.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
</para>

<para>
In the initial release of Truecolor support in PHPlot-5.1.1, alpha channel
information was ignored when using a PHPlot object, and only used with a
PHPlot_truecolor object. This was changed in PHPlot-5.1.2, and alpha
channel information is used for both PHPlot and PHPlot_truecolor classes.
However, alpha channel information is not always useful with palette
images.
More on this can be found in <xref linkend="adv-truecolor-palette"/> below.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-truecolor-plottypes">
<title>Truecolor Images and Plot Types</title>
<para>
All PHPlot plot types work with truecolor images, but not all plot types
work well with alpha blending of data colors.
</para>

<para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Pie Charts</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Avoid using alpha blending with pie charts. The underlying GD
routines do not fill the pie areas in a way that allows proper blending of
colors. Flat pie charts (using SetShading(0)) are not too bad, showing some
artifacts, but shaded or 3D-look pie charts are poorly rendered.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Bar Charts</term>
    <term>Stacked Bar Charts</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Bars are drawn properly, but the 3D shading affects get blended, resulting
in less than ideal appearance. Flat, outlined bars (using SetShading(0))
are fine with transparency, but when shading is on the 3D shadows overlap
portions of the bars. With alpha blending, the overlaps take on new colors.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-truecolor-background">
<title>Background Images</title>
<para><?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
When creating a PHPlot or PHPlot_truecolor object, you can provide an
existing image filename to the constructor as the fourth argument,
<parameter>$input_file</parameter>.
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot = new PHPlot(800, 600, NULL, 'myimage.png');
]]></programlisting>
This image file becomes the background for your plot. (The function
<xref linkend="SetInputFile"/> also does this,
but is deprecated for use except through the constructor.)
</para>

<para>
If you provide an input file to the constructor, the image associated with
your PHPlot or PHPlot_truecolor object takes on the type of the input file:
palette or truecolor. It does not matter which constructor you use when
specifying an input file as background.
(This was changed after the initial release of truecolor support.
In PHPlot-5.1.1, you must use the PHPlot_truecolor constructor in order to
use some truecolor features even when you use a truecolor background
image file. Starting with PHPlot-5.1.2 you can use either constructor.)
</para>

<note>
  <para>
The above applies only when an input file is specified to the PHPlot
or PHPlot_truecolor constructor.  It does not apply to
an image background set with <xref linkend="SetBgImage"/>
nor to a plot area background set with <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaBgImage"/>.
  </para>
</note>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-truecolor-callbacks">
<title>Additional Operations on Truecolor Images Using Callbacks</title>
<para>
Advanced operations on truecolor PHPlot images are possible using PHPlot
callbacks. See <xref linkend="callbacks"/> for more information about using
callbacks.  Here are some of the operations you can perform, and the
corresponding GD functions.  Refer to the GD section of the PHP Manual for
more information on these functions.
</para>
<note>
  <para>
Some of these functions are only available when PHP was built with the
bundled version of the GD library.
  </para>
</note>

<sect3 id="adv-truecolor-callbacks-antialias">
<title>imageantialias()</title>
<para><?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
You can turn on anti-aliasing of truecolor images. This must be done before
anything is drawn, so the pre-drawing callback <literal>draw_setup</literal>
is used. Here is a partial example:
<programlisting><![CDATA[function pre_plot($img)
{
    imageantialias($img, True);
}
...
$plot = new PHPlot_truecolor(1024, 768);
$plot->SetCallback('draw_setup', 'pre_plot');
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
Note: There are limitations with anti-aliased images. You cannot use wide
lines (<xref linkend="SetLineWidths"/>).
Patterned lines do not work, so if you are displaying
X or Y grid lines you must use <xref linkend="SetDrawDashedGrid"/>(False)
to make these solid.
Also note that TrueType Font (TTF) text is always anti-aliased, even on
palette images, regardless of the use of <function>imageantialias()</function>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-truecolor-callbacks-alphablending">
<title>imagealphablending() and imagelayereffect()</title>
<para>
These functions control the combining of partially transparent colors. They
can be used via a <literal>draw_setup</literal> callback, in the same way
as <function>imageantialias</function> in the example above.
Note that alpha blending is on by default with all truecolor images.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-truecolor-callbacks-gammacorrect">
<title>imagegammacorrect()</title>
<para><?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
You can have the GD library perform gamma adjustment on a truecolor image.
This must be done after all drawing, so the post-drawing callback
<literal>draw_all</literal> is used. Here is a partial example:
<programlisting><![CDATA[function post_plot($img)
{
    imagegammacorrect($img, 1.0, 0.5); // Input gamma=1, output gamma=.5
}

...
$plot = new PHPlot_truecolor(1024, 768);
$plot->SetCallback('draw_all', 'post_plot');
]]></programlisting>
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-truecolor-palette">
<title>Palette Images and Advanced Color Features</title>
<para>
You will have a GD palette image if you use the <literal>PHPlot</literal>
constructor without a background image file, or if you use either the
<literal>PHPlot</literal> or <literal>PHPlot_truecolor</literal>
constructors with a background image file that is a palette image (GIF or
some types of PNG). You can use alpha color specifications with palette GD
images, but this is not recommended. The results are not well documented,
but the following behavior has been observed:
</para>

<para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
There is no alpha blending. Drawing operations simply replace existing
pixels values with the new pixel values. (These are actually index values
into the color table.)
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
Alpha values are ignored when the image is output to a JPEG or GIF file.
All colors are output as opaque.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
Alpha values are preserved in PNG image files. These will be palette, not
truecolor, PNG images, with the color table containing the alpha values.
You can therefore have palette PNG files with partial transparency, however
not all viewers properly support this.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Nothing described in <xref linkend="adv-truecolor-callbacks"/> works with
palette images, including gamma adjust and anti-aliasing (except that
TrueType Font text is always anti-aliased.)
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="callbacks">
<title>Callbacks</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This section documents the callback feature in PHPlot.
  </para>
</abstract>

<para>
Callbacks allow a programmer using PHPlot to insert their own functions
into the graph drawing process. Callbacks are currently also used for
development and testing of PHPlot.
</para>

<warning>
  <para>
All PHPlot class variables, and all methods/functions which are not
documented in the "Reference" section of the PHPlot Reference Manual, are
considered to be for internal use and are subject to be changed or removed
at any time.
If you call internal functions, or access internal class variables,
you greatly increase the risk of breaking your application with
future PHPlot releases.
  </para>
</warning>

<sect2 id="callbacks-api">
<title>Callbacks Application Interface</title>
<para>
Refer to these entries in the Function Reference:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
<xref linkend="SetCallback"/> - Register a callback function
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
<xref linkend="GetCallback"/> - Return a currently registered callback function
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
<xref linkend="RemoveCallback"/> - Unregister a callback function
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Either a function name or an object and method can be registered as
a callback with <xref linkend="SetCallback"/>.
For more information about using callbacks with objects and methods,
see the PHP manual under
<ulink url="http://www.php.net/manual/en/language.pseudo-types.php#language.types.callback">Types, Pseudo Types, Callback</ulink>
and the documentation for the PHP
<ulink url="http://www.php.net/manual/en/function.call-user-func.php ">call_user_func</ulink>
function.
Also refer to <xref linkend="callbacks-objects"/> later in this manual.
Whether calling a function or an object method as a callback,
the same calling sequence is used.
</para>
<para>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[function_name($img, $passthrough_arg, [other_args...])
]]></programlisting>
</para>
<para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>$img</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
The GD image resource for the plot image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>$passthrough_arg</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
The third argument supplied to SetCallback ($arg) when the callback is
established. This allows the programmer to pass information to the callback
without using global variables. This can be any PHP type including array.
To pass a reference, you should put it into an array and pass the array.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>other_args...</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Zero or more additional arguments supplied by PHPlot to callbacks of this
type. Refer to <xref linkend="callbacks-names"/> to see what callback
reasons supply extra arguments.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</para>

<para><?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
For example, given this callback setup:
  <programlisting><![CDATA[$plot->SetCallback('draw_graph', 'my_drawing_callback', $myvar);
]]></programlisting>
Then PHPlot will call:
  <programlisting><![CDATA[my_drawing_callback($img, $myvar_value, $plot_area);
]]></programlisting>
Where $myvar_value is the value of $myvar at the time SetCallback was called.
(The plot_area parameter is only supplied for the draw_graph callback in
PHPlot-5.1.0 and later.)
</para>

<para>
Some callbacks are expected to return a value. This is documented in 
<xref linkend="callbacks-names"/>. In all other cases, the return value
from a callback function is ignored.
(Callbacks which return a value were implemented in PHPlot-5.1.3.)
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="callbacks-access">
<title>Callback Function Access</title>
<para>
By default, the callback function has access only to the GD image resource
as the $img argument, the pass-through argument provided when the callback
function was registered, and additional arguments (if any) provided by
PHPlot for the callback. It does not have access to the PHPlot
class object instance, nor any of its contents.
</para>

<para>
If you need access to the internals of the PHPlot class instance from your
callback, you have three options.
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
You can declare your PHPlot class instance variable as
<emphasis>global</emphasis>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
You can pass the instance variable as the $arg when registering the
callback. With PHP5, this will pass a reference to the object, which allows
reading and changing variables. (PHP4 would pass a copy of the object at the
time the callback function is being set up, which would probably not be
useful. There are work-arounds, but PHP4 is no longer supported.)
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
You can use a class method which extends PHPlot.
This is described in <xref linkend="callbacks-objects"/>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</para>

<para>
As stated in the warning at the top of this section, any access to the class
internals is risky and subject to break with any new update to PHPlot.
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="callbacks-names">
<title>Available Callbacks</title>
<para>
This section defines the currently available callback names. A callback
name is also called a <emphasis>reason</emphasis>.
  <note>
    <para>
At most one callback can be active for any given callback name, for each
PHPlot object. Setting a second callback on the same name will result in
the new callback replacing the old one.
    </para>
  </note>
</para>

<para>
Most of the callbacks currently available are drawing callbacks, activated
during the graph drawing process started by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>.
By convention, a drawing callback occurs right after the event which it names.
For example, the <command>draw_titles</command> callback will be called after
drawing the plot titles.
</para>

<para>
Debug callbacks are for use when developing and debugging PHPlot itself.
Needless to say, their use for other purposes is discouraged.
</para>

<para>
The following table lists the available callback reasons.
</para>

<para>
  <informaltable id="callback-reasons">
    <tgroup cols="4">
      <?dbhtml table-summary="PHPlot available callback reasons"?>
      <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="26*" />
      <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="19*" />
      <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="19*" />
      <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="40*" />
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Callback Name:</entry>
          <entry>Calling Point:</entry>
          <entry>Extra Parameters:</entry>
          <entry>Notes:</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>data_color</entry>
          <entry>Every time a color is needed for a data element.</entry>
          <entry>$row, $col, $extra</entry>
          <entry>The callback is expected to return an integer color index
             into the data colors array. This is for custom color selection.
             For more information, see
             <xref linkend="adv-datacolor-callback"/>.</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>data_points</entry>
          <entry>Every time a data point is plotted, for supported plot types.</entry>
          <entry>$shape, $row, $col, ...</entry>
          <entry>This callback is primarily used to create image maps.
             For more information, see <xref linkend="adv-imgmap"/>.
             This was added in PHPlot-5.7.0.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>draw_setup</entry>
          <entry>After all setup, before drawing anything.</entry>
          <entry>(None)</entry>
          <entry>Anything drawn here will be covered by the background.</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>draw_image_background</entry>
          <entry>After drawing the image backgrounds and border.</entry>
          <entry>(None)</entry>
          <entry></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>draw_plotarea_background</entry>
          <entry>After drawing the plot area background.</entry>
          <entry>plot_area</entry>
          <entry>plot_area parameter was added in PHPlot-5.1.0</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>draw_titles</entry>
          <entry>After drawing the plot title, X and Y titles.</entry>
          <entry>(None)</entry>
          <entry>Called even if no titles were set.</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>draw_axes</entry>
          <entry>After drawing the X and Y axis and grid lines.</entry>
          <entry>(None)</entry>
          <entry>Not called for pie charts.</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>draw_graph</entry>
          <entry>After drawing the body of the graph.</entry>
          <entry>plot_area</entry>
          <entry>plot_area parameter was added in PHPlot-5.1.0</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>draw_border</entry>
          <entry>After drawing the plot area border.</entry>
          <entry>(None)</entry>
          <entry>Not called for pie charts before PHPlot-5.6.0</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>draw_legend</entry>
          <entry>After drawing the legend, if legend is enabled.</entry>
          <entry>(None)</entry>
          <entry>Not called if no legend was set.</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>draw_all</entry>
          <entry>After all drawing is complete.</entry>
          <entry>plot_area</entry>
          <entry>Added in PHPlot-5.1.0</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>debug_textbox</entry>
          <entry>Just before drawing any text.</entry>
          <entry>$px, $py, $bbox_width, $bbox_height</entry>
          <entry>Provides access to the orthogonal bounding box position
              and size for the text string.</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>debug_scale</entry>
          <entry>Called at end of many scale calculation functions.</entry>
          <entry>Function name, then an array of variable name =&gt; value</entry>
          <entry>For displaying intermediate values in margin and scale
              calculations.</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
</para>
<note>
  <title>Notes:</title>
  <para>
Several of the drawing callbacks include <parameter>plot_area</parameter>
as an extra parameter. This is an array of 4 values that define the plot area
within the image, in GD pixel coordinates, as left_x, top_y, right_x, and
bottom_y. For more information, see <xref linkend="dev-layout" />.
  </para>
  <para>
See <xref linkend="callbacks-drawing"/>
for information on using the drawing callbacks to annotate your plot.
  </para>
</note>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="callbacks-objects">
<title>Object Methods as Callbacks</title>
<para>
The callback function argument to <xref linkend="SetCallback"/>
can be an array of two elements: a class variable and a method.
This can be used with any class, but here we are interested in using an
extension of the PHPlot class.
Consider the following setup:
</para>
<para>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[class my_PHPlot extends PHPlot
{
  function my_PHPlot($width=600, $height=400, $outfile=NULL, $infile=NULL)
  {
    $this->PHPlot($width, $height, $outfile, $infile);
  }

  function callback($img, $arg)
  {
    fwrite(STDERR, "callback in object\n");
    fwrite(STDERR, "Plot area: ({$this->plot_area[0]}, {$this->plot_area[1]}) :");
    fwrite(STDERR, " ({$this->plot_area[2]}, {$this->plot_area[2]})\n");
  }
}
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
We define a class which extends PHPlot, and a method 'callback' which
displays the plot area using the internal PHPlot class variable plot_area.
(Note we are using a PHP4-style constructor, which also works with PHP5.
You can use the PHP5 constructor method instead.)
</para>

<para>
We will then create an instance of the extended class, and set a callback.
  <programlisting><![CDATA[$plot = new my_PHPlot(400,300);
$plot->SetCallback('draw_titles', array($plot, 'callback'));
]]></programlisting>
This is for PHP5. For PHP4, you need to use a reference to the $plot instance.
Note that PHP4 is no longer supported.
</para>

<para>
When the draw_titles callback is triggered, it will call the 'callback'
method inside our extended class. Because this is an extension of the
PHPlot class, it has access to all the member variables via $this.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="callbacks-drawing">
<title>Using Callbacks to Annotate Plots</title>
<para>
This section contains information about using PHPlot callbacks to annotate
a plot with text and graphics. This is an advanced topic, and requires some
knowledge of both PHPlot and the PHP GD extension.
</para>
<warning>
  <para>
The information in this section uses features which are recent additions
to PHPlot, and in some cases uses PHPlot internal variables and functions.
As a result, these methods are less likely to work with older releases, and
more at risk to change or break in future releases.
  </para>
</warning>

<para>
This section will first provide general information and advice about
annotating plots using callbacks.
<!-- Note exception, link to example's section not example. -->
After, portions of the script from <xref linkend="ex-annotate" />
will be explained in more detail.
</para>

<para>
The emphasis here is on using callbacks, but annotation is also possible 
without callbacks.
You can use <xref linkend="SetPrintImage"/>(False) to disable automatic
output of your image. Then, when <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> returns, you
can annotate your plot using GD functions on the <literal>img</literal>
member variable of your PHPlot object. Use of callbacks is preferred,
however, because it makes your script somewhat less dependent on PHPlot
internals (such as the <literal>img</literal> variable).
</para>

<sect3 id="callbacks-drawing-set">
<title>Setting the callback</title>
<para>
Use <xref linkend="SetCallback"/> to establish a drawing callback.
You can find a list of callbacks in <xref linkend="callbacks-names"/>.
The various callbacks with names starting 'draw_' are called at different
points in the drawing process. Drawn objects will cover items drawn at an
earlier stage. For example, if you draw a line from a 'draw_titles' callback
(which is called after the plot titles are drawn, but before the graph is
drawn), the line would be 'behind' and possibly covered by the plotted data.
</para>
<para>
Note that PHPlot does very little except save parameter values until you
call <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>. For that reason, you should use GD functions
for annotation only from a drawing callback (that is, a callback with a name
starting with 'draw_').
The drawing callbacks are called after PHPlot calculations and image resource
setup, at which point everything is ready for drawing.
In addition, you should not use PHPlot functions which control plot
appearance from your drawing callback. These would either have no affect,
because it is too late, or produce unexpected results.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="callbacks-drawing-coords">
<title>Coordinates</title>
<para>
When drawing with GD, you will use the <link linkend="def-devcoor">Device
Coordinate system</link>. The coordinates in this system are pixels, with
the origin in the upper left corner of your image. Y advances down and X
advances to the right.
</para>
<para>
If you want to make annotations relative to specific values in your plot data,
you need to translate those values from
<link linkend="def-worldcoor">World Coordinates</link> to device coordinates.
Use the PHPlot function <xref linkend="GetDeviceXY"/>
to perform this translation.
You will need access to your PHPlot object from inside your callback function
in order to use this (or any other PHPlot method function). You can make it
global, or designate it as the passthrough argument to SetCallback.
  <note>
    <para>
This does not apply to pie charts, which have do not use world coordinates.
    </para>
  </note>
</para>
<para>
If your annotations will fall outside the plot area (for example, in an
area you reserved for annotation using <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaPixels"/>
or <xref linkend="SetMarginsPixels"/>, then you need not be concerned with
coordinate translation. Of course, you can also add annotations at fixed
pixel coordinates inside the plot area, however these may overlay (if done
from a draw_graph or later callback) or underlay (if done before the
draw_graph callback) the plotted data.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="callbacks-drawing-colors">
<title>Colors</title>
<para>
Every GD drawing function you use will require a color value argument.
You are recommended to allocate your own colors in your callback using the
GD function <function>imagecolorresolve()</function>. This function
will always return a color index, by either re-using an existing color in
the image's color map, or by allocating a new color.
Using imagecolorresolve() rather than trying to access the PHPlot internal
variables for color indexes will protect your script from breaking if the
way PHPlot manages its internal colors ever changes.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="callbacks-drawing-text">
<title>Text</title>
<para>
Text can be added to your plot using GD functions which include
<function>imagestring</function>, for build-in simple fonts, and
<function>imagettftext</function> for TrueType font text. To use these
functions, you need device coordinates, as described above.
</para>
<para>
You can also add text to your plot using the PHPlot function
<xref linkend="DrawText"/>. This is documented only for internal
use by PHPlot, so there is a risk of future incompatibility. But this
function provides support for controlling the text justification, and works
better with multi-line text.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="callbacks-drawing-example">
<title>Example</title>
<para>
This example creates a bar chart and adds annotation. The goal is to draw an
ellipse and add text to the highest and lowest bars in a bar chart.
<!-- Note exception, link to example's section not example. -->
Refer to <xref linkend="ex-annotate" /> for the complete script and
output from this example.
</para>

<para>
The script starts with the usual PHPlot object creation and setup.
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot = new PHPlot(800, 600);
$plot->SetTitle('Monthly Widget Sales');
...
]]></programlisting>
(For the complete script, see the example referenced above.)
</para>

<para>
Before calling DrawGraph, establish the drawing callback. This uses the
<literal>draw_all</literal> callback, which gets called when all drawing is
complete in DrawGraph. (Note: If using PHPlot-5.0.7 or earlier, use
'draw_graph' instead, as 'draw_all' was not yet available.)
The name of our callback function is <literal>annotate_plot</literal>,
and we are passing the PHPlot object ($plot) as a pass-through parameter.
You can use a global or class callback instead -
see <xref linkend="callbacks-api"/> for more on these options.
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot->SetCallback('draw_all', 'annotate_plot', $plot);
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
Here is the declaration of our callback function. The <literal>$img</literal>
parameter is provided by PHPlot itself, and is the GD resource for our image.
The <literal>$plot</literal> parameter is the pass-through argument we provided
above when establishing the callback.
Some callbacks make other parameters available. In fact, 'draw_all' provides
the plot area coordinates as an additional parameter, but we don't need that
here so we do not have to include that in the function declaration.
<programlisting><![CDATA[function annotate_plot($img, $plot)
{
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
As stated above, you should allocate your own colors, rather than trying to
get into PHPlot's internals for color values. Here we allocate two colors
and assign the color indexes to local variables:
<programlisting><![CDATA[$red = imagecolorresolve($img, 255, 0, 0);
$green = imagecolorresolve($img, 0, 216, 0);
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
Next, we want to draw graphics centered on two points in our data. The
points were calculated as best_index (X), best_sales (Y), worst_index (X),
and worst_sales (Y). In order to draw at these locations, we need to
translate the values from
<link linkend="def-worldcoor">World Coordinates</link> to
<link linkend="def-devcoor">Device Coordinates</link>.
This is done using the PHPlot function <xref linkend="GetDeviceXY"/>.
<programlisting><![CDATA[list($best_x, $best_y) = $plot->GetDeviceXY($best_index, $best_sales);
list($worst_x, $worst_y) = $plot->GetDeviceXY($worst_index, $worst_sales);
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
Now we are ready to draw some ellipses, centered on our two data points.
The values 50 and 20 are the width and height, in pixels.
<programlisting><![CDATA[imageellipse($img, $best_x, $best_y, 50, 20, $green);
imageellipse($img, $worst_x, $worst_y, 50, 20, $red);
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
As stated above, we have two options for text, and the example uses each method.
We can draw text using the GD functions, but we have to do a little more
work to position the text. Here the text is approximately centered
horizontally and above the data point. (Note ImageString by default uses the
upper left corner of the text string for positioning.)
<programlisting><![CDATA[$font = '3';
$fh = imagefontheight($font);
$fw = imagefontwidth($font);
imagestring($img, $font, $best_x-$fw*4, $best_y-$fh-10, 'Good Job!', $green);
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
Or, we can use the PHPlot internal function <xref linkend="DrawText"/>.
With a PHPlot version 5.1.0 and later, we omit the font specification
and it will default to the generic font, which can be set with
<xref linkend="SetFont"/>('generic', ...)
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot->DrawText('', 0, $worst_x, $worst_y-10, $red, 'Bad News!', 'center', 'bottom');
]]></programlisting>
</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1> <!-- callbacks -->

<sect1 id="adv-datacolor-callback">
<title>Custom Data Color Selection</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This section describes customizing the selection of data colors using a
PHPlot callback. The data color callback was added in PHPlot-5.1.3.
  </para>
</abstract>

<sect2 id="adv-datacolor-callback-standard">
<title>Standard Behavior of Data Color Selection</title>
<para>
Before explaining how to customize data color selection, here is a review
of how data color selection works by default.
</para>

<para>
Think of your data array as having rows and columns. The rows represent
values of the independent variable (usually X), and the columns contain one
or more values of the dependent variable (usually Y) for that value of the
independent variable. For this discussion, ignore any additional entries in
the data array, such as labels and X values.
The set of values from a column in your data array is also referred to as a
data set.
</para>

<para>
The standard behavior of PHPlot is to select a data color from the data
colors array using the column index for the data point. The selected color
will be used to draw a point marker, line segment, bar, etc.
This was explained in <xref linkend="conc-colors-datacolors"/>.
</para>

<para>
For example, if you have a data array with 12 rows and 3 columns for a bar
chart, you are drawing 12 groups of 3 bars. Within each bar group, the first
bar will be drawn with the first color in the data colors array (the color
with index 0), the second bar will use the second color from
the data colors array, and the third bar will use the third color.
You can see this in <xref linkend="example-bars1"/>, where the first three
colors in the data colors array are SkyBlue, green, and orange.
</para>

<para>
There are two other color arrays: the error bar colors and data border
colors. Error bar colors are used in error plots to indicate the positive
and negative error range, and data border colors are used to outline bars
in bar charts when 3D shading is off.
The same index (but not necessarily the same color) is used to
select the color for any of the three elements which are used in a plot.
For example, the first data set in a points plot with error bars will use
data color index 0 for the point markers, and error bar color index 0 for
the error bars. The second bar in each group in an unshaded bar chart will
use the second data color to fill the bar and the second data border color
to outline it.
</para>

<para>
You can set the colors in the three color arrays with
<xref linkend="SetDataColors"/>, <xref linkend="SetErrorBarColors"/>, and
<xref linkend="SetDataBorderColors"/>.
PHPlot will pad all these arrays to the number of columns in your data
array, by duplicating the earlier values. (For example, if you have 5 data
sets and define 3 colors red, green, and blue, PHPlot will pad this to be a 5
color array red, green, blue, red, green.)
It will not truncate the arrays. This means you can define more data
colors than there are data columns. These additional colors will not be
used with the standard color selection method, but can be used with custom
data color selection.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-datacolor-callback-custom">
<title>Custom Data Color Selection</title>
<para>
If you need more control over data colors, you can use the PHPlot
callback called <literal>data_color</literal>.
(See <xref linkend="callbacks"/> for general information about callbacks.)
Some of the things you can do with custom data color selection are:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
A bar chart with each bar having a different color.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
A linepoints plot with different colors for the line segments and the
point markers.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
A bar chart where the bar color depends on the value of that data point.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>

<note>
  <para>
Custom data color selection is not available for plot types
<literal>pie</literal>, <literal>area</literal>, or
<literal>stackedarea</literal>.
These three plot types already provide full control over the data color
selection, with no need for the callback function,
because each color in the color array is only used once.
  </para>
</note>

<para>
To customize the use of data colors, you will define a function that
accepts as arguments the data array row and column index numbers (0-based
integers), and returns the color array index.  Register this function with
PHPlot as a callback, and your function will be called whenever PHPlot
needs to select a data color.
</para>

<para>
Note that your callback will return an array index, not a color value.
For example, if it returns 0, the first color in the data colors array will
be used, and the first color in the error bar colors array (if error bars
are being drawn), and the first color in the data border colors array (if
data borders are being drawn).
You will most likely need to set up the data colors array (and possibly the
error bar colors array and data border colors array too) in order to get
the results you want.
</para>

<para>
A function to act as a data color callback might look like this:
<programlisting><![CDATA[function pickcolor($img, $passthrough, $row, $col, $extra = 0)
{
  $color_index = ...;

  return $color_index;
}
]]></programlisting>
The first two arguments are common to all callbacks: the PHPlot image
resource, and your passthrough argument (if any - see below).
(You generally will not need to access the image resource from the data colors
callback, but it is provided to all callbacks.)
The second and third arguments specify which data value is being plotted.
The $row corresponds to the independent variable (usually X), and
$col corresponds to the data set - plot line, bar within a bar group, etc.
Both $row and $col are zero based integers indexes.
</para>

<para>
Your callback is expected to return a color array index for this data
point. This will be an integer greater than or equal to zero, where zero
indicates the first color in the colors array should be used.
Your returned index should be within the bounds of the color array being
referenced, however PHPlot will use the value you return modulo the size of
the array. For example, the default PHPlot data colors array has 16 colors.
If your callback returns the value 20, the 5th color in the array will be
used (because 20 % 16 = 4, and index 4 is the 5th value in the array).
</para>

<para>
The $extra argument to your callback is for extra information you may need
to determine the color to use. Currently, this is only used for
'linepoints' plots and 'linepoints' error plots. These plots are drawn in
two stages: points and lines. In case you want different colors for the
points and lines, use the $extra argument. It will have the value 1 when
PHPlot is requesting the color of the point marker (shape), and the value
will be 0 when requesting the color of the line segment.
Note that the error bars of a linepoints error plot are drawn with the
color index returned for the points (but using the error bars colors, not
the data colors).
</para>

<para>
You do not need to specify the $extra argument in your callback function
declaration if you do not need it. But if you do specify it, you must make
it an optional argument with the value zero, because PHPlot does not always
supply the value.
</para>

<para>
The above function would be established as a data color callback for a
PHPlot object $plot like this:
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot->SetCallback('data_color', 'pickcolor', $passthru_arg);
]]></programlisting>
The first argument is the callback name, or 'reason':
<literal>data_color</literal>.
The second argument is the name of your callback function. An object and
method can be used here instead - see <xref linkend="callbacks-objects"/>.
The third argument is an optional pass-through value that will be sent to
your callback function each time it is called.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-datacolor-callback-legend">
<title>Custom Data Color Selection and Legend</title>
<para>
If your plot includes a <link linkend="conc-legend">legend</link>,
the legend uses the colors in the order defined in the data colors array,
without regard to any custom data color selection callback.
When using a legend with a custom data color selection callback, you need
to define your data colors array (with <xref linkend="SetDataColors"/>, if
used) and set your legend lines (with <xref linkend="SetLegend"/>)
knowing that each legend line will reference the corresponding color in the
data array in order.
The Custom Bar Colors example referenced below demonstrates this.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-datacolor-callback-examples">
<title>Custom Data Color Selection Examples</title>
<para>
For examples of using a data color callback, see
<xref linkend="ex-colorcallbackgradient"/> and
<xref linkend="ex-colorcallbackbars"/>.
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1> <!-- Custom data colors -->

<sect1 id="adv-autorange">
<title>Plot Range and Tick Increment Calculations</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This section describes how PHPlot calculates the range of
<link linkend="def-worldcoor">World Coordinate</link> space, and the tick
increment for each axis, when those values have not been set manually.
  </para>
</abstract>

<para>
In order to plot a data set, PHPlot needs to map the data points from world
coordinate space to device coordinate space. The world coordinates of the
data points are generally in real-world units, such as kilometers, seconds,
degrees centigrade, etc. Device coordinates are pixels in an image file,
display screen, or paper hardcopy. PHPlot knows the pixel coordinates of
the limits of the plot area in device space.  In order to translate data
points from world coordinates into pixel coordinates, it needs to know the
limits of world coordinate space.  These can be provided manually, or
computed by PHPlot.
</para>

<para>
The limits of world coordinate space are the end-points of the X and Y axis
lines.  The two end-points of an axis are also referred to as the plot
range along that axis.  Each of those plot ranges is divided into uniformly
sized tick intervals, which may or may not be marked by visible tick marks.
The space between tick marks is called the tick increment. PHPlot will
calculate a suitable tick increment if necessary.
</para>

<para>
The rest of this section describes how PHPlot calculates the limits of the
plot ranges, and the tick increments.
</para>

<note>
  <para>
This section does not apply to pie charts, which do not have X or Y axis lines.
  </para>
</note>

<sect2 id="adv-autorange-manual">
<title>Manual (Fixed) Plot Range and Tick Increment</title>
<para>
If you use <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/> to set both
<varname>Xmin</varname> and <varname>Xmax</varname> to non-NULL values,
this will fix both ends of the X axis.  Similarly, setting both
<varname>Ymin</varname> and <varname>Ymax</varname> to non-NULL values
will fix both ends of the Y axis.
If you set both ends of an axis, PHPlot will use exactly that for the plot
range on that axis.  This is recommended if your data has a range which is
known, predictable, and/or 'natural'. For example, if your Y axis represents
percentage values from 0 to 100, you might use this to fix the Y axis ends:

<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot->SetPlotAreaWorld(NULL, 0, NULL, 100);
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
You can use <xref linkend="SetXTickIncrement"/> to set a fixed X tick
increment, and <xref linkend="SetYTickIncrement"/> to set a fixed Y tick
increment.
If you set a fixed tick increment along an axis, PHPlot will use exactly
that value (even if it results in too many, or too few tick marks).
</para>

<para>
Another way to manually specify tick increments is with
<xref linkend="SetNumXTicks"/> or <xref linkend="SetNumYTicks"/>.
These set the desired number of tick intervals.
PHPlot will then calculate the tick increment by dividing the plot range into
exactly that many intervals.
For example, if the Y axis range is 0 to 17, and you use
<literal>$plot->SetNumYTicks(6)</literal> to get 6 intervals, then the tick
mark spacing will be about 2.833333.
This is probably not a desirable value for the tick increment.
Using <function>SetNumXTicks</function> or <function>SetNumYTicks</function>
to set the number of tick intervals is usually not a good idea, unless you
also set the plot range with <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/>.
</para>

<para>
If you set both ends of the X or Y plot range, PHPlot will position
tick marks starting from the lower end of that range, by default.
For example, if you set the Y axis range from 1 to 20, with a tick
increment of 5, the tick marks will be at 1, 6, 11, and 16.
You can set a <emphasis>tick anchor</emphasis> to change this.
See <xref linkend="adv-autorange-tick-positions"/> below for more information.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-autorange-partial">
<title>Partial Fixed Plot Range</title>
<para>
If you use <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/> to set either
<varname>Xmin</varname> or <varname>Xmax</varname> (but not both) to a
non-NULL value, or you set either
<varname>Ymin</varname> or <varname>Ymax</varname> (but not both) to a
non-NULL value, then you are fixing one end of the plot range.
PHPlot will use your fixed value for that end of the range, and calculate the
other end as described below.
</para>

<para>
This may make sense if your data has a fixed lower (or upper) bound. For
example, if you are plotting outdoor summer temperatures in degrees
Fahrenheit, you might use something like this:
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot->SetPlotAreaWorld(NULL, 60);
]]></programlisting>
which sets Ymin to 60.
</para>

<para>
Since PHPlot positions tick marks starting from the lower limit of the X
and Y plot ranges, setting <varname>Xmin</varname> or <varname>Ymin</varname>
establishes the basis for tick marks along that axis.
For example, if you set the lower end of the X axis range to 12, with a tick
increment of 10, the tick marks along X will be at 12, 22, 32, etc.
You can set a <emphasis>tick anchor</emphasis> to change this.
See <xref linkend="adv-autorange-tick-positions"/> below for more information.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-autorange-range">
<title>Automatic Range Calculation</title>
<para>
Each end of the plot range (for both X and Y) which is not specified using
<xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/> will be calculated by PHPlot.
The algorithm used by PHPlot to calculate the ends of a plot range is not
perfect, but is meant to create reasonable plots in a majority of cases.
</para>
<note>
  <para>
This description applies starting with PHPlot-6.0.0. In older versions,
PHPlot used a more simplistic approach to calculating the plot range.
  </para>
</note>

<para>
Here is an overview of the method, using the Y axis as an example.
<literal>DataMin</literal> and <literal>DataMax</literal>
are the smallest and largest Y values in the data array (or the values
derived from the data array, for some plot types).
<literal>PlotMin</literal> and <literal>PlotMax</literal> are the
calculated limits of the plot range. Remember that PHPlot only calculates
PlotMax and PlotMin if they have not already been set using
<xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/>.

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Initialization:
Start by setting the plot range to the data range: PlotMin = DataMin, and
PlotMax = DataMax. The plot range will now include all the data, but just
barely.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
Zero Magnet:
If the plot range does not currently include zero
(PlotMin &lt;= 0 and 0 &lt;= PlotMax), PHPlot tries to extend the range so it
will begin or end at zero. This is done by either by moving PlotMin down to
zero (for positive data), or by moving PlotMax up to zero (for negative data).
There is a limit as to how far PHPlot is willing to extend the plot range
to include zero (see below).
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
End Adjust / Increase range:
PHPlot may then adjust the ends of the plot range by a factor
(adjust_amount) multiplied by the plot range.  This provides some extra
room above or below the data for data value labels, and prevents the top
(or bottom) of the plotted data from hitting the edge of the plot area,
which would detract from the appearance. Adjustment only occurs for PlotMin
if it is negative, and for PlotMax if it is positive. This corresponds to
the direction of the plot data 'away' from zero.
<!-- This is: 0 < PlotMin < PlotMax  -->
For example, if 0&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;PlotMin&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;PlotMax
(all the data is positive), then PlotMax will be increased.
<!-- This is PlotMin < PlotMax < 0 -->
If PlotMin&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;PlotMax&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;0 (all the data is negative),
then PlotMin will be decreased.
<!-- This is PlotMin < 0 < PlotMax-->
If the range spans 0 with PlotMin&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;0&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;PlotMax,
then both PlotMin will be decreased and PlotMax will be increased.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
End Adjust / Finalize:
PHPlot may then adjust the ends of the plot range further, based on the
adjustment mode (<literal>adjust_mode</literal>), but only if the end of
the range is not already zero.
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the adjustment mode is <literal>T</literal> (Tick, the default mode),
then PlotMax is adjusted up to the next higher tick mark position, and
PlotMin is adjusted down to the next lower tick mark position. Note that
this happens even if tick marks are not displayed.
If a tick anchor is set, this is taken into account when adjusting the
range (see <xref linkend="adv-autorange-tick-positions"/> below).
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the adjustment mode is <literal>R</literal> (Range), there is no further
adjustment.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the adjustment mode is <literal>I</literal> (Integer), then PlotMax is
adjusted up to the next higher integer, and PlotMin is adjusted down to the
next lower integer.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
Note that adjustment modes <literal>R</literal> and <literal>I</literal> are
intended for special applications where the default <literal>T</literal>
(Tick) mode produces undesirable results.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-autorange-params">
<title>Automatic Range Parameters</title>
<para>
The range calculation uses parameters which can be set using
<xref linkend="TuneXAutoRange"/> and <xref linkend="TuneYAutoRange"/>.
The parameters are described in the next sections.
</para>

<sect3 id="autorange-zero-magnet">
<title>Range parameter: zero_magnet</title>
<para>
The <varname>zero_magnet</varname> parameter sets the strength of the
<emphasis>zero magnet</emphasis>, which controls how far PHPlot is
willing to extend the plot range to include zero, if the range does not
already include zero.
This is a floating point number greater than or equal to 0, and less than
or equal to 1.0.
A value of 0 means the magnet is disabled. PHPlot will not extend the
plot range to include zero.
A value of 1.0 means the magnet strength is infinite, and PHPlot will
always extend the plot range to include zero.
For increasing values between 0.0 and 1.0, the zero magnet becomes
stronger, and PHPlot will go further in extending the plot range to include
zero.
</para>

<para>
Between 0 and 1.0, the zero magnet factor is applied as follows. Let
<mathphrase>ZF = zero_magnet / (1 - zero_magnet)</mathphrase>.
This maps the zero magnet domain of 0:1 into the range 0:infinity.
PHPlot will extend the plot range to include 0 if that increases
the range by a factor of ZF or less.
</para>

<para>
For example, the default zero magnet factor of 6/7 results in ZF=6, so
PHPlot will 'pull' the bottom of the plot range down to zero if doing so
will stretch the range by 600% or less. (If the data is all negative, it
will apply the zero magnet to 'pushing' the top of the range to zero in the
same manner.)
If the data range is 500 to 600, PHPlot will adjust it to become 0 to 600,
because adjusting the lower range by 500 is less than the maximum 6*100.
If the data range is 900 to 1000, PHPlot will not adjust it to start at 0,
because the zero magnet is only 'strong enough' to pull the range down by
6*100, not 900.
</para>

<para>
The purpose of having a variable <emphasis>zero magnet</emphasis> is
to balance two conflicting goals:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Including zero in the data range improves the utility of plots, 
as it facilitates comparing relative changes and differences.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Increasing the data range of a plot makes it harder to see relatively small
changes in the data.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="autorange-adjust-mode">
<title>Range parameter: adjust_mode</title>
<para>
The <varname>adjust_mode</varname> parameter selects from one of three methods
PHPlot has to determine how to extend the end of the plot range.
The value is a single character, selecting one of three available modes.
  <informaltable>
    <?dbfo table-width="50%"?> <!-- Table width hint for PDF only -->
    <tgroup cols="2">
      <?dbhtml table-summary="Range adjust mode choices"?>
      <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="20*" align="center" />
      <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="80*" />
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Mode</entry>
          <entry>Description</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>T</entry>
          <entry>
Tick : extend the range, then to the next tick mark.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>R</entry>
          <entry>
Range : extend the range.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>I</entry>
          <entry>
Integer : extend the range, then to the next integer value.
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
The default mode is <literal>T</literal>, extend to tick mark.
Mode <literal>I</literal>, extend to integer, is similar to the only
available adjustment mode available before PHPlot-6.0.0.
</para>

<para>
Range end adjustment works as follows. First, PlotMin is extended by the
<literal>adjust_amount</literal> multiplied by the current plot range
<mathphrase>(PlotMax - PlotMin)</mathphrase>, but only if PlotMin is negative.
Similarly, PlotMax is extended by the same factor, but only if it is positive.
This corresponds to where extra spaces is needed for data value labels, for
example: above positive values, and below negative values.
</para>

<para>
For adjustment mode <literal>R</literal>, that completes the range adjustment.
For example, in this mode, with the adjustment amount 0.025 and data range
-10 to 10, the resulting plot range will be -10.5 to 10.5 (having been
increased at each end by 2.5% times the range of 20).
</para>

<para>
For adjustment mode <literal>I</literal>, after extending the range,
PHPlot adjusts PlotMin to the next lowest integer, and PlotMax to the
next highest integer.
Using the same example, with the data range -10 to 10 and adjustment amount
0.025, the range is now -11 to 11 using this mode.
</para>

<para>
Adjustment mode <literal>T</literal>, the default mode, extends the range
end to coincide with a tick mark (or where a tick mark would be, if tick
marks were displayed).
In this mode, the <literal>adjust_amount</literal> can be thought
of as controlling the minimum amount of space between the top of the data and
the next tick mark.  If the adjust_amount is 0, and the maximum data value
DataMax falls exactly on a tick mark, PHPlot will end the range at that
tick mark. But if adjust_amount is greater than zero, PHPlot will extend
the range by least one additional tick mark.
</para>

<para>
As an example of <literal>T</literal> adjustment mode, consider a Y tick
increment of 10, and adjustment amount 0.03 (3%). With the Y data range of
0 to 95, PHPlot will set PlotMax to 100 - extending the range to the very
next tick mark.  But with a Y data range of 0 to 98, the space between
DataMax and the tick mark at 100 is not enough (less than 3% of the range),
so the range is extended to the next tick mark after that, at 110.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="autorange-adjust-amount">
<title>Range parameter: adjust_amount</title>
<para>
The <varname>adjust_amount</varname> parameter determines how much the end of
the plot range is adjusted (extended) to leave room for labels within the plot
area, or to keep the plotted data from pushing against the edge of the plot.
This is a non-negative floating point value.
</para>

<para>
See the previous section on how the adjust_mode and adjust_amount
parameters are used.
</para>

<para>
The default adjustment amount is either 0 (0%) or 0.03 (3%), depending on the
plot type, and on whether the adjustment is for the independent or dependent
variable. For most plot types, the default is 0 for the independent
variable axis (X for vertical plots, Y for horizontal plots), and 3%
for the dependent variable axis.
Some plot types, such as <link linkend="plottype-bubbles">bubbles</link>,
benefit from adjustment on both axes, so the default value for
adjust_amount is 3% for both X and Y.
Other plot types, such as
<link linkend="plottype-candlesticks">candlesticks</link>, do not need any
adjustment on either axis (because there are no data value labels, and the
upper wick may touch the edge of the plot without harm).
For these plot types, the default adjust_amount is 0% for both X and Y.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-autorange-examples">
<title>Examples of Automatic Range Calculation</title>

<para>
Here are 3 examples showing the automatic range calculation. Each figure
contains 4 plots showing the cumulative effect of the numbered steps which
are detailed above: (1) initial range, (2) zero magnet, (3) end adjust /
increase range, and (4) end adjust / finalize ('Tick' adjust mode).
</para>

<para>
<?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
In the first example, the data is all positive (DataMin &gt; 0).
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/fig-autorange-a.png" scale="58" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Automatic Range calculation steps, positive data.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
</para>

<para>
Note: You can see in the figure about that the small adjustment to the top
of the Y range made at step (3) is completely absorbed in the adjustment to
reach the tick mark at step (4). This is not always the case. If the data
happens to end exactly at a tick mark, and the <literal>adjust_amount</literal>
parameter is greater than zero, PHPlot will extend the range to the next tick
mark after that. In a more general sense, when using 'Tick' adjustment mode,
the adjustment amount represents the minimum amount of space to allow between
the data maximum and the plot maximum.
</para>

<para>
<?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
In the second example, the data is both negative and positive.
Note that in this case the zero magnet (step 2) has no effect, and the end
adjustment (step 3) and adjust to tick (step 4) change
<emphasis>both</emphasis> ends of the range.
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/fig-autorange-b.png" scale="58" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Automatic Range calculation steps, data spans zero.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
</para>

<para>
<?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
The third example has all negative data (DataMax &lt; 0). Zero magnet
applies to the top of the range, and end adjustment applies to the bottom
of the range in this case.
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/fig-autorange-c.png" scale="58" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Automatic Range calculation steps, negative data.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-autorange-implied">
<title>Implied Independent Variable Case</title>
<para>
There are two <emphasis>implied independent variable</emphasis> cases:
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
When using the <link linkend="text-data">text-data</link> data type, you
are drawing a vertical plot without specifying the values of the independent
variable X. Your data array will contain only labels and Y values; the X
values are implied.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
When using the <link linkend="text-data-yx">text-data-yx</link> data type, you
are drawing a horizontal plot without specifying the values of the independent
variable Y. Your data array will contain only labels and X values; the Y
values are implied.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</para>

<para>
If you don't use <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/> to set an explicit plot
range for the independent variable axis in these cases, PHPlot sets the plot
range for that axis to start at 0 and end at N, where N is the number of rows
in the data array. The automatic range calculation is disabled for that
axis, and there is no adjustment.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-autorange-tick">
<title>Automatic Tick Increment Calculation</title>
<para>
For both the X axis and Y axis, PHPlot calculates a tick increment if it was
not set as described above.
(Even if your plot has no visible tick marks along an axis, PHPlot will
calculate a tick increment for that axis, since it might be used in adjusting
the plot range.)
</para>

<note>
  <para>
This description applies starting with PHPlot-6.0.0. In older versions,
PHPlot simply divided the plot range by 10 to calculate the tick increment.
  </para>
</note>

<para>
PHPlot uses one of three methods to calculate a tick increment for a given plot
range (along the X or Y axis). The methods are called 'decimal', 'binary',
and 'date', and correspond to the <varname>tick_mode</varname> parameter
described below.  By default, PHPlot uses the 'decimal' method, unless the axis
labels have been set up to use date/time labels, in which case it uses the
'date' mode.
You can also directly control which method is used.
</para>

<para>
Using the <emphasis>decimal</emphasis> method, PHPlot picks the largest tick
increment which is 1, 2, or 5 times a power of 10, and which divides the plot
range into no fewer than the acceptable minimum number of tick intervals
(see the <varname>min_ticks</varname> parameter below).
The power of 10 can be negative, zero, or positive.
Valid automatically-calculated tick increments for non-negative powers of 10
include 1, 2, 5, 10, 20, 50, 100, 200, 500, etc.
Valid automatically-calculated tick increments for negative powers of 10
include 0.5, 0.2, 0.1, 0.05, 0.02, 0.01, etc.
</para>

<para>
For example, given the range 0 to 135, and the default min_ticks of 8,
PHPlot will calculate a tick increment of 10, giving 14 intervals.  A tick
increment of 20 is not valid because it would result in only 7 intervals,
fewer than the minimum of 8.
A tick increment of 5 would result in 28 intervals; while there is no
explicit maximum, PHPlot chooses the largest valid increment that produces
8 or more intervals.
</para>

<para>
When using the <emphasis>date</emphasis> method, PHPlot selects from a
pre-defined list of valid tick increments.
The list covers a range from 1 second up to 7 days: 1, 2, 5, 10, 15, and 30
seconds; 1, 2, 5, 10, 15, and 30 minutes, then 1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48, 96,
and 168 hours.
PHPlot will pick the largest increment in the list which will result in no
fewer than the acceptable minimum number of tick intervals
(<varname>min_ticks</varname>).
If the plot area range exceeds 7 days, PHPlot switches to the 'decimal' method
instead, with units of 24 hours.
With the 'date' method, PHPlot never chooses an increment less than 1 second.
</para>

<para>
For example, given a date/time range which spans 1020 seconds (17 minutes),
and the default min_ticks of 8, PHPlot will calculate a tick increment of 120
seconds (2 minutes), which results in 9 intervals. This is the largest
increment in the list above which results in 8 or more intervals.
</para>

<para>
When using the <emphasis>binary</emphasis> method, PHPlot picks the largest
tick increment which is a power of 2, and which divides the plot range into no
fewer than the acceptable minimum number of tick intervals
(see the <varname>min_ticks</varname> parameter below).
The power of 2 can be negative, zero, or positive.
Valid automatically-calculated tick increments for non-negative powers of 2
include 1, 2, 4, 8, 16, 32, etc.
Valid automatically-calculated tick increments for negative powers of 2
include 1/2, 1/4, 1/8, 1/16, 1/32, etc. (Note that PHPlot will label these
ticks as decimal values 0.5, 0.25, 0.125 etc., not fractions.)
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-autorange-tick-params">
<title>Automatic Tick Increment Parameters</title>
<para>
The tick increment calculation uses parameters which can be set using
<xref linkend="TuneXAutoTicks"/> and <xref linkend="TuneYAutoTicks"/>.
The parameters are described in the next sections.
</para>

<sect3 id="autotick-min-ticks">
<title>Tick Increment parameter: min_ticks</title>
<para>
The <varname>min_ticks</varname> parameter sets the minimum number of tick
intervals along the axis. The default is 8.
The maximum number of tick intervals will be about 2.5 times the minimum.
(The value 2.5 comes from the largest ratio between adjacent acceptable tick
increment values. This is true for the 'decimal' method choices of 1, 2, 5,
10, 20, etc., the 'binary' method, and also for the pre-defined list of values
used with the 'date' method.)
Therefore, by default, a plot range will have between 8 and 20 tick intervals
inclusive (before possible additional tick intervals resulting from
adjustment to the range, as described above).
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="autotick-mode">
<title>Tick Increment parameter: tick_mode</title>
<para>
The <varname>tick_mode</varname> parameter selects one of the three available
methods to calculate the tick increment:
  <informaltable>
    <?dbfo table-width="50%"?> <!-- Table width hint for PDF only -->
    <tgroup cols="2">
      <?dbhtml table-summary="Axis tick modes"?>
      <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="20*" />
      <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="80*" />
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Mode</entry>
          <entry>Description</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>decimal</entry>
          <entry>Use a power of 10 times 1, 2, or 5</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>binary</entry>
          <entry>Use a power of 2</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>date</entry>
          <entry>Use a date/time increment value</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
These methods are described in more detail above.
</para>

<para>
By default, PHPlot will automatically decide which method to use.
It will use the <literal>'date'</literal> method if the corresponding axis
tick labels use date/time formatting (as set with 
<xref linkend="SetXLabelType"/><literal>('time')</literal> or
<xref linkend="SetYLabelType"/><literal>('time')</literal>).
Otherwise is will use the <literal>'decimal'</literal>  method.
</para>

<para>
Use this parameter to override the automatic tick increment method selection.
For example, if you are using date/time values along the X axis,
but have a custom label formatting function (rather than selecting
<literal>time</literal> format type), you will probably want to tell PHPlot
to pick a date/time tick increment for the X axis:
<programlisting><![CDATA[// Pick a date/time tick increment on X:
$plot->TuneXAutoTicks(NULL, 'date');
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
Another example is if you are using time value label types along X,
but you want tick increments to follow the 1, 2, 5 times power of 10 rule,
rather than choosing a date/time value. You can use:
<programlisting><![CDATA[// Format X labels as time values:
$plot->SetXLabelType('time', '%H:%M:%S');
// Override default and use the decimal method to pick a tick increment:
$plot->TuneXAutoTicks(NULL, 'decimal');
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
In this third example, your Y axis values represent something like memory
sizes which are normally measured in powers of two. You can have PHPlot pick
a power of two as a tick increment with:
<programlisting><![CDATA[// Use a power of 2 for the Y axis tick increment:
$plot->TuneYAutoTicks(NULL, 'binary');
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
If the plot range is small enough, PHPlot may select a tick increment which
is less than one - a negative power of two.
This results in a tick increment of 1/2, 1/4, 1/8, 1/16, or smaller.
If you want to use the binary tick method, but do not want fractional tick
increments, set <varname>tick_inc_integer</varname> (see next section):
<programlisting><![CDATA[// Valid tick increments are powers of 2 &gt;= 1
$plot->TuneXAutoTicks(NULL, 'binary', TRUE);
]]></programlisting>
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="autotick-tick-inc-integer">
<title>Tick Increment parameter: tick_inc_integer</title>
<para>
The <varname>tick_inc_integer</varname> parameter is a boolean flag which
can be set to prevent fractional tick increments.
If the flag is TRUE, PHPlot will not pick a tick increment less than 1.
This may result in fewer than <varname>min_ticks</varname> tick intervals.
If the flag is FALSE, PHPlot may pick any tick increment.
The default is FALSE.
</para>

<para>
The 'decimal' and 'binary' tick increment selection methods (see above)
can select tick increments less than 1, using negative powers of 10 or 2
respectively.
This will happen if the plot range is small enough (and/or
<varname>min_ticks</varname> is high enough).
Specifically, a fractional tick increment will result from having a plot
range which is less than the minimum number of ticks.
Set <varname>tick_inc_integer</varname> to TRUE if you do not want
fractional tick increments.
This parameter does not apply to the 'date' tick increment selection method,
which does not support tick increments less than 1 second.
In 'date' mode, <varname>tick_inc_integer</varname> is assumed TRUE.
</para>

<note>
  <para>
PHPlot never picks a tick increment which is greater than one and not a whole
number. Selected tick increments are either integers &gt;= 1, or fractions
between 0 and 1.
  </para>
</note>

<para>
For example, if your Y data range is 0 to 1.8, and you set the
<varname>tick_inc_integer</varname> parameter for Y to TRUE,
then PHPlot will use a tick increment of 1, and you will get only
2 tick intervals.  This is less than the default minimum of 8
tick intervals.
With <varname>tick_inc_integer</varname> FALSE, PHPlot would use a tick
increment of 0.2 in 'decimal' mode, or 0.125 in 'binary' mode.
</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-autorange-tick-positions">
<title>Tick Positions</title>
<para>
This section describes how PHPlot positions the tick marks along the X and Y
axis (if tick marks are enabled), and the tick label values which result.
Several factors are involved:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
The plot range minimum (PlotMin), which is the world coordinates of the left
end of the X axis, or the world coordinates of the bottom of the Y axis.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Whether or not a tick anchor was set. You use a tick anchor to tell PHPlot
that you want tick marks based on a particular world coordinate value.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
The plot range adjustment mode <varname>adjust_mode</varname> (see above),
if PHPlot calculated the plot range minimum PlotMin automatically.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
PHPlot generally places tick marks along each axis starting from the minimum
value of the plot range (PlotMin), which is the left-most position on the X
axis, and the bottom-most position on the Y axis.
Therefore, the value of PlotMin affects all the tick values. For example,
if the tick increment is 10, and PlotMin is 12, ticks will be at 12, 22,
32, 42.
</para>

<para>
A tick anchor can be set with <xref linkend="SetXTickAnchor"/> or
<xref linkend="SetYTickAnchor"/> to change tick mark positions. In the
above example, with PlotMin 12, if you set a tick anchor at 10, you will
get tick positions 20, 30, 40, etc. Setting the tick anchor shifts all the
ticks, so one of them falls at the anchor (or would, if the axis was
extended).  Thus, a tick anchor can be used to 'round off' the tick values
to desired numbers, when the plot range minimum (PlotMin) is not a multiple
of the tick increment.
</para>

<para>
If you set the plot range minimum (PlotMin) to a fixed value with
<xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/>, consider that this value will be
used as the basis for tick marks along that axis, unless you also set
a tick anchor.
</para>

<para>
If PHPlot calculates the plot range minimum using the default adjustment
mode <literal>T</literal> (adjust to tick, see above), then PHPlot will
adjust the range to start at a tick mark. That is, PHPlot acts as if a
tick anchor was set at 0. Your tick marks will be at whole multiples
of the tick increment, unless you set a tick anchor to move them somewhere
else.
</para>

<para>
In the other adjustments modes - <literal>I</literal> (integer) or
<literal>R</literal> (range) - PHPlot makes no attempt to correlate the
plot range minimum with the tick increment. Your tick marks will probably
not be located at multiples of the tick increment.
In mode <literal>R</literal> (range), your tick marks will likely not even be
whole numbers.  As in all other cases, you can set a tick anchor to position
the tick marks at the values you prefer.
</para>

<para>
Here are some examples of PHPlot-calculated plot ranges and tick positions,
when no tick anchor has been set.
  <informaltable>
    <?dbfo table-width="100%"?> <!-- Table width hint for PDF only -->
    <tgroup cols="6">
      <?dbhtml table-summary="Range and tick position results"?>
      <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="8*" align="center" />
      <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="8*" align="center" />
      <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="12*" align="center" />
      <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="12*" align="center" />
      <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="25*" align="center" />
      <colspec colname="c6" colwidth="35*" />
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Y data min</entry>
          <entry>Y data max</entry>
          <entry>Adjustment Mode</entry>
          <entry>Resulting Plot Range</entry>
          <entry>Resulting Tick Positions</entry>
          <entry>Notes</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>7</entry>
          <entry>123</entry>
          <entry><literal>T</literal> (tick)</entry>
          <entry>0 to 130</entry>
          <entry>0, 10, 20, ... 130</entry>
          <entry>
The bottom of the Y range is extended to zero, and the tick marks are at
multiples of 10. The top of the Y range is extended to the next tick mark.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>7</entry>
          <entry>123</entry>
          <entry><literal>R</literal> (range)</entry>
          <entry>0 to 126.69</entry>
          <entry>0, 10, 20, ... 120</entry>
          <entry>
With <literal>'R'</literal> adjustment mode, the top of the Y range is
extended by 3% of the range. The bottom of the Y range was moved to zero
(due to the <emphasis>zero magnet</emphasis>), so the tick marks are based
at 0 and positioned at whole multiples of 10. The resulting tick marks
are the same as <literal>'T'</literal> mode, except the Y axis does not end
at a tick mark.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>7</entry>
          <entry>123</entry>
          <entry><literal>I</literal> (integer)</entry>
          <entry>0 to 127</entry>
          <entry>0, 10, 20, ... 120</entry>
          <entry>
Here <literal>'I'</literal> adjustment mode is almost the the same as the
previous case, except the top of the range is adjusted to the next integer.
Since there is no tick mark there, the difference would not be visible.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>-17</entry>
          <entry>33</entry>
          <entry><literal>T</literal> (tick)</entry>
          <entry>-20 to 35</entry>
          <entry>-20, -15, -10, -5, 0, 5, 10, ... 35</entry>
          <entry>
Both ends of plot range are adjusted to a tick position,
with an implied tick anchor at 0. The resulting tick marks are at
whole multiples of the tick step 5.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>-17</entry>
          <entry>33</entry>
          <entry><literal>R</literal> (range)</entry>
          <entry>-18.5 to 34.5</entry>
          <entry>-18.5, -13.5, -8.5, 1.5, 6.5, ... 31.5</entry>
          <entry>
In this mode, the range is simply extended by 3% (by default) at each end,
where 3% of (33+17) = 1.5. The resulting tick mark positions are probably
not ideal.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>-17</entry>
          <entry>33</entry>
          <entry><literal>I</literal> (integer)</entry>
          <entry>-19 to 35</entry>
          <entry>-19, -14, -9, -4, 1, 6, ... 31</entry>
          <entry>
In this mode, the range is extended by 3%, and then the ends are extended
to the next integer. The tick mark positions are whole numbers now, but
not anchored at 0.
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
</para>

<para>
To summarize, setting a tick anchor to force the tick positions to align one
tick at a particular value, usually 0, can be useful in the situations
including:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
You are letting PHPlot calculate the range, but with adjustment mode
<literal>R</literal> (range) or <literal>I</literal> (integer).
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
You are manually setting the minimum of the plot range with
<xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/> to a value other than zero or
a whole multiple of the tick increment.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
You are using date/time values along the axis, and you need the ticks to
start at a specific date/time value (such as the start of an experiment).
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
You are using a version before PHPlot-6.0.0, which only supports an
adjustment mode similar to <literal>I</literal> (integer).
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-autorange-regress">
<title>Plot Range Regressive Cases</title>
<para>
Given incomplete or contradictory data, PHPlot will always produce a positive
plot range (PlotMin &lt; PlotMax), although the range may be somewhat arbitrary.
Here are some of the regressive cases, and how PHPlot produces an automatic
range for them. <literal>DataMin</literal> and <literal>DataMax</literal>
mean the limits of the data from the data array; <literal>PlotMin</literal>
and <literal>PlotMax</literal> are the limits of the plot range.
In all cases, any values specified in <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/> will
not be altered by PHPlot, even if it results in a plot with no visible data
points.

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Empty range with non-zero values (DataMin == DataMax != 0):</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
For positive data, PHPlot uses the range 0 to K, where K is the larger of
DataMin and 10. For example, if all the Y values are 5, PHPlot uses 0 to 10
for the Y range; if all the Y values are 150, PHPlot uses 0 to 150.
For negative data, PHPlot uses a similar method, setting PlotMax=0.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Empty range with all zero values (DataMin == DataMax == 0):</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
PHPlot uses the arbitrary range 0 to 10.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Partially specified range with maximum set and all data above that:</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
If you set PlotMax to a value, but all your data is above that (DataMin &gt;
PlotMax), you will get an empty plot. PHPlot will use a range of 0 to
PlotMax if your PlotMax is positive, else a range of PlotMax-10 to PlotMax.
All your data points will be outside the plot area.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Partially specified range with minimum set and all data below that:</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
If you set PlotMin to a value, but all your data is below that (DataMax &lt;
PlotMin), you will get an empty plot. PHPlot will use a range of PlotMin
to 0 if your PlotMin is negative, else a range of PlotMin to PlotMin+10.
All your data points will be outside the plot area.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Negative range or zero range:</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
If you try to use <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/> to set a negative
range (PlotMin &gt; PlotMax) or zero range (PlotMin == PlotMax), PHPlot
will report an error and not produce a plot.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

  </variablelist>
</para>

<para>
Note that the above range choices happen as part of the "initialization"
step of automatic range calculation (see <xref linkend="adv-autorange-range"/>
above). That is, the selected range is then subject to the same adjustments as
in other cases.
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="adv-tuning">
<title>Tuning Parameters</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This section documents some PHPlot class member variables that can be used
to adjust the appearance of plots.
You should rarely find it necessary to change these, and PHPlot does not
provide "Set" functions for them.
  </para>
</abstract>

<para>
The class member variables listed in <xref linkend="dev-vars-list"/> are
generally reserved for use only by the class implementation itself. But
there are some adjustments you can make to the appearance of a plot only
by changing member variables.
This section documents some PHPlot class member variables that alter a plot
appearance, but which do not have any defined class functions for you to
use to set the values.
</para>
<para>
For example, if you want PHPlot to draw the X/Y grid above (after) the plot,
rather than behind it, you would do the following:
  <programlisting><![CDATA[$plot = new PHPlot(800, 600);
...
$plot->grid_at_foreground = TRUE; // Draw grid after plot
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<sect2 id="adv-tuning-bars">
<title>Tuning Bar Charts</title>
<para>
These variables affect plot types <link linkend="plottype-bars">bars</link>
and <link linkend="plottype-stackedbars">stackedbars</link>.
They are used to control the width of the bars.
(For horizontal plots, the "width" of the bars is actually the height.)
</para>

<para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>bar_extra_space</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Controls the amount of extra space within each group of bars. Default is 0.5,
meaning 1/2 of the width of one bar is left as a gap, within the space
allocated to the group (see <varname>group_frac_width</varname>).
Increasing this makes each group of bars shrink together.
Decreasing this makes the group of bars expand within the allocated space.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>group_frac_width</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Controls the amount of available space used by each bar group. Default is 0.7,
meaning the group of bars fills 70% of the available space (but that includes
the empty space due to <varname>bar_extra_space</varname>).
Increasing this makes the group of bars wider.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>bar_width_adjust</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Controls the width of each bar. Default is 1.0.
Decreasing this makes individual bars narrower, leaving gaps between the
bars in a group. This must be greater than 0. If it is greater than 1, the
bars will overlap.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
If bar_extra_space=0, group_frac_width=1, and bar_width_adjust=1
then all the bars touch (within each group, and adjacent groups).
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-tuning-boxes">
<title>Tuning Box Plots</title>
<para>
These variables affect plot type <link linkend="plottype-boxes">boxes</link>.
(Box Plots were added in PHPlot-6.1.0.)
</para>
<para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>boxes_max_width</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
This is one half the maximum width of the boxes. The default is 8 pixels.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>boxes_min_width</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
This is one half the minimum width of the boxes. The default is 2 pixels.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>boxes_frac_width</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
This is the fractional amount of the available space (plot width area
divided by number of points) to use for half the width of the boxes.
The default is 0.3. This needs to be less than 0.5 or there will be
overlap between adjacent boxes.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>boxes_t_width</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
This is the ratio of the width of the 'T' ends of the whiskers to the
width of the boxes.  The default is 0.6, meaning the 'T' ends are 60%
of the width of the boxes.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</para>

<para>
PHPlot calculates the width of the boxes in a box plot in the same way as
it does for OHLC and candlestick plots (see <xref linkend="adv-tuning-ohlc" />).
Half of the width of each box is:
<programlisting>half_width = max(boxes_min_width, min(boxes_max_width, boxes_frac_width * avail_area))
Where avail_area = plot_area_width / number_data_points
</programlisting>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-tuning-bubbles">
<title>Tuning Bubble Plots</title>
<para>
These two variables set the range of bubble size in
<link linkend="plottype-bubbles">bubbles</link> plots.
</para>

<para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>bubbles_min_size</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Minimum bubble diameter in pixels.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>bubbles_max_size</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Maximum bubble diameter in pixels.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</para>

<para>
The point with the smallest Z value will be drawn as a bubble with a diameter
of bubbles_min_size, and the point with the largest Z value will be drawn as
a bubble with a diameter of bubbles_max_size. That is, PHPlot linearly maps
the range of Z values in the plot to the range of bubble sizes.
</para>

<para>
By default, the minimum bubble size is 6 pixels, and the maximum bubble
size is 1/12 times the smaller of the plot area width and plot area height.
For example, if the plot area is 800x600, the default maximum bubble size
will be 50 pixels (600 / 12).
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-tuning-ohlc">
<title>Tuning OHLC Charts</title>
<para>
These variables affect plot types <link linkend="plottype-ohlc">ohlc</link>,
<link linkend="plottype-candlesticks">candlesticks</link>,
and <link linkend="plottype-candlesticks2">candlesticks2</link>,
For candlesticks plots, they adjust the calculation of the width of the
candlestick body.
For basic OHLC plots, they adjust the calculation of the length of the tick
marks which represent opening and closing prices.
(All of these were added in PHPlot-5.3.0.)
</para>
<para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>ohlc_max_width</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
This is one half the maximum width of the candlestick body, or
the maximum length of an OHLC tick mark. The default is 8 pixels.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>ohlc_min_width</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
This is one half the minimum width of the candlestick body, or
the minimum length of an OHLC tick mark. The default is 2 pixels.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>ohlc_frac_width</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
This is the fractional amount of the available space (plot width area
divided by number of points) to use for half the width of the candlestick
bodies or OHLC tick marks. The default is 0.3. This needs to be less than
0.5 or there will be overlap between adjacent candlesticks.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</para>

<para>
PHPlot calculates a value to use for one half the width of the candlestick
bodies, or for the OHLC open/close tick mark lengths, as follows:
<programlisting>half_width = max(ohlc_min_width, min(ohlc_max_width, ohlc_frac_width * avail_area))
Where avail_area = plot_area_width / number_data_points
</programlisting>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-tuning-pie">
<title>Tuning Pie Charts</title>
<para>
These variables adjusts the appearance of
<link linkend="plottype-pie">pie charts</link>.
</para>

<para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>pie_diam_factor</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Diameter factor for shaded pie charts. This is the ratio of the height to
the width of the pie. The default value is 0.5, meaning the pie chart will be
drawn as an ellipse with height equal to half of its width.
This variable is ignored for unshaded plots (see <xref linkend="SetShading"/>),
which are always circular (diameter factor of 1.0).
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>pie_min_size_factor</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
The minimum size of the pie in a pie chart, relative to the plot area size.
When pie chart autosizing is on (see <xref linkend="SetPieAutoSize"/>),
and pie labels are located outside the pie chart (as they are by default),
PHPlot will shrink the pie so the labels will fit inside the plot area.
To prevent an overly long label from making the pie too small,
PHPlot uses <varname>pie_min_size_factor</varname> to limit
how small the pie will become.
The default value is 0.5, meaning the pie chart will be no smaller than
half the width or height of the plot area, even if that makes the labels
fall partly off the image.
        </para>
        <para>
Setting this smaller allows the pie to be a smaller portion of the plot
area, if long labels require the space. Setting this larger prevents the
pie from becoming smaller in that case.
Setting this to 1.0 is approximately equivalent to using
<literal>SetPieAutoSize(False)</literal>. (The difference is that the
later still leaves a small gap between the pie and the plot area boundary.)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-tuning-legend">
<title>Tuning the Legend</title>
<para>
This variable adjusts the appearance of the legend.
</para>
<para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>legend_colorbox_width</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
This is an adjustment factor for the width of the color boxes in the legend.
With the default value 1.0, the color boxes are as wide as one character in
the font used in the legend (width of "E" for TrueType fonts).
A value of 2.0 makes the color boxes twice as wide, and 0.5 makes them half
the character width.
(This was added in PHPlot-5.3.0.)
        </para>

        <para>
If point shapes are used in the legend instead of color boxes
(see <xref linkend="SetLegendUseShapes"/> - for points plots and similar),
then <literal>legend_colorbox_width</literal> still adjusts the horizontal
space allocated for the point shape. The point shape itself is not scaled,
but is always drawn at the same size as in the plot itself. If the plot
area has a color background, the width adjustment will stretch the
box in that color which is drawn behind the point shape.
        </para>

        <para>
If line markers are used in the legend of instead of color boxes (see
<xref linkend="SetLegendUseShapes"/> - with line plots and similar),
then <literal>legend_colorbox_width</literal> scales the horizontal
space allocated for the line marker, but there is an additional factor
of 4 applied by PHPlot.
This leaves enough room to draw a line segment that can be identified
visually by color and width.
        </para>

      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-tuning-labels">
<title>Tuning Labels</title>
<para>
These variables affect the appearance of labels.
</para>

<para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>data_value_label_angle</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
This sets the angle, in degrees, for the position of data value labels near
the data points they label.
Together with <varname>data_value_label_distance</varname>,
it determines the position of the reference point for the label.
(This does not apply to data value labels for bars or stackedbars plots, as
the label position is fixed for these plot types.)
The default is 90 degrees, which places the label above the data point.
PHPlot automatically selects which text alignment to use, based on the angle.
For example, with the default 90 degree angle, the label will
be horizontally centered, vertically bottom aligned.  If the angle is 0
degrees, the alignment is horizontally left, vertically centered.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>data_value_label_distance</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
This sets the distance, in pixels, for the position of data value labels near
the data points they label.
Together with <varname>data_value_label_angle</varname>,
it determines the position of the reference point for the label.
(This does not apply to data value labels for bars or stackedbars plots, as
the label position is fixed for these plot types.)
The default is 5 pixels.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-tuning-misc">
<title>Miscellaneous Tuning</title>
<para>
These variables affect other aspects of the appearance of a plot.
</para>

<para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>grid_at_foreground</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Controls the order in which certain plot elements are drawn. The default is
FALSE, meaning the X axis, Y axis, and grid lines are drawn before the main
part of the plot. If TRUE, the X axis, Y axis, and grid lines are drawn
after the main part of the plot, which results in the grid lines overlaying
the plotted data.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>locale_override</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Set this to TRUE (or any non-empty value) to prevent PHPlot from loading
information about the locale from the operating system.
You must do this if you want to override the locale using
<function>setlocale()</function> from your PHP code, perhaps because your
platform does not allow setting the locale from environment variables.
See <xref linkend="SetNumberFormat"/> for more information.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><varname>safe_margin</varname></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
This is the amount of space that PHPlot leaves between elements that
should not touch. The default is 5 pixels. Changing this is not recommended.
The effect is similar to changing the cellpadding on an HTML table.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1> <!-- Tuning -->

<sect1 id="adv-multiplot">
<title>Multiple Plots Per Image</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This section contains information about producing more than one plot on an
image.
  </para>
</abstract>

<para>
Using PHPlot, you can produce more than one plot on a single image.  These can
be <emphasis>tiled plots</emphasis> - separate plots manually positioned within
the image, or <emphasis>overlay plots</emphasis>.
Tiled plots are used when you want to display more than one plot on a single
image, for example side-by-side.
Overlay plots are used when you want to show more than one type or range
of data representation on a single plot.  For example, an overlay plot could
be used to show two data sets with different Y scales, or to overlay a bar
chart with a line plot.
You can also combine tiled and overlay plots in a single image.
</para>

<para>
An example of two tiled plots on an image can be found in
<xref linkend="ex-twoplot1"/>.
An example of an overlay plot can be found in
<xref linkend="ex-outbreak"/>
</para>

<sect2 id="adv-multiplot-overview">
<title>Overview of Multiple Plots</title>

<para>
When producing multiple plots on an image, a single PHPlot object is used.
The overall steps to be followed are:
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Create a <function>PHPlot</function> or <function>PHPlot_truecolor</function>
object (referred to here as <literal>$plot</literal>).
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Use <literal>$plot->SetPrintImage(False)</literal> to disable automatic
output of the image after a plot is created.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Prepare the first plot, including setting the data array, plot type, and any
other applicable settings.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Use <literal>$plot->DrawGraph()</literal> when complete. 
This creates the plot, but does not produce any output.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Repeat the previous two steps to prepare each additional plot, completing
it with <literal>$plot->DrawGraph()</literal>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
When all the plots are complete, use <literal>$plot->PrintImage()</literal> to
output the completed image.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</para>

<para>
The sections which follow contain additional information you will need
to produce multiple plots on a single image.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-multiplot-settings">
<title>Plot Settings with Multiple Plots</title>

<para>
In general, PHPlot applies settings made for one plot as defaults for the
next plot, when using the same PHPlot class instance.
There are some special cases, however, which are discussed in the
sections below.
</para>

<sect3 id="adv-multiplot-global">
<title>Global Settings</title>
<para>
Certain plot elements apply to the image as a whole, not to individual plots.
PHPlot will draw these at most once per image. (That is, the element will be
drawn only the first time <literal>DrawGraph()</literal> is called after the
element has been set up.)
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Main title (<xref linkend="SetTitle"/>)
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Image background color (<xref linkend="SetBackgroundColor"/>)
or image background file (<xref linkend="SetBgImage"/>)
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Image border (<xref linkend="SetImageBorderColor"/> and
<xref linkend="SetImageBorderType"/>)
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
For example, the first plot on an image that has a main title will result in
the main title being drawn. If any subsequent plot (using the same PHPlot
instance) also sets a main title, that will be ignored.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-multiplot-datascale">
<title>Data Scaling</title>
<para>
Whether you use <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/> to set the plot area
data range, or you let PHPlot calculate the plot area data range,
that range applies to all subsequent plots unless overridden.
Even if you set a new data array, the calculated or pre-set data range from
the previous plot applies. Without being told otherwise, PHPlot will not
re-examine the data array to recalculate the data range.
This allows you to re-use an automatically calculated data range, if you want.
  <note>
    <para>
Nothing related to world coordinates and data scaling applies to pie charts,
which have do not use world coordinates.
    </para>
  </note>
</para>
<para>
If instead you want PHPlot to automatically calculate the data range for
additional plots, call <literal>SetPlotAreaWorld()</literal> (with no
arguments), or <literal>SetPlotAreaWorld(NULL, NULL, NULL, NULL)</literal>.
Either of these forms causes PHPlot to forget about a specified or
calculated data range, and it will compute a new range.
</para>
<para>
Of course, you can also use <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/> with
parameter values, to manually set all or part of the data range for each plot.
Any parameters you do not set (or specify as NULL) will be calculated based
on the data array for the current plot.
That is, PHPlot will forget about the previous data range once you call
<xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/>, regardless of how many non-NULL parameters
you use.
</para>
<para>
When overlaying plots, you will often want all the plots to use the same
data scale, so the values can be read off of the axis. Another option is to
have two separate Y scales, with one represented on the left side and one
on the right side. (See <xref linkend="ex-outbreak"/> for an example of
overlaying plots with two different Y scales.)
In some cases it may make sense to overlay plots with different scales and
no separate axis, for example when using data value labels, or when the
important information is the trend or shape shown by the graph rather than
the actual values.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-multiplot-plotarea">
<title>Plot Area</title>
<para>
You can specify a plot area (window) with <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaPixels"/>
or <xref linkend="SetMarginsPixels"/>, or you can let PHPlot calculate a
plot area.
Whether you set the plot area yourself, or you let PHPlot calculate
it, those settings apply to all subsequent plots unless overridden.
</para>
<para>
This means that if you are doing side-by-side (tiled) plots on an image,
you must use <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaPixels"/> or
<xref linkend="SetMarginsPixels"/> with each plot, to set
the area of the image to be used for that plot.
Remember that the plot area does not include the axis labels, tick marks,
or titles, so you must leave enough room between and around plots for these.
</para>
<para>
If you are doing overlay plots, you can let PHPlot calculate the plot area
for the first plot, or you can specify the area with
<xref linkend="SetPlotAreaPixels"/> or <xref linkend="SetMarginsPixels"/>.
You need not use these for subsequent plots; PHPlot will continue to use the
same window, overlaying the additional plots.
</para>
<para>
However, if you allow PHPlot to calculate the plot area, it will only use
information in the first plot to determine the margins.
This will not work well if subsequent plots require more margin space.
For example, if the first plot has a Y axis title and tick labels only on the
left side, and the second overlay plot has a Y axis title and tick labels
on the right side, automatic plot area calculation will only leave enough
margin space on the left side.  As a result, the right side Y axis title and
tick labels may fall off the image edge.  To avoid this, use either
<xref linkend="SetPlotAreaPixels"/> or <xref linkend="SetMarginsPixels"/>
to specify large enough margins.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-multiplot-ticks">
<title>Tick Increment</title>
<para>
Tick increments are recalculated for each plot, based on the data range, unless
set with <xref linkend="SetXTickIncrement"/>
or <xref linkend="SetYTickIncrement"/>.
'Data range' here refers to that set with <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/>,
or automatically calculated.
This differs from the way PHPlot handles the data range, which is not
recalculated by default after the first plot.
</para>
<para>
For overlay plots, if you want to use the same tick increments,
you should either set the desired tick increment (doing this for the first
plot is sufficient), or make sure the data ranges match.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-multiplot-grid">
<title>Grid Lines</title>
<para>
PHPlot defaults to drawing the dependent variable grid (usually Y), and the
grid lines will be drawn at tick positions.
As stated above, the tick positions by default will be recalculated for
each plot, using the calculated or explicitly set data range.
</para>
<para>
For overlay plots, you generally do not want to have more than one set of
grid lines in each of X and Y, or the results will be confusing.  Even if
your plot overlays have the same tick increments, avoid having the grid
lines drawn more than once. Otherwise, the grid lines for the second plot
will overlay the plotted data from the first plot.
You can turn off the grid lines with <literal>SetDrawXGrid(False)</literal>
and <literal>SetDrawYGrid(False)</literal>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-multiplot-legend">
<title>Legend Positioning</title>
<para>
Legend position with multiple plots works differently depending on whether
the position is defaulted or set, and if set what method was used.
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
If the legend position is defaulted, a legend will be drawn at the upper
right corner of each plot.
The same legend will be drawn in each position, unless the contents are
changed with <xref linkend="SetLegend"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
If the legend position is specified using device coordinates with
<xref linkend="SetLegendPixels"/>, or by using
<xref linkend="SetLegendPosition"/> (PHPlot-5.4.0 or later) with mode 'image'
or 'title', then the legend position is relative to the image.
The legend will be drawn at the specified position on the image,
once per plot, at the same location.
This repeated over-drawing is usually harmless,
but if you want to have it drawn only once,
either use <xref linkend="SetLegend"/> only before the last plot,
or use either <literal>SetLegend(NULL)</literal>
or <literal>SetLegend(array())</literal>
to cancel the legend after the first plot.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
If the legend position is specified using world coordinates with
<xref linkend="SetLegendWorld"/>, or by using
<xref linkend="SetLegendPosition"/> (PHPlot-5.4.0 or later) with mode 'world'
or 'plot', then the legend position is relative to the plot or the data
within the plot.
The legend will be drawn at the calculated position on each plot.
If using <xref linkend="SetLegendWorld"/>, or
<xref linkend="SetLegendPosition"/> with mode 'world', this assumes the
specified world coordinates are within the plot area for each plot.
As with the default positioning case, the same legend will be drawn for
each plot, unless the contents are changed with
<function>SetLegend()</function>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-multiplot-background">
<title>Plot Area Background</title>

<para>
If you set a plot area background color with <xref linkend="SetPlotBgColor"/>
and <xref linkend="SetDrawPlotAreaBackground"/>,
or if you set a plot area background image with
<xref linkend="SetPlotAreaBgImage"/>,
this will be applied to each plot until disabled.
This works well for side-by-side (tiled) plots, as each will get the same
background by default.
</para>

<para>
If you are overlaying multiple plots on an image, setting a plot area
background color or image for one plot will result in that background
hiding previous plots. Therefore, you need to set up the background for the
first plot, then turn it off it for the second plot.
If you previously set a plot area background image, you can disable it for
subsequent plots with <literal>SetPlotAreaBgImage(NULL)</literal>.
If you previously set and enabled a plot area background color, you can
disable it for subsequent plots with
<literal>SetDrawPlotAreaBackground(FALSE)</literal>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-multiplot-axis">
<title>Axis Positioning</title>
<para>
You can position the X and Y axis manually with
<xref linkend="SetXAxisPosition"/> and <xref linkend="SetYAxisPosition"/>,
or you can let PHPlot calculate the axis positions for you.
Whether you set the positions yourself, or let PHPlot calculate them for you,
those positions apply to subsequent plots unless overridden.
Even if you set a new data array, PHPlot will not recalculate the axis
positions unless told to.
</para>
<para>
If you want PHPlot to automatically re-calculate the X axis position for a
subsequent plot, use <literal>SetXAxisPosition()</literal> (with no
arguments), or <literal>SetXAxisPosition('')</literal>.
To restore automatic Y axis position calculation, use
<literal>SetYAxisPosition()</literal>
or <literal>SetYAxisPosition('')</literal>.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-multiplot-tiled">
<title>Summary - Tiled Multiple Plots</title>
<para>
Here are some guidelines for tiling multiple plots:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Unless all plots will use the same X and Y data ranges, use
<xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/> with each plot.
Call the function with no arguments to have PHPlot automatically calculate
the data range for the plot, or supply arguments to explicitly set a data range.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Use <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaPixels"/> to set the area within the image
for each plot. Remember to leave room for axis labels and titles.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
If you want a legend for each plot, use <xref linkend="SetLegendPixels"/>,
<xref linkend="SetLegendWorld"/>, or <xref linkend="SetLegendPosition"/>
to position it.
Or let the position default to the upper right corner of each plot.
If instead you want a single legend, for example outside all the plot areas,
either set it up for the last plot, or
set it up for any plot and cancel it for the next plot.
Position the single legend with <xref linkend="SetLegendPixels"/>,
or with <xref linkend="SetLegendPosition"/> using any mode except 'world'.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
You can only have one main title for the entire image.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-multiplot-overlay">
<title>Summary - Overlay Multiple Plots</title>
<para>
Here are some guidelines for overlaying multiple plots:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
All plots will use the same data scaling by default, whether automatically
calculated by PHPlot or set with <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/>.
Use <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/> if you want different data scaling
for subsequent plots.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
You can let PHPlot calculate the plot window by default, but it will not
account for additional margin space needed by plots after the first.
Instead, you can use <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaPixels"/> or
<xref linkend="SetMarginsPixels"/>
to set a specific plot area to use for all plots.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Set the tick increments you want for each plot, especially if the data
ranges differ. You can have two sets of tick marks and labels if you position
them on the opposite sides of the plot area.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draw grid lines, if you want them, only for the first plot, and turn them
off for the second plot.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
If you want a single legend, either set it up for the last plot, or
set it up for any plot and cancel it for the next plot.
If you want multiple legends, one per overlay, position them
manually with <xref linkend="SetLegendWorld"/>,
<xref linkend="SetLegendPixels"/>, or <xref linkend="SetLegendPosition"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
If you want a plot area background, you must set it for the first plot
and cancel it for the second plot, or it will hide the plots.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-multiplot-history">
<title>Multiple Plots - History</title>
<para>
A number of fixes were made in PHPlot-5.3.1 that affect multiple plots
per image. If you are creating multiple plot images using PHPlot-5.3.0 or
earlier, you should upgrade to the latest release. If you are unable to
upgrade, you may need to work around the following issues:

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Color allocation: In PHPlot-5.2.0 and PHPlot-5.3.0, the data color array
(whether defaulted or set with <xref linkend="SetDataColors"/>) was truncated
to the number of colors required for a plot.
This means that the additional colors were not available for subsequent plots,
so the data colors would repeat.
For example, if plot #1 used 3 colors for 3 data sets, and plot #2 had 5
data sets, only 3 colors were available and the first two colors would be
reused for the 4th and 5th data sets.
To work around this, you can reload the data colors before each subsequent plot.
To reload the default data colors, use
<literal>$plot->SetDataColors(False)</literal>.
Another work-around is to define a custom data color callback, which
turns off the color slot optimization.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Legend positioning using <xref linkend="SetLegendWorld"/> was not correctly
applied to subsequent plots in an image through PHPlot-5.3.0.
If you have multiple side-by-side plots and you want the legend in the same
world coordinate position in each plot, you still need to use
<literal>SetLegendWorld(..., ...)</literal> when creating each plot.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Through PHPlot-5.3.0, there was no way to reset the X axis position or Y
axis position to the default of automatic positioning.
That is, <literal>SetXAxisPosition()</literal>,
<literal>SetXAxisPosition('')</literal>,
<literal>SetYAxisPosition()</literal>,
and <literal>SetYAxisPosition('')</literal> did not work.
There is no work-around to get automatic positioning of the axis lines.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Through PHPlot-5.3.0, several functions had more restricted usage
when resetting to defaults.
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Use <literal>SetLegendPixels(NULL, NULL)</literal>
rather than <literal>SetLegendPixels()</literal>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Use <literal>SetNumXTicks('')</literal> and <literal>SetNumYTicks('')</literal>
rather than <literal>SetNumXTicks()</literal> and
<literal>SetNumYTicks()</literal>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Use <literal>SetLegend(array())</literal>
rather than <literal>SetLegend(NULL)</literal>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1> <!-- Multiple Plots -->

<sect1 id="adv-streaming">
<title>Streaming Plots</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This section contains information about producing streaming plots.
The end of this section contains a complete example.
  </para>
</abstract>

<para>
A script can use PHPlot to produce a series of plots that are streamed to a
browser or other viewing application. The result is a movie, or video,
consisting of a plot with changing data. This might be used to display
real-time data, to replay historical data, or for graphical display of
any data where adding a time dimension improves the presentation.
This feature was added in PHPlot-5.8.0.
</para>

<para>
This feature is intended for use when you want to update a plot one or more
times per second. If instead you want each plot to be displayed for one or
more seconds, consider using a refreshing page instead, for example
using using a "Refresh" meta-tag.
</para>

<warning>
  <para>
Producing streaming plots will place a significant load on your server.
See <xref linkend="adv-streaming-performance"/> below for more information.
  </para>
</warning>

<para>
PHPlot produces streaming plots using
<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motion_Jpeg">Motion JPEG</ulink>
(M-JPEG), specifically Streaming M-JPEG over HTTP.
This method (which is not a standard) sends a series of JPEG images,
with appropriate MIME headers, in a stream to the browser or viewer.
PHPlot produces each plot as usual, and sends it out as part of the stream.
Your script is responsible for changing the data (or other plot
elements) between frames, and for the overall frame timing.
</para>

<para>
Browsers and viewers which have been found to be capable of displaying
a Motion-JPEG Stream over HTTP include recent versions of:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Mozilla Firefox</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Mozilla Seamonkey</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>VLC Media Player</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
Note: Microsoft Internet Explorer is <emphasis>not</emphasis> able to
display these streams without an add-on.
Google Chrome and Apple Safari are reported to be capable of displaying these
streams, but they have not been tested with PHPlot.
</para>

<para>
Although only JPEG images are used in this section, the same method
works in theory for other image types such as PNG, and PHPlot does not
force the use of JPEG with streaming plots.  Mozilla Firefox and
Seamonkey have been found to be able to display "Motion-PNG" streams - a
sequence of PNG images using the same MIME structure as Motion-JPEG.
(VLC Media Player cannot display them.) Since plot images using JPEG
compression are of poorer quality than PNG images, you might want to
consider using another format such as PNG, however compatibility with
viewers is a bigger issue than with JPEG.
</para>

<sect2 id="adv-streaming-using">
<title>Streaming Plots - Creating Moving Plots</title>
<para>
There are generally 3 parts to a script that produces streaming plots:
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Creating a PHPlot object, and configuring your plot. This is the same as
for single image plots.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
You will need an incremental way to produce data for the plot. Typically,
it will produce one new row of a PHPlot data array for each plot frame.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Your script will have a loop that produces frames and includes frame timing.
(If your data is produced at fixed intervals, your loop may not need any
additional timing.) You may choose to produce a fixed number of frames (or
equivalently, run for a fixed length of time), or run forever. The user can
always end the stream by stopping their browser or viewer, and the script
will terminate on the server.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</para>

<para>
You will use these PHPlot functions to produce streaming plots, in addition
to the functions used for static plots.
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Use <xref linkend="SetPrintImage"/>(False) to disable automatic printing
from <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Use <xref linkend="SetFileFormat"/>('jpg') to select JPEG format. This is
the only format that is 'legal' with Motion-JPEG Streaming, although other
formats work with some browsers.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Call <xref linkend="StartStream"/> outside your main loop to begin the plot
stream.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Within your main loop, use <xref linkend="SetDataValues"/> to reload the
data array after addition the new row(s). This is necessary because PHPlot
creates a copy (rather than a reference) of your data.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Use <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> to produce the plot (but not output it).
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Still within your main loop, use <xref linkend="PrintImageFrame"/> to
output the plot as a single frame within the plot stream.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
If your plot stream ends at some point (rather than running until stopped
by the user), call <xref linkend="EndStream"/> to cleanly end the plot stream.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Your PHP script should be referenced from an HTML page using an
<literal>&lt;img&gt;</literal> tag, just like when creating a single plot.
The MIME type returned by PHPlot (<literal>multipart/x-mixed-replace</literal>
rather than <literal>image/jpeg</literal> for example) tells the browser or
viewer to expect a stream rather than a single image.
</para>

<para>
Be aware that PHP is usually configured to time out scripts that run too
long, and will terminate your streaming plot script. To prevent this, use
the PHP function <literal>set_time_limit($seconds)</literal>. If you know
the total number of frames and frame rate, you can set the timeout to a bit
more than the total expected runtime.
Alternatively, you can call <function>set_time_limit</function> within
your main loop, so it is called when each frame is produced. Because this
function resets the PHP timer, your script will not time out and can
produce frames forever.
</para>

<para>
For frame timing, you can use the PHP functions <function>microtime()</function>
and <function>time_sleep_until()</function>.
Call <literal>microtime(TRUE)</literal> once, to get a
precise timestamp as a floating point number. Then, within your main loop,
use <literal>time_sleep_until($timestamp)</literal> to put your script to 
sleep until the time to start of the next frame.
</para>

<note>
  <para>
Be sure your PHP script does not leak memory during the loop that produces
frames, especially if the script is designed to runs until stopped (rather
than producing a fixed number of frames). Appending to an array inside the
loop is an example of something to avoid.
  </para>
</note>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-streaming-performance">
<title>Streaming Plots - Performance Considerations</title>
<para>
This section discusses performance considerations for streaming plots,
starting with some definitions.
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Frame Rate</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
The number of plots (frames) produced per second.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Frame Time</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
The total time per frame, equal to the reciprocal of the frame rate.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Plot Time, Output Time, Idle Time</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
These are the 3 parts of the Frame Time. The Plot Time is the time it takes
to prepare your data for each frame and draw the plot graphics. The Output
Time is the time to send the completed plot to the browser or viewer.
Idle time is when your script is sleeping, waiting for the next frame's time
interval.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Frame Slippage, Missed Frames</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
If your script and processor cannot keep up with the plot stream requirements,
the idle time will drop to zero. Frame slippage is when the frame time exceeds
the desired goal, so the frame rate drops (but no frames are lost).
A different approach is to enforce the frame time and drop frames to catch
up, resulting in missed frames.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</para>

<para>
To produce a good plot stream, your script and server must be able to
consistently produce and output frames at the desired rate.
The frame rate you want will depend on your data and application, while the
rate you can achieve depends on the complexity of your script and your
available processing power. Although typical video runs at between 24 and
60 frames per second, those rates are likely too fast to be useful with plot
data.
A more realistic starting point for streaming plots is 10 frames per second.
This will provide the appearance of continuous motion of the graph(s),
but without too much blurring of the data.
</para>
<para>
Here are some real performance numbers, using a relatively simple plot, and
hardware that is old but was considered high performance when introduced
several year ago (circa 2007).
With a PHPlot script producing 10 frames per second, the Apache server
process was found to be using about 24% of one processor core's available
CPU time. (Keep in mind that this is not a short-term load, but means 24%
for the duration of the plot stream.) On the same hardware, 15 frames per
second used 35% CPU time, and 30 frames per second used 70% CPU time (of
one core).
</para>

<para>
You can measure the performance of your script with a small change, if you
are using a main loop like the one shown in the full example in the next
section (repeated briefly here).
  <programlisting><![CDATA[$timestamp = microtime(TRUE);
$frame_time = 1 / $frame_rate;
$slip = 0; // Number of slipped frames
$frame = 0; // Current frame number
while(1) {
    $frame++;
    ...
    $plot->DrawGraph();
    $plot->PrintImageFrame();
    if (!@time_sleep_until($timestamp += $frame_time)) $slip++;
}]]></programlisting>
The PHP function <function>time_sleep_until()</function> returns FALSE if the
desired time already passed. (We use @ to suppress the message which would
be logged in that case.) The variable $slip counts the number of slipped
frames.
The ratio of $slip to $frame should be as low as possible, ideally zero.
If <literal>($slip/$frame)</literal> gets too high, you may need to use a
lower frame rate, because either your frame rate is too high, your plot is
too complex, or your server is too slow to keep up.
However, optimizing your plot may help.
</para>

<para>
To optimize performance of your streaming plot, you should avoid these more
expensive features:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Plots that use area fills are slower. This especially includes pie charts
with shading (because PHPlot redraws the filled pie segments for each
level of shading). Area and stackedarea plots have a lot of area fill.
Bar charts have some area fill, with shaded bar charts having more shading
(but not nearly as much as shaded pie charts).
The fastest plot types are line plots.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
TrueType fonts are slower than GD fonts. Consider using text in the HTML
page containing the image reference, rather than in the image itself.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Some operations on truecolor images are slow (for example, gamma adjustment
or anti-aliasing) and should be avoided.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Avoid using a background image, especially one which needs to be scaled.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Avoid external factors that can affect performance. An obvious example is
database access, since a database server can take a variable amount of time
to respond to a query.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Note that PHPlot redraws the complete plot image for each frame, regardless
of which functions are used inside or outside your loop. For example, if
you use <xref linkend="SetTitle"/> to set title text outside the frame loop,
the same title will be drawn into each frame. If it is inside the loop,
you can change the text for each frame. Either way, the time to draw the title
counts for each frame. The same is true for legend, labels, etc.
Although you should keep invariant PHPlot "Set...()" function calls outside
your frame loop, this does not significantly affect the performance.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-streaming-example">
<title>Streaming Plots - Example</title>
<para>
This is a complete example that produces a streaming plot sequence showing
sin() and cos(). The frame rate and run time are set with variables at the
top.
</para>
<para>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
# Example of Streaming Plots with PHPlot
# This simply plots sin(x) and cos(x), updating at the rate given below.
# Replace the function next_row() to plot something else.
# This must run using a web server, not CLI.

require_once 'phplot.php';

# Configuration:
# This is the fixed number of points along the X axis:
$n_rows = 40;
# Data range for Y:
$max_y = 1;
$min_y = -1;
# Frames per second:
$frame_rate = 10;
# Total runtime in seconds. Use 0 to run 'forever':
$run_for = 0;

# Derived:
$run_forever = $run_for == 0;
$frame_time = 1 / $frame_rate;
$n_frames = $frame_rate * $run_for;

# Return the next data row (per PHPlot text-data data type):
function next_row($x)
{
    global $frame_rate;
    # Map 8 seconds of frames into 360 degrees (360/8 = 45 degrees/second)
    $theta = deg2rad(45 * $x / $frame_rate);
    return array('', sin($theta), cos($theta));
}

# Create an initial data array with no values. New values will be
# shifted in to the end. This is text-data format; the X values
# are implicit and ignored (not plotted).
for ($i = 0; $i < $n_rows; $i++) $data[$i] = array('', '', '');

# Create and configure the PHPlot object:
$plot = new PHPlot(640, 480);
$plot->SetDataType('text-data');
$plot->SetPlotType('lines');
$plot->SetFileFormat('jpg');
$plot->SetXTickLabelPos('none');
$plot->SetXTickPos('none');
$plot->SetXDataLabelPos('none');
# Don't draw the initial, empty values:
$plot->SetDrawBrokenLines(True);
# Force the Y range, or it will use the first frame to calculate:
$plot->SetPlotAreaWorld(NULL, $min_y, NULL, $max_y);
$plot->SetPrintImage(False);

# Main loop:
$plot->StartStream();
$timestamp = microtime(TRUE);
for ($frame = 0; $run_forever || $frame < $n_frames; $frame++) {
    # Set PHP timeout so it won't terminate the script early.
    set_time_limit(60);
    # Discard the oldest data row, and shift in the new row:
    array_shift($data);
    $data[] = next_row($frame);
    # Set a plot title that includes the frame number:
    $plot->SetTitle(sprintf("Moving Plot Test (Frame %4d)", $frame));
    # Reload the data array:
    $plot->SetDataValues($data);
    # Draw and output the plot:
    $plot->DrawGraph();
    $plot->PrintImageFrame();
    # Sleep until it is time to start the next frame:
    time_sleep_until($timestamp += $frame_time);
}
# End the stream:
$plot->EndStream();
]]></programlisting>
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1> <!-- Streaming Plots -->

<sect1 id="adv-imgmap">
<title>Image Maps for Plot Data</title>
<!-- Note: The text for this section on Image Maps is based on the text
     file Imagemaps.txt that was distributed with PHPlot-5.7.0.
     The 2 examples in that file can be found in the Examples chapter, in
     addition to the 3rd example which was quoted but not included in full.
-->
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This section describes the use of the <literal>data_points</literal>
callback to generate an HTML image map (or other similar construct) from
plot data.
An image map created using this callback will contain links from the
data points or shapes on the plot.
This feature was first added in PHPlot-5.7.0 as an experimental feature,
and was first documented in this Reference Manual with PHPlot-6.0.0.
  </para>
</abstract>

<note>
  <para>
    Use of callbacks is documented in <xref linkend="callbacks"/>.
  </para>
</note>

<para>
The <literal>data_points</literal> callback makes the
<link linkend="def-devcoor">device coordinates</link> of
plotted data available to a script using PHPlot.
If a script registers a function as a handler for the
<literal>data_points</literal> callback name, the function will be called
repeatedly when the plot is being generated.  Each call will contain
parameters describing the graphics for the corresponding data point.
These parameters can be used to create an HTML image map.
</para>

<para>
This feature is most likely only useful when generating embedded image data
with PHPlot.
(See <xref linkend="EncodeImage"/> for details on embedded image data.)
This is because HTML requires the image map be included in the
HTML page which contains the reference to the plot image.
The browser will first request the HTML page, then make a second request for
the image. Normally, the image is generated by a script using PHPlot, but
the image map has to be available before this script runs.
Using embedded image data allows a single PHP script to produce both the
image map and the image data, and return the result as a single page.
</para>

<para>
Nevertheless, it is also possible to create an image map with a non-embedded
image.  See <xref linkend="adv-imgmap-nonembed"/> for details.
</para>

<para>
The <literal>data_points</literal> callback works with the following plot
types:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
<link linkend="plottype-bars">bars</link> and
<link linkend="plottype-stackedbars">stackedbars</link>
(both horizontal and vertical)
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
<link linkend="plottype-boxes">boxes</link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
<link linkend="plottype-bubbles">bubbles</link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
<link linkend="plottype-ohlc">ohlc</link>,
<link linkend="plottype-candlesticks">candlesticks</link>, and
<link linkend="plottype-candlesticks2">candlesticks2</link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
<link linkend="plottype-pie">pie</link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
<link linkend="plottype-points">points</link> and
<link linkend="plottype-linepoints">linepoints</link>
(both standard and error bar plots)
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
No other plot type is supported. This includes lines, squared, thinbarline,
area, and stackedarea. (These plot types do not have well-defined areas
which could map to data points.)
</para>

<para>
The rest of this section contains details on the callback, usage with
each plot type, and additional information.
</para>

<sect2 id="adv-imgmap-usage">
<title>Image Maps - Usage</title>
<para>
To register a callback function to handle <literal>data_points</literal>, use:
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot->SetCallback('data_points', 'my_handler', $my_arg);
]]></programlisting>
Where <literal>my_handler</literal> is the name of your function,
<literal>$my_arg</literal> is an optional additional argument to pass
to your function.
</para>

<para>
The <literal>data_points</literal> callback function
(<function>my_handler()</function> above) will be called with 5
fixed-purpose arguments followed by variable arguments. The number and
purpose of the variable arguments depends on the plot type.  If your
handler only needs to work with one specific plot type, you can declare
these arguments in your function definition.
</para>

<para>
If your handler must handle multiple plot types, define your function without
arguments and use <function>func_get_arg()</function> or
<function>func_get_args()</function> to access the arguments.
You can use the value of the 3rd argument, <literal>$shape</literal>,
to determine the number and usage of the variable arguments, since there is
one specific function argument set for each value of <literal>$shape</literal>.
See <xref linkend="adv-imgmap-callback"/> for more information.
</para>

<para>
Here are the fixed arguments to the <literal>data_points</literal>
callback function, with this general declaration:
<programlisting><![CDATA[function my_handler($img, $passthru, $shape, $row, $column, ...)
]]></programlisting>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$img</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
The image resource (standard for all callbacks).
Not generally used with a <literal>data_points</literal> callback, which
cannot safely draw on the image (since PHPlot is in the middle of drawing
the plot on the same image).
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$passthru</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Pass-through argument, supplied in the <xref linkend="SetCallback"/>() call
(standard for all callbacks, referred to above as <literal>$my_arg</literal>).
You can use this however you want, or ignore it.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$shape</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
A word describing the shape of the area being described. This does not
necessarily correspond to an HTML image map &lt;area&gt; shape.
Each plot type passes a specific shape value, and the shape value defines
the usage of the variable arguments.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$row</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
The number of the data row being plotted. This typically corresponds
to the ordinal of the X axis values (Y for horizontal plots), starting
with 0 for the first point, 1 for the second point, etc.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$column</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
The column, or data set index, starting with 0 for the first data set.
This indicates which Y value for a given X, for example, or
which bar within a bar group, or segment within a stacked bar.
(For horizontal plots, this would indicate which X for a given Y.)
Always 0 for pie charts and OHLC plots, which only have a single data set.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>

<para>
For the variable arguments, refer to the sections below which describe each
plot type.
</para>

<sect3 id="adv-imgmap-bars">
<title>Image Maps from Bars and Stackedbars Plots</title>
<para>
With plot types <link linkend="plottype-bars">bars</link>
and <link linkend="plottype-stackedbars">stackedbars</link>,
an image map can be produced which indicates the area of each bar or stacked
bar segment. This works with both vertical and horizontal plots.
</para>
<para>
For bar and stackedbar plots, the <literal>data_points</literal> callback
has this form:
<programlisting><![CDATA[function my_handler($img, $passthru, $shape, $row, $column, $x1, $y1, $x2, $y2)
]]></programlisting>
The first 2 arguments are standard for all PHPlot callbacks and are not
described here. The next 3 arguments are common to all data_points
callbacks, and there are 4 additional arguments:
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$shape</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Always <literal>rect</literal>, indicating a rectangle shape.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$row</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
This is the bar group index.
The left-most bar group (for vertical bar charts) is row 0.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$column</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
This is the bar index within a group.  For vertical plot type 'bars', index 0
is the left-most in the group. For vertical plot type 'stackedbars', index 0
is the bar segment closest to the X axis.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$x1, $y1</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Device coordinates of the upper left corner of a bar or segment.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$x2, $y2</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Device coordinates of the lower right corner of a bar or segment.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>

<para>
Generating an image map for bar and stackedbar plots is straight-forward.
The provided <literal>$shape</literal> and coordinates are compatible with
HTML &lt;area&gt; markup.
You must provide the URL, alternate text, and optionally a title (tooltip text).
</para>

<para>
This example appends the image map line to a string.
sprintf() is used to convert the coordinates to integers for cleaner HTML.
<programlisting><![CDATA[$coords = sprintf("%d,%d,%d,%d", $x1, $y1, $x2, $y2);
$image_map .= "  <area shape=\"rect\" coords=\"$coords\""
          .. " title=\"$title_text\" alt=\"$alt_text\" href=\"$url\">\n";
]]></programlisting>
The <literal>$url</literal>, <literal>$title_text</literal>, and
<literal>$alt_text</literal> would typically depend on the passed
<literal>$row</literal> and <literal>$column</literal>.
</para>

<para>
Refer to <xref linkend="ex-imagemap-bars"/> for a complete example of an
image map for a bar chart.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-imgmap-boxes">
<title>Image Maps from Box Plots</title>
<para>
With plot type <link linkend="plottype-boxes">boxes</link>, an image map
can be produced which indicates the area of each data point.
This area is the bounding box which includes the box and both whiskers.
The bounding box does not include any outliers.
</para>

<para>
For box plots, the <literal>data_points</literal> callback
has this form:
<programlisting><![CDATA[function my_handler($img, $passthru, $shape, $row, $column, $x1, $y1, $x2, $y2)
]]></programlisting>
The first 2 arguments are standard for all PHPlot callbacks and are not
described here. The next 3 arguments are common to all data_points
callbacks, and there are 4 additional arguments:
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$shape</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Always <literal>rect</literal>, indicating a rectangle shape.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$row</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
The index of the data row, starting with 0 for the first X value.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$column</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
This is unused, and always 0.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$x1, $y1</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Device coordinates of the upper left corner.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$x2, $y2</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Device coordinates of the lower right corner.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
The upper left and lower right coordinates above refer to the bounding box
as described above.
</para>

<para>
Generating an image map for box plots is straight-forward.
The provided <literal>$shape</literal> and coordinates are compatible with
HTML &lt;area&gt; markup.
You must provide the URL, alternate text, and optionally a title (tooltip text).
</para>

<para>
This example appends the image map line to a string.
sprintf() is used to convert the coordinates to integers for cleaner HTML.
<programlisting><![CDATA[$coords = sprintf("%d,%d,%d,%d", $x1, $y1, $x2, $y2);
$image_map .= "  <area shape=\"rect\" coords=\"$coords\""
          .. " title=\"$title_text\" alt=\"$alt_text\" href=\"$url\">\n";
]]></programlisting>
The <literal>$url</literal>, <literal>$title_text</literal>, and
<literal>$alt_text</literal> would typically depend on the passed
<literal>$row</literal>.
</para>

<para>
<xref linkend="ex-imagemap-bars"/> contains a complete example of an
image map for a bar chart, and the parameters and usage for box plots are
the same except that the $col (column) parameter is always 0, since there
is only one data set.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-imgmap-bubble">
<title>Image Maps from Bubbles Plots</title>
<para>
With plot type <link linkend="plottype-bubbles">bubbles</link>,
an image map can be produced which indicates the area of each bubble.
</para>

<para>
For bubbles plots, the <literal>data_points</literal> callback
has this form:
<programlisting><![CDATA[function my_handler($img, $passthru, $shape, $row, $column, $x, $y, $diam)
]]></programlisting>
The first 2 arguments are standard for all PHPlot callbacks and are not
described here. The next 3 arguments are common to all data_points
callbacks, and there are 3 additional arguments:
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$shape</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Always <literal>circle</literal>, indicating a disk shape.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$row</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
The row is the index for the independent variable X.
The first X value has index 0.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$column</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
The column is the index for the dependent variable Y.
For the first (or only) dataset for each X, the column index is 0.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$x, $y</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Device coordinates of the center of the bubble.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$diam</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Diameter of the bubble, in pixels.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>

<para>
Generating an image map for bubble plots is straight-forward.
PHPlot provides parameters that are compatible with HTML image map markup,
except that PHPlot provides a diameter, and HTML requires the radius.
</para>

<para>
Here is an example of generating one area in an image map from a bubbles
plot. You must provide the URL, alternate text, and
optionally a title (tooltip text).  This appends the image map line to a
string.  sprintf() is used to convert the coordinates to integers for
cleaner HTML. 
<programlisting><![CDATA[$coords = sprintf("%d,%d,%d", $x, $y, $diam / 2);
$image_map .= "  <area shape=\"circle\" coords=\"$coords\""
            . " title=\"$title_text\" alt=\"$alt_text\" href=\"$url\">\n";
]]></programlisting>
The <literal>$url</literal>, <literal>$title_text</literal>, and
<literal>$alt_text</literal> would typically depend on the passed
<literal>$row</literal> and <literal>$column</literal>.
</para>

<para>
Other than the above code, a script to generate an image map for a bubbles
plot would be similar to <xref linkend="ex-imagemap-bars"/>, which produces
a bar chart.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-imgmap-ohlc">
<title>Image Maps from Financial OHLC Plots</title>
<para>
With plot types <link linkend="plottype-ohlc">ohlc</link>,
<link linkend="plottype-candlesticks">candlesticks</link>, and
<link linkend="plottype-candlesticks2">candlesticks2</link>
(collectively called OHLC - open, high, low, close plots),
an image map can be produced which indicates the area of each data point.
For candlesticks and candlesticks2 plots, this area is the bounding box
containing the candlestick and its wicks.
For ohlc plots, this area is the bounding box formed by the vertical line
and horizontal ticks.
</para>

<para>
For OHLC plots, the <literal>data_points</literal> callback
has this form:
<programlisting><![CDATA[function my_handler($img, $passthru, $shape, $row, $column, $x1, $y1, $x2, $y2)
]]></programlisting>
The first 2 arguments are standard for all PHPlot callbacks and are not
described here. The next 3 arguments are common to all data_points
callbacks, and there are 4 additional arguments:
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$shape</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Always <literal>rect</literal>, indicating a rectangle shape.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$row</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
The index of the data row, starting with 0 for the first X value.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$column</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
This is unused, and always 0.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$x1, $y1</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Device coordinates of the upper left corner.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$x2, $y2</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Device coordinates of the lower right corner.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
The upper left and lower right coordinates above refer to the bounding box
as described above.
</para>

<para>
Generating an image map for OHLC plots is straight-forward.
The provided <literal>$shape</literal> and coordinates are compatible with
HTML &lt;area&gt; markup.
You must provide the URL, alternate text, and optionally a title (tooltip text).
</para>

<para>
This example appends the image map line to a string.
sprintf() is used to convert the coordinates to integers for cleaner HTML.
<programlisting><![CDATA[$coords = sprintf("%d,%d,%d,%d", $x1, $y1, $x2, $y2);
$image_map .= "  <area shape=\"rect\" coords=\"$coords\""
          .. " title=\"$title_text\" alt=\"$alt_text\" href=\"$url\">\n";
]]></programlisting>
The <literal>$url</literal>, <literal>$title_text</literal>, and
<literal>$alt_text</literal> would typically depend on the passed
<literal>$row</literal>.
</para>

<para>
<xref linkend="ex-imagemap-bars"/> contains a complete example of an
image map for a bar chart, and the parameters and usage for OHLC plots are
the same except that the $col (column) parameter is always 0, since there
is only one data set.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-imgmap-pie">
<title>Image Maps from Pie Plots</title>
<para>
With plot type <link linkend="plottype-pie">pie</link>,
an image map can be produced which indicates the area of each pie segment.
However, PHPlot only supplies the values which identify the outline of the
pie segment, and HTML maps do not support areas of this shape.
Therefore, the callback handler function needs to generate
one or more polygons which approximate the pie segment area.
</para>

<note>
  <para>
PHPlot does not attempt to draw pie segments that are too small (due to
the implementation of the PHP/GD drawing function). If a segment's calculated
start angle and end angle are equal (after converting to integers), the
segment will not be drawn, and the data_points callback will not be called for
that segment.
  </para>
</note>

<para>
For pie charts, the <literal>data_points</literal> callback has this form:
<programlisting><![CDATA[function my_handler($img, $passthru, $shape, $row, $column, $x, $y,
                    $pie_width, $pie_height, $start_angle, $end_angle)
]]></programlisting>
The first 2 arguments are standard for all PHPlot callbacks and are not
described here. The next 3 arguments are common to all data_points
callbacks, and there are 6 additional arguments:
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$shape</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Always <literal>pie</literal>, indicating a pie segment of an ellipse.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$row</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
The pie segment index, starting at 0 for the first segment.
(By default, segments are drawn counter-clockwise from 0 degrees, but this
can be changed.)
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$column</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
This is unused, and always 0.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$x, $y</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Device coordinates of the center of the pie.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>$pie_width</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Horizontal diameter of the pie, in pixels.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$pie_height</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Vertical diameter of the pie, in pixels.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term>$start_angle</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Starting angle for the segment, in clockwise degrees (see note).
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$end_angle</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Ending angle for the segment, in clockwise degrees.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>
<note>
  <para>
<emphasis>clockwise degrees</emphasis> means (360 - A), where A is an angle
measured in the conventional sense: counter-clockwise from the X axis.
For example, a pie segment that starts at the top of the pie ('North') and
ends at the bottom point ('South') would have start_angle=270 and end_angle=90.
The start_angle is always greater than the end angle.
  </para>
</note>

<para>
Generating an image map for pie charts is more involved than with other
plot types.
Each pie segment is defined by the ellipse center point, the two diameter
values, and the start and end angles.
Due to the PHP/GD implementation, PHPlot uses clockwise angles (360-A), so
the start_angle is greater than the end_angle, and the segment is drawn
clockwise from the end_angle to the start_angle.
</para>

<para>
HTML image maps do not support ellipse section shapes directly.
Therefore, the callback function has to approximate the area using one or
more polygons.
</para>

<para>
The method shown in the example linked below approximates the pie segment
area using a polygon with one point at the pie center, one point at each
end of the arc, and zero or more points along the arc , such that the
maximum separation of points along the circumference is no more than 20
degrees. This has been found to produce a good fit for image maps.  More
details on the method can be found in the example.
</para>

<para>
Once you have your points (converted to integers, in an array
<literal>$points</literal> with X and Y values alternating), you can generate
a line in the image map as follows.
This example appends the image map line to a string.
<programlisting><![CDATA[$coords = implode(',', $points);
$image_map .= "  <area shape=\"poly\" coords=\"$coords\""
           .  " title=\"$title_text\" alt=\"$alt_text\" href=\"$url\">\n";
]]></programlisting>
The <literal>$url</literal>, <literal>$title_text</literal>, and
<literal>$alt_text</literal> would typically depend on the passed
<literal>$row</literal>.
</para>

<para>
Refer to <xref linkend="ex-imagemap-pie"/> for a complete example of an
image map for a pie chart.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="adv-imgmap-points">
<title>Image Maps from Points and Linepoints Plots</title>
<para>
With plot types <link linkend="plottype-points">points</link>
and <link linkend="plottype-linepoints">linepoints</link>,
an image map can be produced which indicates the area around each point.
The lines in a linepoints plot are not part of the image map areas.
This also works with error plots that use these plot types, however the
error bars are not part of the image map areas.
</para>

<para>
For points and linepoints plots, the <literal>data_points</literal> callback
has this form:
<programlisting><![CDATA[function my_handler($img, $passthru, $shape, $row, $column, $x, $y)
]]></programlisting>
The first 2 arguments are standard for all PHPlot callbacks and are not
described here. The next 3 arguments are common to all data_points
callbacks, and there are 2 additional arguments:
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$shape</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Always <literal>dot</literal>, indicating a single point.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$row</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
The row is the index for the independent variable X.
The first X value has index 0.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$column</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
The column is the index for the dependent variable Y.
For the first (or only) dataset for each X, the column index is 0.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>$x, $y</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
Device coordinates of the center of the point marker.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>

<para>
Generating an image map for points and linepoints plots is straight-forward.
PHPlot provides only the center coordinates for each point marker. It
does not indicate the shape or size of the marker, nor the coordinates of
any line segments or error bars. To generate an image map, you should use a
fixed radius size and define the image map areas as circles with that
radius centered around each data point. You need to choose a radius. A
larger radius provides a larger clickable area, but the area of adjacent
points may overlap.
</para>

<para>
Here is an example of generating one area in an image map from a points
or linepoints plot. You must provide the URL, alternate text, and
optionally a title (tooltip text).  This appends the image map line to a
string.  sprintf() is used to convert the coordinates to integers for
cleaner HTML.  This example uses a 20 pixel radius for the areas around
each data point.
<programlisting><![CDATA[define('MAP_RADIUS', 20); // Capture area circle radii
$coords = sprintf("%d,%d,%d", $x, $y, MAP_RADIUS);
$image_map .= "  <area shape=\"circle\" coords=\"$coords\""
           . " title=\"$title_text\" alt=\"$alt_text\" href=\"$url\">\n";
]]></programlisting>
The <literal>$url</literal>, <literal>$title_text</literal>, and
<literal>$alt_text</literal> would typically depend on the passed
<literal>$row</literal> and <literal>$column</literal>.
</para>

<para>
Other than the above code, a script to generate an image map for a points or
linepoints plot would be similar to <xref linkend="ex-imagemap-bars"/>, which
produces a bar chart.
</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-imgmap-callback">
<title>Image Maps - data_points Callback Parameter Summary</title>
<para>
The following table contains a summary of the <literal>data_points</literal>
callback parameters for each supported plot type.

<!-- Editor's note: In the first column, each cell spans 2 rows. -->
<informaltable>
  <tgroup cols="2">
    <?dbhtml table-summary="data_points callback parameter summary"?>
    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="20*" />
    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="80*" />
    <thead>
      <row>
        <entry>Plot Type(s)</entry>
        <entry>Callback Parameters / Notes</entry>
      </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>

      <row>
        <entry morerows="1">bars, stackedbars </entry>
        <entry>$img, $passthru, $shape='rect', $row, $column, $x1, $y1, $x2, $y2</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>
          Image map area does not include shading.
        </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry morerows="1">boxes</entry>
        <entry>$img, $passthru, $shape='rect', $row, 0, $x1, $y1, $x2, $y2</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>
          Rectangle shape includes box and whiskers. It does not include
          any outliers.
        </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry morerows="1">bubbles</entry>
        <entry>$img, $passthru, $shape='circle', $row, $column, $x, $y, $diam</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>
          x,y is center. Use diam/2 for radius in image map circle area.
        </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry morerows="1">candlesticks, candlesticks, ohlc</entry>
        <entry>$img, $passthru, $shape='rect', $row, 0, $x1, $y1, $x2, $y2</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>
          Rectangle shape includes body, wicks, ticks of each candlestick
          or OHLC marker.
        </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry morerows="1">pie</entry>
        <entry>$img, $passthru, $shape='pie', $row, 0, $x, $y, $width, $height, $start_angle, $end_angle</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>
          Callback needs to fit a polygon to the ellipse segment.
        </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry morerows="1">points, linepoints</entry>
        <entry>$img, $passthru, $shape='dot', $row, $column, $x, $y</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>
          x,y is center. Supply a radius for image map circle areas.
          Image map area will cover the points only, not lines.
        </entry>
      </row>

    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</informaltable>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-imgmap-impl-notes">
<title>Image Maps - Implementation Notes and Limitations</title>
<para>
Since most PHPlot scripts will not produce image maps, the burden of
converting data points into a format for HTML image maps was left to the
implementation in the callback function. This is why PHPlot passes the
diameter values it already calculated (instead of radius values), and why
pie chart segments must be interpolated by the callback function.
</para>

<para>
You can generate image maps for error plots (data types
<link linkend="data-data-error">data-data-error</link> and
<link linkend="data-data-yx-error">data-data-yx-error</link>)
with points and linepoints plot types, but the image map areas will not
include the error bars. For these plot types, the only the coordinates of
the data points are provided.
</para>

<para>
PHPlot does not provide the data values from the data array that go with
the points. If you need these values, for example in tooltips, your callback
function needs to get them from the data array, using the $row and $column
index values. This may be complex for pie charts (for example, if you want
tooltip text to show the percentage value of the pie segment).
<xref linkend="ex-imagemap-pie"/> shows access to data values for a pie
chart in the simple case of data type <literal>text-data-single</literal>.
<xref linkend="ex-imagemap-nonembed"/> shows access to data values for a
bar chart.
</para>

<para>
For OHLC plots (candlesticks, candlesticks2, and ohlc plot types), and
for box plots,
PHPlot does not provide the callback with the coordinates of individual
features (such as the candlestick body rather than the high point wick).
PHPlot only provides the bounding box rectangle for the overall data point
graphic.
</para>

<para>
The image map must be located in the same HTML file as the image reference.
Although the HTML definition of the <literal>usemap</literal> attribute
of the <literal>&lt;img&gt;</literal> tag seems to indicate that a URL to an
external file containing the map may be used, this does not in fact work.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-imgmap-nonembed">
<title>Image Maps with Non-embedded Image Data</title>
<para>
It is also possible to generate an image map when the PHPlot script
produces an image in the normal way (not embedded) and returns it to the
browser as image data.  But the script will need to run twice: once to
generate the PHPlot image, and once to generate the containing HTML page
with the image map.  (You can use two separate scripts instead, but this is
not recommended, since both operations must create identical plots so the
image map areas correspond to the plot areas.)
</para>

<para>
In the following example, the script normally generates an HTML page. The page
contains an image map, generated with PHPlot, and also a
<literal>&lt;img&gt;</literal> image tag which points back to the same script
to have it generate the plot image.
When requesting the image, the script adds a parameter 'mode=plot' to the
URL. This tells the second execution of the script to generate the image
data instead of the HTML page.
</para>

<para>
The obvious drawback to this method is that you are processing a complete
plot twice each time a plot is needed. The first time, only the image map
is needed, and the plot itself is discarded. This is inefficient, especially
if the plotting script needs to query a database or perform extensive
calculations.
</para>

<para>
Another concern is if the script queries a database, the data could change
between the two uses of the script, resulting in an image map and plot
which do not correlate.
</para>

<para>
The rest of this section contains selected, annotated code from
<xref linkend="ex-imagemap-nonembed"/>.
</para>

<para>
Start by checking for the mode parameter:
<programlisting><![CDATA[# Produce an image if the URL has mode=plot, and an HTML page otherwise:
$do_html = empty($_GET['mode']) || $_GET['mode'] != 'plot';
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
The callback handler is the same as the other imagemap examples, in that it
appends to the global string $image_map one line from the image map.
<programlisting><![CDATA[# Callback for 'data_points' : Generate 1 line in the image map.
function store_map($im, $data, $shape, $row, $col, $x1, $y1, $x2, $y2)
{ ... }
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
The <function>generate_html()</function> function creates the containing
HTML page. Only parts of the code are shown.
<programlisting><![CDATA[function generate_html()
{
    global $image_map;
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
Create a self-referencing URL with mode=plot parameter for the
<literal>&lt;img&gt;</literal> tag:
<programlisting><![CDATA[    # If the URL already has parameters, use & separator, else ?.
    $sep = empty($_SERVER['QUERY_STRING']) ? '?' : '&';
    $url = htmlspecialchars($_SERVER['REQUEST_URI'] . $sep .  'mode=plot');
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
Now generate the HTML page. Include the image map using the global string
<literal>$image_map</literal>, which our callback function has
built line-by-line as PHPlot produced the plot.
Also include the reference to the plot image. This will result in the browser
making a second request to the script, this time with the mode=plot parameter.
<programlisting><![CDATA[    echo <<<END
<!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD HTML 4.01 Transitional//EN"
     "http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/loose.dtd">
<html>
...
<map name="map1">
$image_map
</map>
...
<img src="$url" alt="Plot image" usemap="#map1">
...
</html>

END;
}
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
This ends the <function>generate_html()</function> function.
</para>

<para>
In the main body of the script, create a PHPlot object and configure the
plot as usual.  Set the <literal>data_points</literal> callback. (You need only
do this in the case of generating HTML, not the image case.)
There are two other places where the operation differs for the HTML or image
generation, based on the <literal>$do_html</literal> flag: disabling automatic
output with <xref linkend="SetPrintImage"/>, and calling
the <function>generate_html()</function> function at the end.
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot = new PHPlot(800, 600);
if ($do_html) {
    // Do not output the image in this mode:
    $plot->SetPrintImage(False);
    // Set the callback for image map generation:
    $plot->SetCallback('data_points', 'store_map');
}
... // Set up the plot, data values, plot type, etc.
// Output the image (in plot mode), or build the image map (in html mode):
$plot->DrawGraph();
if ($do_html) generate_html();
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
That's all. If <literal>$do_html</literal> is true, no image will be produced
(due to <literal>SetPrintImage(False)</literal>),
and <function>generate_html()</function> will be called.
If <literal>$do_html</literal> is false, <function>DrawGraph()</function>
will output the plot image, and the map data will be not be produced or output.
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1> <!-- Image Maps -->

</chapter>
