<!-- $Id$
     Developer's Guide chapter for PHPlot Reference Manual
-->
<part label="III" id="part3">
<title>Developer's Guide to PHPlot</title>
<partintro id="developer">
  <abstract><title></title>
    <para>
This part of the PHPlot manual is about PHPlot internals, and various
technical details which are of interest mostly to developers of PHPlot
itself.
    </para>
  </abstract>
</partintro>

<chapter id="dev-layout">
<title>PHPlot Plot Layout</title>
<para>
This figure illustrates the plot layout, starting with PHPlot-5.0.5 when
the margin calculations were rewritten.
Use the following notes to help understand the figure.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
A vertical plot is shown. The X and Y coordinate system is the same for
horizontal plots, but the roles are reversed: Y is the independent
variable, and X is the dependent variable.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
The safe_margin (box with X) is a gap of 5 pixels used to separate elements.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
The main title, X titles, and Y titles are optional. If these titles are
not set, the space allocated to them collapses, including the safe_margin
gap. This is shown in the figure with an arrow.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Similarly, the X tick labels, X axis data labels (for vertical plots),
Y tick labels, and Y axis data labels (for horizontal plots) are optional.
If these labels are not used, the space allocated to them collapses,
including the safe_margin.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
For vertical plots, X axis data labels and X tick labels occupy the same space.
For horizontal plots, Y axis data labels and Y tick labels occupy the same space.
Normally only one of these should be present; if both are on for some reason
they will overlay.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
The base_margin (pink box with plus sign) is the space between the image edge
and the outermost graphics or text. If there is no image border, or the
image border is no wider than 2 pixels (which is always the case through
PHPlot-5.1.1), then the base_margin is set to the same as the safe_margin
value (5 pixels). A wider image border increases the base_margin; for example
an 8 pixel image border results in a base_margin of 11 pixels.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
The top, left, right, and bottom margins consist of base_margin plus
whatever space is needed for titles and ticks.  There is a minimum value
for these margins - 2 times safe_margin plus base_margin.  Even if there
are no titles at all on a side, the margin on that side will be no less
than this minimum margin. This keeps the axis or plot area edge from coming
too close to the image edge.
The calculated plot area margins shown can be overridden by using
<xref linkend="SetPlotAreaPixels"/> or <xref linkend="SetMarginsPixels"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
The main title is positioned relative to the top of the image.
Starting with PHPlot-5.0.5, the X and Y titles are positioned relative
to the plot area. 
PHPlot-5.0.4 and earlier positioned the X and Y titles
relative to the image edges.
The difference should not be visible with automatic margins, but if the
margins are set larger, or the plot area smaller, then the X and Y titles
will move inwards with the newer releases.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
It is possible to position X ticks and X tick labels to
<literal>xaxis</literal>, and Y ticks and Y tick labels to
<literal>yaxis</literal>, so the ticks and/or labels will
float to the axis positions rather than always appear on the edges of the
plot area. Space will be allocated for the corresponding margin only if the
axis happens to fall exactly at the data limits for that side. This may
cause problems if the axis is close but not quite at the edge; no margin
space will be allocated on that side for the labels, and the labels may
overlap the title or fall off the edge of the image.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/layout.png" scale="58" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
      <phrase>PHPlot plot layout figure</phrase>
    </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
</informalfigure>

</chapter>

<chapter id="dev-legend">
<title>PHPlot Legend Layout</title>
<para>
This figure illustrates the layout of the legend, as drawn by
<xref linkend="DrawLegend"/>.
Two of six possible arrangements of the color boxes and text are shown.
See <xref linkend="SetLegendStyle"/> for more information.
</para>
<para>
Through PHPlot-5.2.0, the width of the color boxes was always
<varname>char_w</varname>, the width of one character (or the width of the
upper case letter "E") in the legend text font.
Starting with PHPlot-5.3.0, this can be adjusted using a class variable.
See <xref linkend="adv-tuning-legend"/> for more.
</para>
<para>
If point shapes are used in the legend instead of color boxes
(see <xref linkend="SetLegendUseShapes"/>, added in PHPlot-5.4.0),
the same amount of space is still allocated, including width adjustment.
But the point shape itself is always drawn at the same size as in
the plot, regardless of the width adjustment factor.  If the plot area has
a color background, the width adjustment will stretch the box in that color
which is drawn behind the point shape.
</para>

<para>
If line markers are used in the legend instead of color boxes (see
<xref linkend="SetLegendUseShapes"/>, added in PHPlot-6.0.0 for line plots),
the width of the area reserved for color boxes is scaled by 4
(along with any 'tuning' adjustment).
This leaves enough room to draw a line segment that can be identified
visually by color and width.
</para>

<para>
<informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/legend-layout.png" scale="75" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
      <phrase>PHPlot legend layout figure</phrase>
    </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
</informalfigure>
</para>

</chapter>

<chapter id="dev-internal">
<title>PHPlot Class Internal Functions</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This chapter documents PHPlot internal functions. These functions are
intended to be used only by PHPlot itself.
  </para>
</abstract>

<note>
  <para>
Starting with PHPlot-5.1.0, most of the internal functions are declared as
<literal>protected</literal>, which limits their visibility to other member
functions and inherited or parent classes. Some internal functions are
still <literal>public</literal>, usually because they are needed for
testing PHPlot. However, all functions documented in this chapter should be
treated as private, for use only by PHPlot. If you feel you have a need to
use one of these functions from outside PHPlot (or an inherited class),
please report this via the available PHPlot support mechanisms.
  </para>
</note>

<!-- Original material is from "PHPlot Internal Functions" included with
   pre-5.0rc3 releases of PHPlot, but extensively edited.
   All functions in phplot.php should either be documented in "reference"
   (if 'public') or here (if 'private').

   This string and the REMOVED tags are used to help maintain the document:
   BEGIN INTERNAL FUNCTIONS
-->

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="array_merge_php4" xreflabel="array_merge_php4"/>array_merge_php4($array1,$array2)</term> <!-- REMOVED -->
  <listitem>
    <para>
This non-member function was removed at PHPlot-5.0.4.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="array_pad_array" xreflabel="array_pad_array"/>array_pad_array(&amp;$arr, $size, $arr2=NULL)</term> <!-- REMOVED -->
  <listitem>
    <para>
This non-member function was removed at PHPlot-5.0.4 and replaced with
the class member function <xref linkend="pad_array"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcAxisPositions" xreflabel="CalcAxisPositions"/>CalcAxisPositions()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates the X and Y axis positions in world coordinates. These can be
supplied by the user, in which case they are only changed if they are
outside the data range. If axis positions are not supplied by the user, 
CalcAxisPositions applies defaults as described in
<xref linkend="SetXAxisPosition"/> and <xref linkend="SetYAxisPosition"/>.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>.
Note: This code was moved out of CalcTranslation at PHPlot-5.0.5.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcBarWidths" xreflabel="CalcBarWidths"/>CalcBarWidths($stacked, $verticals)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates values for <literal>bars</literal> and <literal>stackedbars</literal>
plot types.
It calculates the width of the bars and the margins around and between them.
An argument was added in PHPlot-5.1.2 to support horizontal plots.
Arguments were changed in PHPlot-5.3.0 to explicitly select stacked or
grouped bars, and vertical or horizontal plots.
This is called by the bar chart drawing functions
<xref linkend="DrawBars"/>, <xref linkend="DrawStackedBars"/>,
<xref linkend="DrawHorizBars"/>, and <xref linkend="DrawHorizStackedBars"/>.
(Through PHPlot-5.1.2 this was called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> before a
bars or stackedbars plot.)
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcGridSettings" xreflabel="CalcGridSettings"/>CalcGridSettings()</term> <!-- REMOVED -->
  <listitem>
    <para>
This function was removed at PHPlot-6.0.0. It applied the defaults to the X
and Y grid flags. PHPlot now uses <xref linkend="GetGridSetting"/> instead.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcMargins" xreflabel="CalcMargins"/>CalcMargins($maximize)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates the size of the four margins around the plot area:
x_left_margin, x_right_margin, y_top_margin, and y_bot_margin.
It does this by trying to determine how much space is needed for titles,
labels, and tick marks.
Starting with PHPlot-5.0.5, this is only called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>,
and it also calculates position offsets for titles and labels. It is called
even in case of a user-supplied plot area (SetPlotAreaPixels or
SetMarginsPixels was used). If the $maximize argument is true, then the
plot area does not leave room for X or Y axis, labels, or titles; this is
used for pie charts.
    </para>
    <para>
Through PHPlot-5.0.6, all 4 margins are either user-defined or all 4 are
automatically calculated. Starting with PHPlot-5.0.7, the 4 margins can be
independently set or defaulted to automatic. CalcMargins calculates values
for all 4 margins, but only saves those that have not been set using either
<xref linkend="SetMarginsPixels"/> or <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaPixels"/>.
Note that other than the overall plot title, elements are drawn relative to
the plot area, which is calculated based on the actual margins. If the top
margin is increased, for example, the plot title stays at the top of the
image, but top tick marks and labels move down against the graph.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcMaxDataLabelSize" xreflabel="CalcMaxDataLabelSize"/>CalcMaxDataLabelSize($which = 'x')</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates the size of the biggest X or Y data label.
For 'x' it returns the height along the Y axis of the tallest data label.
For 'y' it returns the width along the sides of the widest data label.
This is used to allocate space for margins.
This was added to PHPlot-5.0.5.
The argument supporting Y label width was added in PHPlot-5.1.2.
Called by <xref linkend="CalcMargins"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcMaxTickLabelSize" xreflabel="CalcMaxTickLabelSize"/>CalcMaxTickLabelSize($which)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates the size of the biggest tick label. The $which argument is 'x'
or 'y' to indicate which labels to work with. For 'x', it returns the
height along the Y axis; for 'y' it returns the width along the X axis.
This is used to allocate space for margins.
This was added to PHPlot-5.0.5.
Calls <xref linkend="CalcTicks"/> to determine the tick value parameters.
Called by <xref linkend="CalcMargins"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcPlotAreaPixels" xreflabel="CalcPlotAreaPixels"/>CalcPlotAreaPixels()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates the pixel coordinates of the plot area.
This was added to PHPlot-5.0.5 by moving the parts of the calculations out of
SetPlotAreaPixels and SetMarginsPixels. Those two functions now simply
record their arguments, and make no attempt to calculate any parameters.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>, after <xref linkend="CalcMargins"/>
is used to calculate margins.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcPlotAreaWorld" xreflabel="CalcPlotAreaWorld"/>CalcPlotAreaWorld()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates the world coordinate limits of the plot area.
This was added to PHPlot-5.0.5 by moving the calculations out of
<xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/>.
Starting with PHPlot-6.0.0, it just calls <xref linkend="CalcPlotRange"/>
twice, once for X and once for Y.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>, after <xref linkend="FindDataLimits"/>
is used to examine the data array values.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcPlotRange" xreflabel="CalcPlotRange"/>CalcPlotRange($which)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates the plot range and tick increment. $which is 'x' or 'y', to
calculate values for the X or Y axis.
Specified values (e.g. with <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/>
or <xref linkend="SetXTickIncrement"/>) are used if set. Otherwise, values
are calculated heuristically.
Returns an array of 3 calculated values: tick_increment, plot_min, and plot_max.
This was added in PHPlot-6.0.0.
Calls <xref linkend="CalcStep"/> if necessary to calculate the tick
increment. (If either the tick increment or number of ticks has been set,
then CalcPlotRange uses those instead of calling CalcStep).
Called by <xref linkend="CalcPlotAreaWorld"/>, once for X and once for Y.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcRangeInit" xreflabel="CalcRangeInit"/>CalcRangeInit(&amp;$plot_limit, $implied, $min_flag, $data_limit, &amp;$adjust_flag)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates the initial values for the plot range ends.
$plot_limit is one end (min or max) of a plot range. It is passed as a
reference because it might be unset. Unset, NULL, or an empty string means
this end of the range has not been set and needs to be calculated.
$implied is true when the data type does not specify the value (for
example, the X value in text-data data type).
$min_flag is TRUE for the low end of a range; this affects the range end
for the $implied case only.
$data_limit is the actual data limit (min or max) at this end of the range;
given no other information this is the initial guess for the plot range limit.
Returns the initial value for the plot limit value, and sets the
$adjust_flag to TRUE if that needs further adjustments.
    </para>
    <para>
This was added in PHPlot-6.0.0.
Called by <xref linkend="CalcPlotRange"/> 4 times, once for each end of the X
and Y ranges.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcStep" xreflabel="CalcStep"/>CalcStep($which, $range)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates an appropriate tick increment.
$which is 'x' or 'y', and selects configuration variables for that axis.
$range is the plot area range (max - min).
Returns the calculated tick increment.
    </para>
    <para>
This function is not called if the user has set a tick increment
(<xref linkend="SetXTickIncrement"/>, <xref linkend="SetYTickIncrement"/>)
or the number of tick marks
(<xref linkend="SetNumXTicks"/>, <xref linkend="SetNumYTicks"/>).
This function calls either <xref linkend="CalcStep125"/>,
<xref linkend="CalcStepBinary"/>, or <xref linkend="CalcStepDatetime"/>
to calculate an appropriate value, depending on the tick increment mode.
This was added in PHPlot-6.0.0.
Called by <xref linkend="CalcPlotRange"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcStep125" xreflabel="CalcStep125"/>CalcStep125($range, $min_ticks)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates an appropriate tick increment in 'decimal' mode. This is the
default mode.
$range is the plot area range (max - min).
$min_ticks is the minimum number of tick intervals to produce.
Returns the calculated tick increment.
The algorithm produces the largest tick increment that is a power of 10
times 1, 2, or 5, and divides the plot area range $range into no fewer than
$min_ticks intervals.
This was added in PHPlot-6.0.0.
Called by <xref linkend="CalcStep"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcStepBinary" xreflabel="CalcStepBinary"/>CalcStepBinary($range, $min_ticks)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates an appropriate tick increment in 'binary' (power of 2) mode.
$range is the plot area range (max - min).
$min_ticks is the minimum number of tick intervals to produce.
Returns the calculated tick increment.
The algorithm produces the largest tick increment that is a power of 2
and divides the plot area range $range into no fewer than $min_ticks intervals.
This was added in PHPlot-6.0.0.
Called by <xref linkend="CalcStep"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcStepDatetime"
xreflabel="CalcStepDatetime"/>CalcStepDatetime($range, $min_ticks)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates an appropriate tick increment in 'date' mode.
This is for when the values along the axis represent date/time values.
$range is the plot area range (max - min), in seconds.
$min_ticks is the minimum number of tick intervals to produce.
Returns the calculated tick increment.
The function contains a list of acceptable intervals between 1 second and 1
week, and returns one of those if possible - the largest value that divides
the plot area range $range into no fewer than $min_ticks intervals.  If the
range is too large (would produce too many ticks with an increment of 1
week), the function falls back to using <xref linkend="CalcStep125"/> with
units of 1 day.
This was added in PHPlot-6.0.0.
Called by <xref linkend="CalcStep"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcTicks" xreflabel="CalcTicks"/>CalcTicks($which)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Gets the tick parameters. $which is 'x' or 'y'. Returns an array of 3
values: start, end, and interval.
This was added to PHPlot-5.0.5, although still using the method
of just dividing the interval by 10 if there is no user-supplied interval
or tick count.
Starting with PHPlot-5.4.0, it also accounts for a tick anchor value, by
shifting the start value as needed.
Starting in PHPlot-6.0.0, it no longer calculates the tick increment, but
simply uses the values calculated by <xref linkend="CalcPlotRange"/>.
Called by <xref linkend="CalcMaxTickLabelSize"/>,
<xref linkend="DrawYTicks"/>, and <xref linkend="DrawXTicks"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CalcTranslation" xreflabel="CalcTranslation"/>CalcTranslation()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates the parameters for transforming world to pixel coordinates.
This function calculates the scale (xscale, yscale) and origin
(plot_origin_x, plot_origin_y) for X and Y translations, which
are used by the xtr() and ytr() functions.
Starting with PHPlot-5.0.5, this is only called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>,
as nothing else uses the parameters until the graph is ready to be drawn.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CheckDataArray" xreflabel="CheckDataArray"/>CheckDataArray()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Checks that there is a valid data array for the plot, and calculates values
that depend on the data type.
Called very early by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>.
This was added in PHPlot-5.1.3, moving the checking out of DrawGraph
and adding the data_columns calculation.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CheckDataType" xreflabel="CheckDataType"/>CheckDataType($valid_types)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Used to validate the data_type for a plot_type. This works like a specialized
version of <xref linkend="CheckOption"/>.  $valid_types contains the valid
data type(s) for the current plot_type, separated by a comma and space if more
than one is supported. If the current data_type is in the list, returns TRUE,
else produces an error.  This was added in PHPlot-5.1.2 to unify the way
the plot drawing functions check the data type.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CheckDataValueLabels" xreflabel="CheckDataValueLabels"/>CheckDataValueLabels($label_control, &amp;$dvl)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Checks to see if data value labels should be drawn, based on $label_control
(which is always <literal>$this->y_data_label_pos</literal>, since only
vertical plot functions currently use this).
Returns FALSE if the labels are off, else returns TRUE and sets 4 variables
in the $dvl array. This array is used by <xref linkend="DrawDataValueLabel"/>
to position the label. The array contains these keys: x_offset, y_offset :
device coordinate (pixel) offsets for the label; h_align, v_align :
text alignment.
Called by plot type drawing functions such as <xref linkend="DrawDots"/>
which do data value labels, other than bars and stackedbars.
This was added in PHPlot-5.3.0.
Through PHPlot-5.7.0, four separate reference arguments were used for the
return values, instead of an array.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CheckLabels" xreflabel="CheckLabels"/>CheckLabels()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Fixes up the data and tick label position, angle, and format settings.
This applies defaults to data label and tick label positions but avoids
having them overlap unless the user deliberately positioned them that way.
Also sets the default angle for X data labels, and the default formatting
for X and Y data labels, to match the corresponding settings for tick
labels if they were not already set.
This is for compatibility with PHPlot-5.0.7 and earlier, when there was only
one control for both types of labels.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> before calculating margins with
<xref linkend="CalcMargins"/>.
This was added in PHPlot-5.1.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CheckLabelsAllEmpty" xreflabel="CheckLabelsAllEmpty"/>CheckLabelsAllEmpty()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Returns TRUE if all of the labels in the data array are empty strings.
This is used by <xref linkend="CheckLabels"/> to determine whether tick or
axis data labels should default on if both are left off.
This was added in PHPlot-5.1.2.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CheckOption" xreflabel="CheckOption"/>CheckOption($which_opt, $which_acc, $which_func)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Checks the validity of an option passed to a PHPlot member function.
$which_opt is the string to check, and $which_acc is a string of acceptable
choices (with a comma and then a space between choices).
If the string to check is not found in the string of acceptable choices, a
fatal error will be reported using <xref linkend="PrintError"/>.
The error message will include $which_func which should
be the name of the calling function (using the PHP __FUNCTION__ magic constant).
Note that this is used to catch programming errors, not run-time or user errors.
If the string to check is acceptable, it is returned down-cased and trimmed
of leading and trailing spaces.
Note: At PHPlot-5.0.5, this function was changed to require exactly ', '
(comma space) between acceptable choices, and reject empty strings for
$which_opt and disallow partial matches.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CheckOptionArray" xreflabel="CheckOptionArray"/>CheckOptionArray($opt, $acc, $func)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Checks the validity of an option argument passed to a PHPlot member function
that can accept its argument as either a string or an array of strings.
$opt is the string or array to check, and $acc is a string of acceptable
choices (with a comma and then a space between choices).
If the $opt argument is supplied as a string, it is first converted to an
array with one element. Then the elements of the array are each checked
for validity. If any element of the array of strings to check is not
found in the string of acceptable choices, a fatal error will be reported
using <xref linkend="PrintError"/>.  The error message will include $func
which should be the name of the calling function (using the PHP
__FUNCTION__ magic constant).  Note that this is used to catch programming
errors, not run-time or user errors.  If all of the array elements to check
are acceptable, the array is returned with each element down-cased and
trimmed of leading and trailing spaces.  Note that an array is always
returned, even if the opt argument is a string.
This was added in PHPlot-5.1.2.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CheckPieLabels" xreflabel="CheckPieLabels"/>CheckPieLabels()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Sets up the default pie chart label type and format. The default is percentage
labels formatted as 'data' (fixed-point). The default cannot be statically
defined, for compatibility with previous releases which used the Y label
precision (if set), else 1 digit if <xref linkend="SetPrecisionY"/>
was never called.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawPieChart"/>.
This was added in PHPlot-5.6.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CheckPlotRange"
xreflabel="CheckPlotRange"/>CheckPlotRange($which, &amp;$plot_min, &amp;$plot_max, $adjust_min, $adjust_max)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Ensures that the X or Y plot range is positive.  This is necessary because the
plot range and tick increment calculations, as well as the overall plotting
functions, cannot handle zero or negative ranges.
A bad range can happen as a result of 'flat' or missing data (all Y values
the same, for example), or if <xref linkend="SetPlotAreaWorld"/> is used to
set one end of the data range, and the actual data is on the wrong side of
that limit. (<function>SetPlotAreaWorld</function> itself defends against
setting both ends of a range such that min >= max).
PHPlot will never adjust user-set plot limits, but it will adjust its own
calculated limits to force a positive range (even if the resulting plot may
not be useful).
    </para>
    <para>
$which is 'x' or 'y' (this is only used for error reporting).
$plot_min and $plot_max are the range limits. These are passed by reference
and may be adjusted by the function.
$adjust_min and $adjust_max are flags indicating if the corresponding
$plot_min and $plot_max values were user-specified (False) or calculated (True).
A flag value of True means <function>CheckPlotRange</function> may adjust
the corresponding plot range value to prevent a non-positive range.
Called by <xref linkend="CalcPlotRange"/>.
This was added in PHPlot-6.0.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="CheckPointParams" xreflabel="CheckPointParams"/>CheckPointParams()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Adjusts the point_shapes and point_sizes arrays so they have the same size,
and stores the size in a class variable. This handles processing deferred
from <xref linkend="SetPointShapes"/> and <xref linkend="SetPointSizes"/>
until graph drawing time. It it is called by <xref linkend="DrawDots"/>
before using point shapes.
This was added in PHPlot-5.1.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DecodeDataType" xreflabel="DecodeDataType"/>DecodeDataType()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Decodes the data type, and sets several member variables that other functions
can use to understand how to process the data array. The variables it sets
all have names starting with "datatype_" (refer to <xref linkend="dev-vars"/>).
This is called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>.
It was added in PHPlot-5.1.2 (where it returned an array of 4 flags, and
was called by several functions that needed to know the structure of the
data array.)
In PHPlot-5.1.3, it was changed to set member variables instead.
It is now called just once, and the other functions reference the variables
as needed.
Starting with PHPlot-6.1.0, it uses the
<link linkend="var-datatypes">$datatypes</link> array to set the flags based
on the data type, so it no longer needs to 'know' the actual data type names.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DisableCaching" xreflabel="DisableCaching"/>DisableCaching()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Sends HTTP headers to the browser to disable client-side caching.  This is
called by <xref linkend="PrintImage"/> if
<xref linkend="SetBrowserCache"/> was used to disable caching.
It is also used by <xref linkend="StartStream"/>.
This was added in PHPlot-5.8.0 by moving code out of PrintImage.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DoCallback" xreflabel="DoCallback"/>DoCallback($reason, ...)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Call a callback (hook) function.  $reason is the name given to the
callback, for example <literal>draw_titles</literal>
(meaning: call after drawing titles).
The reasons are array indexes in the $callbacks class variable. Following
that are zero or more arguments to pass to the callback, after the image
resource and passthrough arguments. DoCallback does nothing if there is no
callback registered for the given reason, otherwise it calls the callback
function. See <xref linkend="callbacks"/> for more information on callbacks.
    </para>
    <para>
Starting with PHPlot-5.1.3, <function>DoCallback</function> returns the value
returned by the callback function, if any. If there is no callback defined for
the given reason,  <literal>NULL</literal> is returned. So it is possible to
define a callback that returns a meaningful value (such as True/False), and
still distinguish the case of where no callback has been set.  However, it is
often simpler to test first to see if a callback has been set, using
<xref linkend="GetCallback"/>, before using <function>DoCallback</function>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawArea" xreflabel="DrawArea"/>DrawArea($do_stacked = False)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws an area plot, or a stacked area plot (if the optional argument is True).
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> when the plot type is
<literal>area</literal> or <literal>stackedarea</literal>.
Stacked area plots were added in PHPlot-5.1.1; through PHPlot-5.1.0 this
function did not have a parameter and was used only for area plots.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawBackground" xreflabel="DrawBackground"/>DrawBackground($overwrite = False)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws the image background, either an image file or solid fill or nothing.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> and <xref linkend="DrawMessage"/>.
The optional argument $overwrite (added in PHPlot-5.7.0 for DrawMessage)
forces the background to be drawn, even if it was already drawn.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawBar" xreflabel="DrawBar"/>DrawBar($row, $column, $x1, $y1, $x2, $y2, $data_color, $shade_color, $border_color, $shade_top = TRUE, $shade_side = TRUE)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a single bar (or bar segment), with either shading or border.
The $row and $column indicate which data point is being plotted.
Four corner coordinates and 3 color indexes are provided.
The first color $data_color is the bar fill color,
the second color $shade_color is the shading color, and the third
color $border_color is used for bar borders.
(These three come from <xref linkend="GetBarColors"/>.)
The last two arguments are flags used to suppress the top or side shading
for certain cases of stacked bar segments.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawBars"/> and <xref linkend="DrawHorizBars"/>
to draw each bar.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawStackedBars"/> and
<xref linkend="DrawHorizStackedBars"/> to draw each bar segment.
This was added in PHPlot-5.2.0, moving common code from those 4 functions.
    </para>
    <para>
Starting with PHPlot-5.7.0, the arguments were changed as shown to accommodate 
a new callback which provides access to drawing coordinates.
In previous releases, the usage was
<function>DrawBar($x1, $y1, $x2, $y2, $data_color, $alt_color,
$shade_top = TRUE, $shade_side = TRUE)</function>.
    </para>
    <para>
In PHPlot-6.0.0, a single $alt_color argument was split into separate
$shade_color and $border_color arguments. This corresponds to the change
in <xref linkend="GetBarColors"/>, and allows for bar charts with
independent control over shading and borders.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawBars" xreflabel="DrawBars"/>DrawBars()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a bar chart plot.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> when the plot type is
<literal>bars</literal>.
If the data type indicates a horizontal bar chart,
calls <xref linkend="DrawHorizBars"/> instead.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawBoxes" xreflabel="DrawBoxes"/>DrawBoxes()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a box plot.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> when the plot type is
<literal>boxes</literal>.
This was added in PHPlot-6.1.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>


<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawBubbles" xreflabel="DrawBubbles"/>DrawBubbles()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a bubbles plot.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> when the plot type is
<literal>bubbles</literal>.
This was added in PHPlot-5.5.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawDataLabel" xreflabel="DrawDataLabel"/>DrawDataLabel($which_font, $which_angle, $x_world, $y_world, $which_color, $which_text, $which_halign = 'center', $which_valign = 'top', $x_adjustment=0, $y_adjustment=0)</term> <!-- REMOVED -->
  <listitem>
    <para>
This function was removed in PHPlot-5.1.3 and replaced
by <xref linkend="DrawDataValueLabel"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawDataValueLabel" xreflabel="DrawDataValueLabel"/>DrawDataValueLabel($x_or_y, $row, $column, $x_world, $y_world, $text, $dvl)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a data value label (previously called "Y data label").
These are the above-bar or in-bar labels on bar and stackedbar charts, and
the labels near data points available with some other plot types.
</para>
<para>
$x_or_y is 'x' or 'y' to select the font, angle, and formatting type.
The $row and $column are passed to <xref linkend="FormatLabel"/>
for possible use with a custom formatting function.
The label is drawn at world coordinates ($x_world, $y_world) after device
coordinate offset is applied (see below).
$text is the label text, which gets formatted with
<xref linkend="FormatLabel"/> before drawing.
</para>
<para>
The $dvl argument is an array with up to 6 variables containing positioning
and related information. In $dvl, x_offset and y_offset are pixel offsets
for the label; h_align and v_align specify the text alignment relative
to the plotting point (see <xref linkend="DrawText"/>);
min_width and max_width used to prevent labels from overlapping their
allocated space. If either min_width or max_width is supplied in the $dvl
array, the text is sized before drawing, and if it won't fit in the space
the label is not drawn. This is used to suppress labels that are too wide to
be drawn inside their bars, for example.
The defaults for the X and Y offsets are 0, and the default alignment is
(center, center). (The $dvl argument is required, but none of its elements
is required.)
</para>
<para>
This function is called by all plot drawing functions which support data value
labels, if those labels are enabled.
</para>
<para>
This function was added in PHPlot-5.1.3 and replaced
<xref linkend="DrawDataLabel"/>.
Through PHPlot-5.7.0, 6 separate arguments were used instead of the $dvl
array, and the $row and $column arguments were not present.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawDot" xreflabel="DrawDot"/>DrawDot($row, $column, $x_world, $y_world, $color)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a single marker point ('dot') at the given X and Y world coordinates,
using the given color.
The $row and $column indicate which data point is being plotted.
The $column parameter also selects the marker shape and size,
using the arrays set up with SetPointSizes() and SetPointShapes().
Called by <xref linkend="DrawDots"/> to plot point markers.
Starting with PHPlot-5.4.0, DrawDot() simply converts the coordinates to device
coordinates and then calls <xref linkend="DrawShape"/>. It has no knowledge of
the available dot shapes.
    </para>
    <para>
Starting with PHPlot-5.7.0, the arguments were changed as shown to accommodate 
a new callback which provides access to drawing coordinates.
In previous releases, the usage was
<function>DrawDot($x_world, $y_world, $record, $color)</function>.
The old $record argument is equivalent to the new $column argument.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawDots" xreflabel="DrawDots"/>DrawDots($paired = False)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a points plot, or the points for a linepoints plot, including error plots.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> when the plot type is 
<literal>points</literal>, and by <xref linkend="DrawLinePoints"/> for the
points portion of a <literal>linepoints</literal> plot.
$paired is true for <literal>linepoints</literal> plots.
When $paired is true, DrawDots() draws the points and error bars, and
<xref linkend="DrawLines" /> draws the lines and data labels.
(The $paired argument was added in PHPlot-5.1.3.)
Starting with PHPlot-6.0.0, DrawDots() also handles error plots,
and horizontal points and linepoints plots.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawDotsError" xreflabel="DrawDotsError"/>DrawDotsError($paired = False)</term> <!-- REMOVED -->
  <listitem>
    <para>
This function was removed in PHPlot-6.0.0 and merged into
<xref linkend="DrawDots" />.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawError" xreflabel="DrawError"/>DrawError($error_message, [$where_x], [$where_y])</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Starting with PHPlot-5.0.5, this function is an alias for
<xref linkend="PrintError"/> and is retained for compatibility.
The $where_x and $where_arguments are now ignored. (Previously they
positioned the error message on the image, but were never used.)
Starting with PHPlot-5.7.0, this function is considered deprecated.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawHorizBars" xreflabel="DrawHorizBars"/>DrawHorizBars()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a horizontal bars plot.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawBars"/> when the data type indicates a
horizontal plot.
This was added in PHPlot-5.1.2 (but was called by DrawGraph).
In PHPlot-5.1.3 it was changed to be called by DrawBars.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawHorizStackedBars" xreflabel="DrawHorizStackedBars"/>DrawHorizStackedBars()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a horizontal stacked bars plot.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawStackedBars"/> when the data type indicates a
horizontal plot.
This was added in PHPlot-5.1.3.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawImageBorder" xreflabel="DrawImageBorder"/>DrawImageBorder($overwrite = False)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a border around the image, if enabled by
<xref linkend="SetImageBorderType"/>.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> and <xref linkend="DrawMessage"/>.
The optional argument $overwrite (added in PHPlot-5.7.0 for DrawMessage)
forces the border to be drawn, even if it was already drawn.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawLegend" xreflabel="DrawLegend"/>DrawLegend(x,y,type)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws the plot legend. This includes the box, text labels, and color boxes
or shapes.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>,
but only if legend text has been set using <xref linkend="SetLegend"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawLinePoints" xreflabel="DrawLinePoints"/>DrawLinePoints()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a linepoints plot, with or without error bars.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> when the plot type is
<literal>linepoints</literal>.
It simply calls <xref linkend="DrawLines"/> and <xref linkend="DrawDots"/>,
which handle both the plain and error bar cases.
This was added in PHPlot-5.1.3 to provide a function specific to this
plot type.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawLines" xreflabel="DrawLines"/>DrawLines($paired = False)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a line plot, or the lines part of a linepoints plot, including error
plots.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> when the plot type is
<literal>lines</literal>, and by <xref linkend="DrawLinePoints"/> for the
lines portion of a <literal>linepoints</literal> plot.
$paired is true for <literal>linepoints</literal> plots.
When $paired is true, DrawLines() draws the lines and data labels, and
<xref linkend="DrawDots" /> draw the points and error bars.
(The $paired argument was added in PHPlot-5.1.3.)
Starting with PHPlot-6.0.0, DrawLines() also handles error plots,
and horizontal lines and linepoints plots.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawLinesError" xreflabel="DrawLinesError"/>DrawLinesError($paired = False)</term> <!-- REMOVED -->
  <listitem>
    <para>
This function was removed in PHPlot-6.0.0 and merged into
<xref linkend="DrawLines" />.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawOHLC" xreflabel="DrawOHLC"/>DrawOHLC($draw_candles, $always_fill = FALSE)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws one of the three types of OHLC (Open/High/Low/Close) plots.
If $draw_candles is FALSE, draws a basic OHLC plot
(plot type <literal>ohlc</literal>).
If $draw_candles is TRUE and $always_fill is FALSE,
draws a candlestick OHLC plot
(plot type <literal>candlesticks</literal>).
If $draw_candles is TRUE and $always_fill is TRUE,
draws a filled candlestick OHLC plot
(plot type <literal>candlesticks2</literal>).
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> when the plot type is one of those
three types.
This was added in PHPlot-5.3.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawPieChart" xreflabel="DrawPieChart"/>DrawPieChart()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a pie chart plot.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> with the plot type is
<literal>pie</literal>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawPieLabel" xreflabel="DrawPieLabel"/>DrawPieLabel($label_txt, $xc, $yc, $start_angle, $arc_angle, $r)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a pie chart label. $label_txt is the already-formatted label text
string. ($xc, $yc) is the center of the pie (not the text basepoint).
$start_angle is the starting angle in degrees for the segment being
labeled, which extends for $arc_angle degrees. $r is an array of static
values (constant for each pie chart): ellipse parameters and a flag to
indicate the text alignment should be reversed.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawPieChart"/>.
This was added in PHPlot-5.6.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>


<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawPlotAreaBackground" xreflabel="DrawPlotAreaBackground"/>DrawPlotAreaBackground()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws the plot area background, either an image file set with
<xref linkend="SetPlotAreaBgImage"/>,
or else a solid fill color selected by <xref linkend="SetPlotBgColor"/>
if enabled with <xref linkend="SetDrawPlotAreaBackground"/>
or else nothing.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawPlotBorder" xreflabel="DrawPlotBorder"/>DrawPlotBorder($draw_axes=TRUE)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws the border around the plot area.
This draws zero to four lines around the plot area (depending on
<xref linkend="SetPlotBorderType"/>).
The $draw_axes argument (added in PHPlot-5.6.0) is true for all plot types
except pie charts, and controls the default value if SetPlotBorderType() was
not called.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawShape" xreflabel="DrawShape"/>DrawShape($x, $y, $record, $color, $allow_none = TRUE)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a single marker point ('dot' or 'shape') at the given X and Y device
(pixel) coordinates, using the given color. The $record parameter selects the
marker shape and size using the arrays set up with SetPointSizes() and
SetPointShapes(); they are not passed as arguments themselves.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawDot"/> and <xref linkend="DrawLegend"/>.
This is the function that knows which shapes are available and how to draw
them. (<xref linkend="SetPointShapes"/> also has a list of valid shapes.)
This was added at PHPlot-5.4.0 by moving the shape drawing code out of
DrawDot(), leaving behind only the conversion from world to device coordinates.
This was necessary because DrawLegend() needs to specify marker positions
in pixel coordinates when using point shapes instead of color boxes.
    </para>
    <para>
If the optional $allow_none is FALSE, then the function will substitute
another shape for the special 'none' shape (which suppresses a shape marker
for a data set in a linepoints plot). This is used when drawing a legend, to
ensure that there is a marker shape for each data set. This argument was
added in PHPlot-6.0.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawSquared" xreflabel="DrawSquared"/>DrawSquared()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a squared (stepped lines) plot.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> when the plot type is
<literal>squared</literal>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawStackedBars" xreflabel="DrawStackedBars"/>DrawStackedBars()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a stacked bars chart plot.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> when the plot type is
<literal>stackedbars</literal>.
If the data type indicates a horizontal plot,
calls <xref linkend="DrawHorizStackedBars"/> instead.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawText" xreflabel="DrawText"/>DrawText($font, $angle, $xpos, $ypos, $color, $text, $halign = 'left', $valign = 'bottom')</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a string of text $text, at position ($xpos, $ypos).
The font settings are specified by $font, which is one of the text element
names used by <xref linkend="SetFont"/> such as <literal>'title'</literal>
or <literal>'x_label'</literal>.  An empty string or NULL can be used to get
the <literal>'generic'</literal> font.  For backward compatibility,
a font array (from the PHPlot object $fonts[] array) can be used too.
    </para>
    <para>
The text is drawn at angle $angle (built-in fonts can be used at 0
and 90 degrees only, TrueType at any angle). $color is a GD color
index for the image. Text alignment relative to the (x,y) point is
controlled with $halign (<literal>center</literal>,
<literal>left</literal>, or <literal>right</literal>)
and $valign (<literal>center</literal>, <literal>bottom</literal>,
or <literal>top</literal>).
    </para>
    <para>
Multi-line text strings are supported. This function accounts for the
limitations and differences in GD text drawing routines for built-in and
TrueType fonts.
Called by numerous functions which place text on the plot.
    </para>
    <para>
Starting with PHPlot-5.0.5, this function just calls
<xref linkend="ProcessText"/> in text drawing mode. DrawText should be used
by all internal PHPlot code that needs to draw text, and ProcessText should
only be used by DrawText and SizeText.
    </para>
    <para>
Starting with PHPlot-5.1.0, $font can be NULL or an empty string to
use the <emphasis>generic</emphasis> font.
This was intended to allow callbacks to avoid having to reference the internal
class array variable which stores font information.
    </para>
    <para>
Starting with PHPlot-6.0.0, the preferred form for $font is the name of a
PHPlot text element, with use of the $fonts[] member variable deprecated.
This further eases use of DrawText by callbacks, which can specify a font
other than 'generic' without referencing internal class variables.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawThinBarLines" xreflabel="DrawThinBarLines"/>DrawThinBarLines()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a thin bar lines plot. This is sometimes called an impulse plot.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> when the plot type is
<literal>thinbarline</literal>.
This function draws both vertical and horizontal variants of this plot type.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawTitle" xreflabel="DrawTitle"/>DrawTitle()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws the main plot title as set with <xref linkend="SetTitle"/>. This is centered at the
very top of the image.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawXAxis" xreflabel="DrawXAxis"/>DrawXAxis()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws the X (horizontal) axis, including the axis line,
tick marks and labels,
and also draws the vertical grid lines.
All of these except the axis line are done in <xref linkend="DrawXTicks"/>.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawXDataLabel" xreflabel="DrawXDataLabel"/>DrawXDataLabel($xlab, $xpos, $row, $do_lines=FALSE)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws an axis data label for an X value. The labels are above or below the plot
area or both, depending on the value set with
<xref linkend="SetXDataLabelPos"/>.
The $row value indicates the row index in the data array for this label; it
is used to position the data label line, and for custom label formatting.
If $do_lines is true, this calls <xref linkend="DrawXDataLine"/> to draw a
line from the label to the point, if enabled and supported by the plot type.
    </para>
    <para>
This function is used by vertical plots.
It is called by plot drawing routines for all plot types except
<literal>pie</literal>:
<xref linkend="DrawArea"/>, 
<xref linkend="DrawBars"/>,
<xref linkend="DrawDots"/>, 
<xref linkend="DrawThinBarLines"/>, 
<xref linkend="DrawLines"/>, 
<xref linkend="DrawSquared"/>, and
<xref linkend="DrawStackedBars"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawXDataLine" xreflabel="DrawXDataLine"/>DrawXDataLine($xpos, $row)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws X data lines, which are vertical lines from the bottom or top of the
plot to the data points. This is enabled with
<xref linkend="SetDrawXDataLabelLines"/>. The lines are drawn from the
position (above, below, or both) of the X axis data labels, which are set with
<xref linkend="SetXDataLabelPos"/>.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawXDataLabel"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawXErrorBars"
xreflabel="DrawXErrorBars"/>DrawXErrorBars($x, $y $error_plus, $error_minus, $color)</term> 
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws an error bar set for the point at world coordinates ($x, $y).
$error_plus and $error_minus are the X error amounts (in world coordinates).
Both are non-negative values.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawDots"/> and <xref linkend="DrawLines"/> when
the data type indicates a horizontal error plot.
This was added in PHPlot-6.1.0 when horizontal error plots were implemented.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawXTick" xreflabel="DrawXTick"/>DrawXTick($x, $x_pixels)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a single X value tick mark and its label.
These can appear on the bottom of the graph, top of the graph, along the
X axis (even if it is in the middle somewhere), on both sides, or nowhere,
as set with <xref linkend="SetXTickPos"/> and
<xref linkend="SetXTickLabelPos"/>.
$x is the X value of the tick, and $x_pixels is its device coordinate value.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawXTicks"/>.
This was added at PHPlot-5.0.5 by splitting the code out of DrawXTicks,
for symmetry with DrawYTicks.
Through PHPlot-5.7.0, $x was passed to this function already formatted with
<xref linkend="FormatLabel"/>. Starting with PHPlot-5.8.0, the actual tick
value is passed, so <function>DrawXTick</function> can decide whether or
not to format it.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawXTicks" xreflabel="DrawXTicks"/>DrawXTicks()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws the vertical grid lines, the tick marks, and tick labels.
Calls <xref linkend="CalcTicks"/> to calculate the tick parameters.
Calls <xref linkend="DrawXTick"/> to draw each tick mark and its label.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawXAxis"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawXTitle" xreflabel="DrawXTitle"/>DrawXTitle()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws the X axis title. There can be zero, one, or two of them depending on
the position parameter specified in <xref linkend="SetXTitle"/>.
Calls <xref linkend="DrawText"/> to actually draw the title(s).
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawYAxis" xreflabel="DrawYAxis"/>DrawYAxis()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws the Y (vertical) axis, including the axis line,
tick marks and labels,
and also draws the horizontal grid lines.
All of these except the axis line are done in <xref linkend="DrawYTicks"/>.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawYDataLabel" xreflabel="DrawYDataLabel"/>DrawYDataLabel($ylab, $ypos, $row, $do_lines=FALSE)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws an axis data label for a Y value. The labels are along the Y axis or
side of the plot, or both, depending on the value set with
<xref linkend="SetYDataLabelPos"/>.
The $row value indicates the row index in the data array for this label; it
is used for custom label formatting.
If $do_lines is true, this calls <xref linkend="DrawYDataLine"/> to draw a
line from the label to the point, if enabled and supported by the plot type.
This function is used by horizontal plots, and was added in PHPlot-5.1.2.
Called by horizontal plot drawing functions such as
<xref linkend="DrawHorizBars"/>.
The $do_lines argument was added in PHPlot-6.0.0 when horizontal plots
supporting data label lines were first available.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawYDataLine" xreflabel="DrawYDataLine"/>DrawYDataLine($ypos, $row)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws Y data lines, which are horizontal lines from the left or right side of
the plot to the data points. This is enabled with
<xref linkend="SetDrawYDataLabelLines"/>, and is only valid with horizontal
plots which support Y data label lines. The lines are drawn from the
position (left, right, or both) of the Y axis data labels, which are set with
<xref linkend="SetYDataLabelPos"/>.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawYDataLabel"/>.
This was added in PHPlot-6.0.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawYErrorBar" xreflabel="DrawYErrorBar"/>DrawYErrorBar($x_world, $y_world, $error_height, $color)</term> <!-- REMOVED -->
  <listitem>
    <para>
This function was removed in PHPlot-6.1.0 and replaced with
<xref linkend="DrawYErrorBars"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawYErrorBars" xreflabel="DrawYErrorBars"/>DrawYErrorBars($x, $y $error_plus, $error_minus, $color)</term> 
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws an error bar set for the point at world coordinates ($x, $y).
$error_plus and $error_minus are the Y error amounts (in world coordinates).
Both are non-negative values.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawDots"/> and <xref linkend="DrawLines"/> when
the data type indicates a vertical error plot.
This was added in PHPlot-6.1.0, replacing <xref linkend="DrawYErrorBar"/>
(which drew only 1 of the error bars for a point).
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawYTick" xreflabel="DrawYTick"/>DrawYTick($y, $y_pixels)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws a single Y value tick mark and its label.
These can appear on the left of the graph, right of the graph, along the
Y axis (even if it is in the middle somewhere), on both sides, or nowhere,
as set with <xref linkend="SetYTickPos"/> and
<xref linkend="SetYTickLabelPos"/>.
$y is the Y value of the tick, and $y_pixels is its device coordinate value.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawYTicks"/>.
Through PHPlot-5.7.0, $y was passed to this function already formatted with
<xref linkend="FormatLabel"/>. Starting with PHPlot-5.8.0, the actual tick
value is passed, so <function>DrawYTick</function> can decide whether or
not to format it.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawYTicks" xreflabel="DrawYTicks"/>DrawYTicks()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws the horizontal grid lines, the tick marks, and tick labels.
Calls <xref linkend="DrawYTick"/> to draw each tick mark and its label.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawYAxis"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="DrawYTitle" xreflabel="DrawYTitle"/>DrawYTitle()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws the Y axis title. There can be zero, one, or two of them depending on
the position parameter specified in <xref linkend="SetYTitle"/>.
Calls <xref linkend="DrawText"/> to actually draw the title(s).
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="FindDataLimits" xreflabel="FindDataLimits"/>FindDataLimits()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Finds the limits of the data. Using the data_type and the data array, it
goes through the points and determines the minimum and maximum X and Y values.
It stores the min and max Y values for each row (plot line) in the
class arrays data_min and data_max.
(Before PHPlot-5.0.4, these were stored back into the data array
with special index values MINY (-1) and MAXY (-2).)
It also stores the overall min and max X and Y values as min_x, max_x,
min_y, and max_y.
It also stores the length of the longest data label in max_t.
Starting with PHPlot-5.0.5, this is only called once by
<xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>. (In PHPlot-5.0.4 and earlier, this was called
from various places, with a flag data_limits_done to indicate it was called.)
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="FormatLabel" xreflabel="FormatLabel"/>FormatLabel($which_pos, $which_lab, ...)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Formats a value for use as a tick, data, or pie chart label.
This implements the format type selected with
<xref linkend="SetXLabelType"/>, <xref linkend="SetYLabelType"/>,
<xref linkend="SetXDataLabelType"/> ,<xref linkend="SetYDataLabelType"/>,
and <xref linkend="SetPieLabelType"/>.
If no formatting is in effect for that label type ($which_pos), it returns the 
label string $which_lab as-is. Otherwise, it formats it as directed. This
can be a floating point number (formatted with <xref linkend="number_format"/>),
a date/time value, or it can be formatted with <function>sprintf</function>
or a user-defined function (type 'custom').
Any additional arguments after the first 2 are passed through to a custom label
formatting function. This is used to make the data row and column available
to the user-defined function (if applicable for the label type).
    </para>
    <para>
Called by several functions that need to format label values.
Separation of data and tick label formatting was available starting with
PHPlot-5.1.0. Use with pie chart labels was added in PHPlot-5.6.0.
Support for additional arguments for custom functions  was added
in PHPlot-5.8.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="FormatPieLabel" xreflabel="FormatPieLabel"/>FormatPieLabel($index, $pie_label_source, $arc_angle, $slice_weight)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Formats a pie chart label. This first gets the initial value, based on
the $source argument to <xref linkend="SetPieLabelType"/>, which is passed
in as $pie_label_source. It may use $index, $arc_angle, or $slice_weight,
or a combination of those. Then it formats that value using
<xref linkend="FormatLabel"/> and returns the result.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawPieChart"/>.
This was added in PHPlot-5.6.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetBarColors"
xreflabel="GetBarColors"/>GetBarColors($row, $idx, &amp;$vars, &amp;$data_color, &amp;$shade_color, &amp;$border_color)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Gets the color indexes to be used for a bar plot.
This is used by bar and stackedbar plot drawing functions, and
accounts for a custom data color callback if defined.
$row and $idx are the indexes for the current bar or bar segment.
$vars is an array argument that maintains information across calls - the
caller allocates an empty array, and this function updates it.
The color index for bar filling is returned in $data_color.
$shade_color is the color index to use for shading (if shading is on).
$border_color is the color index to use for the bar border (if on).
This was added in PHPlot-5.2.0, moving common code into a function.
In PHPlot-6.0.0, a single $alt_color argument was split into separate
$shade_color and $border_color arguments.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetColorIndex" xreflabel="GetColorIndex"/>GetColorIndex(&amp;$color, $default_color_index=0)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Allocate a GD color index for a color given as a 4 component array (R,G,B,A)
$color.  Returns a color index to be used in GD drawing functions.
The color returned is the exact color requested if it already exists in the
image, or if can be allocated.
For palette images, if the color map is full, no new colors can be allocated,
and this function will return an index to the closest existing color.
For truecolor images, this function always returns an index for the exact
requested color.
If $color is empty or unset, returns $default_color_index instead, without
allocating a new color.
This was added in PHPlot-5.2.0, replacing the second half of
<xref linkend="SetIndexColor"/>.
The $default_color_index argument was added in PHPlot-5.7.0, and the $color
argument was changed to a reference (so an unset variable can be passed 
without an error).
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetColorIndexArray" xreflabel="GetColorIndexArray"/>GetColorIndexArray($color_array, $max_colors)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Allocates GD color indexes for each color in the array $color_array, which are
given as 4 component arrays (R,G,B,A). Up to $max_colors colors will be
allocated. (This is used to limit the number of allocated data colors to the
number of data sets in the plot, for example.)
<xref linkend="GetColorIndex"/> is used to allocate each color.
Returns an array of GD color indexes to be used in GD drawing functions.
This was added in PHPlot-5.3.1.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetDarkColorIndex" xreflabel="GetDarkColorIndex"/>GetDarkColorIndex($color)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Allocate a GD color index for a darker shade of a color given as a 4 component
array (R,G,B,A).
Returns a color index to be used in GD drawing functions.
The method used is to subtract 48 from each red, green, and blue component
(without letting any go negative).
The alpha component is not adjusted.
The color returned is the exact color requested if it already exists in the
image, or if can be allocated, else the closest color available.
This is used for shadow colors (for example, in bar charts and pie charts).
This was added in PHPlot-5.2.0, replacing the second half of
<xref linkend="SetIndexDarkColor"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetDarkColorIndexArray" xreflabel="GetDarkColorIndexArray"/>GetDarkColorIndexArray($color_array, $max_colors)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Allocates GD color indexes for a darker shade of each color in the array
$color_array, which are given as 4 component arrays (R,G,B,A). Up to
$max_colors colors will be allocated. (This is used to limit the number of
allocated dark-shade data colors to the number of data sets in the plot,
for example.)
<xref linkend="GetDarkColorIndex"/> is used to allocate each color.
Returns an array of GD color indexes to be used in GD drawing functions.
This was added in PHPlot-5.3.1.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetDataColor" xreflabel="GetDataColor"/>GetDataColor($row, $idx, &amp;$vars, &amp;$data_color, $extra=0)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Gets the color index to be used for a data element (a point or line
segment, for example).
This is used by multiple plot drawing functions to get the data color,
accounting for a custom data color callback if defined.
$row and $idx are the indexes for the data point. $vars is an array argument 
that maintains information across calls - the caller allocates an empty
array, and this function updates it.
The color index to use is returned in $data_color.
$extra contains extra information for a data color callback.
This was added in PHPlot-5.2.0, moving common code into a function.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetDataErrorColors" xreflabel="GetDataErrorColors"/>GetDataErrorColors($row, $idx, &amp;$vars, &amp;$data_color, &amp;$error_color, $extra=0)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
This is an extended version of <xref linkend="GetDataColor"/> which is used
for error bar plots. It returns two color index values: $data_color for the
data element, and $error_color for the error bar.
This is used by error plot drawing functions, and accounts for a custom
data color callback if defined.
$row and $idx are the indexes for the data point. $vars is an array argument 
that maintains information across calls - the caller allocates an empty
array, and this function updates it.
$extra contains extra information for a data color callback.
This was added in PHPlot-5.2.0, moving common code into a function.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetDefaultTTFont" xreflabel="GetDefaultTTFont"/>GetDefaultTTFont()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Returns the default TrueType font name. If no default font has been set
using <xref linkend="SetDefaultTTFont"/>, the first time this is called it
will go through a list of likely sans-serif fonts, trying to find one
that works.  The first one that works, or the last one if none works, will
be set as the default font.
This was added in PHPlot-5.1.3, replacing the static initialization of
default font.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetGridSetting" xreflabel="GetGridSetting"/>GetGridSetting($xy)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Returns a flag indicating whether to draw the grid along the axis
indicated by $xy ('x' or 'y'). This implements the grid default which
differs for horizontal and vertical plots.
This was added in PHPlot-6.0.0, replacing CalcGridSettings().
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetImage" xreflabel="GetImage"/>GetImage($image_filename, &amp;$width, &amp;$height)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Reads an image file from $image_filename, stores the width and height
(in pixels) in the $width and $height reference arguments, and returns
a PHP GD image resource of the image.
This is used by <xref linkend="SetInputFile"/> and <xref linkend="tile_img"/>.
Errors go to <xref linkend="PrintError"/>; there is no way for the script
to recover. Possible errors include an image file type which is unsupported
by PHP GD, or a corrupt image file.
Note: This was added at PHPlot-5.0.4, by moving common code from the
two calling functions.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetImageBorderWidth" xreflabel="GetImageBorderWidth"/>GetImageBorderWidth()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
This returns the image border width, as set with
<xref linkend="SetImageBorderWidth" /> or as defaulted.
It is used by <xref linkend="CalcMargins" /> to account for image border width,
and by <xref linkend="DrawImageBorder" /> when drawing the image border.
This was added in PHPlot-5.1.2.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetImageType" xreflabel="GetImageType"/>GetImageType(&amp;$mime_type, &amp;$output_f)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Given the current file type (e.g. 'png'), this sets the MIME type for the
image (e.g. 'image/png') and the name of the GD output function (e.g.
'imagepng') corresponding to that type. The results are stored in the
arguments, and TRUE is returned unless an error occurs.
It is used by <xref linkend="PrintImage" /> and <xref linkend="EncodeImage"/>.
This was added in PHPlot-5.5.0, from code moved out of PrintImage.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetLegendPosition" xreflabel="GetLegendPosition"/>GetLegendPosition($width, $height)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
This calculates and returns the device coordinates (as a 2 element array X,Y)
of the upper left corner of the legend box. $width and $height are the size of
the legend box.  It accounts for the positioning mode, reference point,
base point, and pixel offset as set with <xref linkend="SetLegendPosition"/>.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawLegend"/>.
This was added in PHPlot-5.4.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetLegendSizeParams" xreflabel="GetLegendSizeParams"/>GetLegendSizeParams()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
This calculates a number of parameters that determine how to draw the
legend, and returns an array containing those variables and their values.
Called by <xref linkend="GetLegendSize"/> (which only uses the 'width' and
'height' elements), and by <xref linkend="DrawLegend"/>.
This was added in PHPlot-5.4.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetLineSpacing" xreflabel="GetLineSpacing"/>GetLineSpacing($font)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Given a font array variable, returns the proper spacing in pixels between lines
of text using that font. This works for both GD and TrueType fonts. See also 
<xref linkend="SetLineSpacing"/>.
Used by <xref linkend="ProcessTextGD"/>, <xref linkend="ProcessTextTTF"/>,
and <xref linkend="DrawLegend"/>.
Note: This was added at PHPlot-5.0.6, with support for mixing TTF and GD
fonts.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetRangeEndAdjust" xreflabel="GetRangeEndAdjust"/>GetRangeEndAdjust($which, &amp;$adjust)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Applies a default to $adjust, the plot range end adjustment factor. $which is
'x' or 'y'. If $adjust is already set, the function does nothing.
Otherwise, it uses the current plot type to apply a default setting to $adjust.
See the notes on the <literal>adjust_type</literal> entry in
<xref linkend="var-plots"/> for more on the per-plot-type adjustment mode.
This is used by <xref linkend="CalcPlotRange"/>.
It was added at PHPlot-6.0.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="GetTextAlignment" xreflabel="GetTextAlignment"/>GetTextAlignment($sin_t, $cos_t, &amp;$h_align, &amp;$v_align, $reverse = FALSE)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Selects the best alignment for text which is at a specific angle ($sin_t,
$cos_t) from a point. The result is returned in $h_align and $v_align,
suitable for use with <xref linkend="DrawText"/>.
The alignment is chosen from 8 possible values (left/center, center/bottom,
etc.) to keep the closest edge or corner of the text box at a fixed
distance from the reference point (typically the center of a pie chart, or
a plotted point), regardless of the text string size.
For example, text at 0 degrees is left/center aligned, and text at 90 degrees
is center/bottom aligned.
If $reverse is true, the alignment is reversed; this is used for text inside
an ellipse but close to the circumference.
Used by <xref linkend="CheckDataValueLabels"/>
and <xref linkend="DrawPieLabel"/>.
Note: This was added at PHPlot-5.6.0 by moving code out of
<xref linkend="CheckDataValueLabels"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>


<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="initialize" xreflabel="initialize"/>initialize($imagecreate_function, $width, $height, $output_file, $input_file)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Initialize a newly created object. This is called from the two class
constructors, <xref linkend="PHPlot"/> and <xref linkend="PHPlot-truecolor"/>.
$imagecreate_function is the name of the GD function used to create an image
(<function>imagecreate</function> or <function>imagecreatetruecolor</function>).
The other arguments are the same as in the class constructors, except the
defaults are already applied.
This was added in PHPlot-5.6.0 by moving duplicated code from the two
constructors into a shared function.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="NeedDataDarkColors" xreflabel="NeedDataDarkColors"/>NeedDataDarkColors()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Allocates darker data colors, which are used for shading.
This is called by graph drawing functions such as <xref linkend="DrawPieChart"/>
if they need to use these colors for shading.
This was added in PHPlot-5.2.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="NeedErrorBarColors" xreflabel="NeedErrorBarColors"/>NeedErrorBarColors()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Allocates colors used for error bars.
This is called by any graph drawing functions that is going to draw error bars.
This was added in PHPlot-5.2.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="number_format" xreflabel="number_format"/>number_format($number, $decimals=0)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Formats a floating point number, like PHP's number_format(), inserting
a decimal separator and thousands groups separators. Unlike the PHP
function, this uses variables in the PHPlot class to select the separators.
The separators can be set with <xref linkend="SetNumberFormat"/>, or by
default PHPlot will attempt to get locale-specific values.
For example, 1234+(56/100) will be returned as "1,234.56" if the locale is
"en_US", and as "1.234,56" if the locale is "de_DE".
As a fall-back, if locale information is not available, '.' is used for
decimal point, and ',' for thousands separator. This fall-back is equivalent
to the behavior in PHPlot 5.0rc3 and earlier.
This is used by <xref linkend="FormatLabel"/> when the formatting type is
<literal>data</literal>, and also for the pie chart labels in
<xref linkend="DrawPieChart"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="pad_array" xreflabel="pad_array"/>pad_array(&amp;$arr, $size)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Pads an array $arr with copies of itself until it reaches the given size.
If $arr is a scalar, it will first be converted to an array with one
element. Then, if $arr has fewer than $size elements, elements of $arr
starting from the first will be appended until it reaches $size elements.
This only works on zero-based sequential integer indexed arrays.
Called by <xref linkend="PadArrays"/>, <xref linkend="SetPointShapes"/>,
and <xref linkend="SetPointSizes"/>.
This replaced <xref linkend="array_pad_array"/> at PHPlot-5.0.4,
however that had an unused 3rd argument, and worked on general indexed arrays.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="PadArrays" xreflabel="PadArrays"/>PadArrays()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Pads the style arrays (line_widths, line_styles, data_colors, etc.) so they
are all large enough to contain an entry for each data set or plot line.
This uses <xref linkend="pad_array"/>.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> before drawing anything.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="PrintError" xreflabel="PrintError"/>PrintError($error_message)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Handles a fatal error within PHPlot. Starting with PHPlot-5.0.5 this and
<xref linkend="DrawError"/> are identical. PrintError attempts to draw the
error message $error_message into the image, and then output the image.
This method is used because PHPlot is normally expected to output an image,
and text output would not be displayed properly. (If no image resource was
available, and the <xref linkend="SetIsInline"/> flag is not on, PHPlot
will send a 500 Internal Server Error header.) PrintError uses
<xref linkend="DrawMessage"/> to actually draw the message onto the image.
After this, PrintError uses the PHP trigger_error() function to signal a user
error. This is normally fatal to the script, unless caught. This will also
result in the error message written to the error output stream, which
typically ends up in a web server error log.
    </para>
    <para>
(Through PHPlot-5.0.4, PrintError wrote an error message to standard output
and exited.)
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="ProcessText" xreflabel="ProcessText"/>ProcessText($draw_it, $font_id, $angle, $x, $y, $color, $text, $halign, $valign)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
This function acts as a bridge, or switch, between the two functions
<xref linkend="SizeText"/> and <xref linkend="DrawText"/>, which handle
both GD and TTF text,
and the functions which specifically handle GD text or TTF text.
The arguments to this function are the same as
<xref linkend="DrawText"/> except for an additional first argument
$draw_it. If $draw_it is true, text is drawn. This is used by DrawText. If
$draw_it is false, only the bounding box size of the text is calculated and
returned. This is used by SizeText. In text sizing mode, the x, y, color,
halign, and valign arguments are ignored, as they are not needed when
calculating the text bounding box size.
This function is only called by
<xref linkend="SizeText"/> and <xref linkend="DrawText"/>, and calls either
<xref linkend="ProcessTextTTF"/> or <xref linkend="ProcessTextGD"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
<function>ProcessText</function> examines the $font_id argument and handles
the variations described under <xref linkend="DrawText"/>. If $font_id is
an array, it is assumed to be an element of the member array $fonts[], and
is passed as-is to the lower level functions.
If it is a string that exists as an index to $fonts[], that font array is
used. In all other cases, the <literal>generic</literal> font is used.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="ProcessTextGD" xreflabel="ProcessTextGD"/>ProcessTextGD($draw_it, $font, $angle, $x, $y, $color, $text, $h_factor, $v_factor)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws GD fixed-font text, or calculates the size of GD fixed-font text.
This is only called by <xref linkend="ProcessText"/> after it determines
that GD text is in use.
If $draw_it is true, text is drawn;
if $draw_it is false, only the bounding box size of the text is calculated and
returned as a two-element array ($width, $height).
Here $width is measured along the X axis, and $height along Y, regardless
of the text angle. These are the size of an orthogonal bounding box that
contains the text block.
The $font argument is a PHPlot font array, which must reference a GD font.
The $angle is 0 or 90 degrees, as GD text only supports those values.
$x, $y are the reference point of the text $text, which is drawn in color
$color.
The text string can contain multiple lines, with a newline character between
lines.
The $h_factor and $v_factor arguments are translated from the
alignment arguments supplied to DrawText or SizeText: 0, 0.5, or 1.0
If $draw_it is false, for text sizing mode, the x, y, color,
h_factor and v_factor arguments are ignored.
    </para>
    <para>
Note: This was added at PHPlot-5.0.5. It was changed at PHPlot-5.0.6 to
take a single font array argument, rather than 3 separate arguments for
font number, width, and height.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="ProcessTextTTF" xreflabel="ProcessTextTTF"/>ProcessTextTTF($draw_it, $font, $angle, $x, $y, $color, $text, $h_factor, $v_factor)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Draws TTF text, or calculates the size of TTF text.
This is only called by <xref linkend="ProcessText"/> after it determines
that TTF text is in use.
If $draw_it is true, text is drawn;
if $draw_it is false, only the bounding box size of the text is calculated and
returned as a two-element array ($width, $height).
Here $width is measured along the X axis, and $height along Y, regardless
of the text angle. These are the size of an orthogonal bounding box that
contains the text block.
The $font argument is a PHPlot font array, which must reference a TTF font.
The text is drawn at $angle degrees; unlike GD text TTF text can be drawn
at any angle.
$x, $y are the reference point of the text $text, which is drawn in color
$color.
The text string can contain multiple lines, with a newline character between
lines.
The $h_factor and $v_factor arguments are translated from the
alignment arguments supplied to DrawText or SizeText: 0, 0.5, or 1.0
If $draw_it is false, for text sizing mode, the x, y, color,
h_factor and v_factor arguments are ignored.
    </para>
    <para>
Note that the interpretation of the alignment for text at arbitrary angles
may not be what you expect. Rotation of text happens before alignment, and
alignment and positioning use the orthogonal bounding box of the text.
    </para>
    <para>
Note: This was added at PHPlot-5.0.5. It was changed in PHPlot-5.0.6 to
take a single font array argument, rather than 2 separate arguments for
font filename and size.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="SetBgColorIndexes" xreflabel="SetBgColorIndexes"/>SetBgColorIndexes()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Allocates the colors for the image background and image border.
Called by <xref linkend="SetColorIndexes"/> before drawing anything, and
by <xref linkend="DrawMessage"/> if needed.
This was added in PHPlot-5.7.0 by moving code from SetColorIndexes, so that
DrawMessage can set up only the color indexes it needs.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="SetColorIndexes" xreflabel="SetColorIndexes"/>SetColorIndexes()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Allocates all the colors needed for a plot.
Called by <xref linkend="DrawGraph"/> before drawing anything.
Calls <xref linkend="SetBgColorIndexes"/> (starting at PHPlot-5.7.0) to set
the background and border color indexes.
This was added in PHPlot-5.2.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="SetDashedStyle" xreflabel="SetDashedStyle"/>SetDashedStyle($which_ndxcol, $use_style = TRUE)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Sets the GD line style to select a dashed line, if line styles are enabled,
in preparation for drawing a dashed line. $which_ndxcol is the color index
to use for the line, and $use_style is a flag indicating if a styled line
is to be drawn. Returns a GD color index to use for drawing. If
$use_styles is false, indicating solid lines, the return value is
$which_ndxcol. If $use_styles is true or omitted, the return value is a
GD constant used to indicate drawing a styled line, and $which_ndxcol is
used to set up the line style. The return value is then used by the caller
as the color argument in drawing functions such as
<function>imageline</function>.
    </para>
    <para>
To understand how this function works, see the documentation for the
PHP GD function <function>ImageSetStyle()</function> and also refer to
<xref linkend="SetDefaultDashedStyle"/>. GD expects a line style to be
specified as an array of pixel values, which is awkward to deal with.
PHPlot uses a shorthand notation with integer values indicating pairs of
the number of color, then transparent pixels.
<function>SetDefaultDashedStyle</function> creates a string of PHP code to
generate an array of pixel values the way GD wants them, but defers filling
in the exact color to use. <function>SetDashedStyle</function> evaluates this
string with <varname>$which_ndxcol</varname> set to the color to use for
the current line.
The result is an array of pixel values for <function>ImageSetStyle</function>.
    </para>
    <para>
Called by all functions that need to draw lines that can have a line style
applied, including <xref linkend="DrawXTicks"/> and <xref linkend="DrawYTicks"/>
(for drawing the grid lines, not the ticks), and <xref linkend="DrawLines"/>
for drawing line plots.
    </para>
    <para>
The $use_style argument and return value were added in PHPlot-6.0.0.
Before that, <function>SetDashedStyle</function> unconditionally set up the
line style, and returned a boolean value.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="SetDefaultFonts" xreflabel="SetDefaultFonts"/>SetDefaultFonts()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Selects all the default font values and sizes. See <xref linkend="SetFont"/>
for details of the font element names and default values.  Called by the class
constructor initialization function <xref linkend="initialize"/> to initialize
fonts in the plot object, and by <xref linkend="SetUseTTF"/> to restore the
defaults when changing from or to TrueType font usage.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="SetDefaultStyles" xreflabel="SetDefaultStyles"/>SetDefaultStyles()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Initializes default colors and styles for PHPlot objects. Mostly this calls
the public member functions such as <xref linkend="SetDataColors"/> but
without specifying an array of colors, which causes the member functions
to select default values.
Called by the class constructor initialization function
<xref linkend="initialize"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="SetIndexColor" xreflabel="SetIndexColor"/>SetIndexColor($which_color, $alpha = 0)</term> <!-- REMOVED -->
  <listitem>
    <para>
This function was removed in PHPlot-5.2.0.
It parsed a color specification, and allocated a GD color index.
The first part is replaced by calling <xref linkend="SetRGBColor"/> directly,
and the second part is implemented with <xref linkend="GetColorIndex"/>
at graph drawing time.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="SetIndexDarkColor" xreflabel="SetIndexDarkColor"/>SetIndexDarkColor($which_color, $alpha = 0)</term> <!-- REMOVED -->
  <listitem>
    <para>
This function was removed in PHPlot-5.2.0.
It parsed a color specification, and allocated a GD color index for a
slightly darker shade of the color.
The first part is replaced by calling <xref linkend="SetRGBColor"/> directly,
and the second part is implemented with <xref linkend="GetDarkColorIndex"/>
at graph drawing time.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="SetInputFile" xreflabel="SetInputFile"/>SetInputFile($which_input_file)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Sets an image file $which_input_file to be used as the background image for
the graph. Also resets the graph size to the size of the image file.
Called by the class constructor initialization function
<xref linkend="initialize"/>.
Note: In earlier releases, this was considered an externally available
function. After a PHPlot object was created with the constructor,
SetInputFile could be used to resize it and set the background image.
Although this still works, it is deprecated. SetInputFile should be
considered an internal-use-only function. Users should set the background
image file using the 4th argument of <xref linkend="PHPlot"/> or
<xref linkend="PHPlot-truecolor"/>  when creating an instance of the object.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="SetLabelType" xreflabel="SetLabelType"/>SetLabelType($mode, $args)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Sets the formatting used for tick, data, and pie chart labels.
This implements <xref linkend="SetXLabelType"/>,
<xref linkend="SetYLabelType"/>, <xref linkend="SetXDataLabelType"/>,
<xref linkend="SetYDataLabelType"/>, and part of
<xref linkend="SetPieLabelType"/>.
$mode is either 'x', 'xd', 'y', 'yd', or 'p' to select the type of label
(x, y for tick labels; xd, yd for data labels; p for pie chart labels).
$args is an array of arguments, with $args[0] selecting the type of
formatting (for example, <literal>data</literal>).
Additional array elements depend on the formatting type.
For more details, see the above-referenced functions.
All arguments to those functions are combined into an array and passed to
<function>SetLabelType</function> as $args.
Separation of data and tick label formatting was available starting with
PHPlot-5.1.0. Support for pie chart label formatting was added in PHPlot-5.6.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="SetRGBColor" xreflabel="SetRGBColor"/>SetRGBColor($color_asked, $alpha = 0)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Converts a general color specification into a standard form as an array of
4 components: red, green, blue, and alpha, and returns the array.  The 3
color components are integers in the range 0-255, and the alpha component
is an integer in the range 0-127 (where 0 means opaque).  The acceptable
color specification forms are documented in <xref linkend="conc-colors-forms"/>
and <xref linkend="adv-truecolor-forms"/>,
and include color names, component arrays, and strings of the form #RRGGBB
and #RRGGBBAA.  The alpha argument provides a default value if the color
specification does not include alpha; the default 0 makes the color
opaque.
This is used directly by all functions that accept a color specification.
Use of alpha in the color specification, the default alpha argument, and the
4th component in the returned array were added in PHPlot-5.1.1.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="SizeText" xreflabel="SizeText"/>SizeText($font, $angle, $text)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Calculates the size of a block of text. It works on both GD (fixed-font) and TTF
text.
$font is a text element name, empty, or a PHPlot font array (use of an array
is deprecated); see <xref linkend="DrawText"/> for details.
$angle is the text angle in degrees.
$text is the text string. The text string can contain multiple lines,
with a newline character between lines.
This function just calls <xref linkend="ProcessText"/> in text sizing mode
to do the work.
It returns a two-element array with the text width and height. These are the
width and height of an orthogonal bounding box (box aligned with the X
and Y axes) which contains the rotated text block.
Called by functions which need to determine text size for laying out
plot elements, such as <xref linkend="CalcMargins"/>.
This function replaced <xref linkend="TTFBBoxSize"/> at PHPlot-5.0.5.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="tile_img" xreflabel="tile_img"/>tile_img($file, $xorig, $yorig, $width, $height, $mode)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Tiles an image file over another the current plot image.
$file is the filename of the image to use as the tile.
($xorig, $yorig) are the origin point for the tiling,
and ($width, $height) are the area to be tiled. These are used to tile just
under the plot area versus the entire image. The $mode can be
<literal>centeredtile</literal>, <literal>tile</literal>, or
<literal>scale</literal>.  Scale mode scales the source image to
fit the target area. Tile and centeredtile modes repeat the source image as
needed to fit into the target area; the difference is that centeredtile
offsets the tile start position by half its size, which works better for
some tiles.
Called by
<xref linkend="DrawBackground"/> and <xref linkend="DrawPlotAreaBackground"/>
if an image file is selected for the plot area or overall background.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="truncate_array" xreflabel="truncate_array"/>truncate_array(&amp;$array, $size)</term> <!-- REMOVED -->
  <listitem>
    <para>
This was added in PHPlot-5.2.0 and removed in PHPlot-5.3.1,
when data color processing was changed to not truncate the color arrays.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="TTFBBoxSize" xreflabel="TTFBBoxSize"/>TTFBBoxSize($size, $angle, $font, $string)</term> <!-- REMOVED -->
  <listitem>
    <para>
This function was removed at PHPlot-5.0.5.
It was replaced by <xref linkend="SizeText"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="TuneAutoRange" xreflabel="TuneAutoRange"/>TuneAutoRange($which, $zero_magnet, $adjust_mode, $adjust_amount)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
This implements <xref linkend="TuneXAutoRange"/> and
<xref linkend="TuneYAutoRange"/> to store tuning parameters used by the
automatic range calculation. $which is 'x' or 'y', and the other arguments
are as described under those two public functions.
This was added in PHPlot-6.0.0
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="TuneAutoTicks"
xreflabel="TuneAutoTicks"/>TuneAutoTicks($which, $min_ticks, $tick_mode, $tick_inc_integer)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
This implements <xref linkend="TuneXAutoTicks"/> and
<xref linkend="TuneYAutoTicks"/> to store tuning parameters used by the
tick increment calculation. $which is 'x' or 'y', and the other arguments
are as described under those two public functions.
This was added in PHPlot-6.0.0
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="xtr" xreflabel="xtr"/>xtr($x_world)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Translates an X world coordinate value into a pixel coordinate value.
This uses the scale and translation set up by <xref linkend="CalcTranslation"/>.
See <xref linkend="GetDeviceXY"/> for a public interface.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="ytr" xreflabel="ytr"/>ytr($y_world)</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
Translates a Y world coordinate value into a pixel coordinate value.
This uses the scale and translation set up by <xref linkend="CalcTranslation"/>.
See <xref linkend="GetDeviceXY"/> for a public interface.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="__sleep" xreflabel="__sleep"/>__sleep()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
This is a PHP "magic method" that prepares a PHPlot object for serialization.
It stores the PHPlot version string (for checking at wakeup time), and a
flag indicating if it used a truecolor image or not.
See <xref linkend="adv-serialize"/>.
This was added in PHPlot-5.8.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="__wakeup" xreflabel="__wakeup"/>__wakeup()</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
This is a PHP "magic method" that re-creates a PHPlot object after
unserialization.
It checks the stored version string to make sure the object was serialized with
the exact same PHPlot version, and then re-creates the image resource.
See <xref linkend="adv-serialize"/>.
This was added in PHPlot-5.8.0.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</chapter>

<chapter id="dev-vars">
<title>PHPlot Class Member Variables</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This chapter provides information about the PHPlot class member variables
and constants.
  </para>
</abstract>

<para>
Most PHPlot class member variables are meant for internal use only,
and are declared to have <emphasis>protected</emphasis> visibility
(starting with PHPlot-6.0.0).
This means they are not accessible from your application, unless you define
a class that extends PHPlot.
All these member variables are subject to change in future
releases without concern for backward compatibility.
</para>

<para>
One exception is the plot tuning variables, which have public visibility.
<xref linkend="adv-tuning"/> describes how these PHPlot member variables
can be used to adjust plot appearance.
Setting them from your application is generally safe, as they have relatively
small effects on plots, and are less likely to change in future releases.
</para>

<para>
A few additional member class variables have public visibility, due to past
use in applications, but you should avoid using them. This includes
<literal>img</literal>, the GD image resource, and <literal>fonts</literal>,
the array of font information.
</para>

<sect1 id="dev-vars-list">
<title>List of Member Variables</title>

<para>
The table below lists the PHPlot class member variables.
</para>

<para>
The initial values are listed under <emphasis>Default Value</emphasis>.
Variables which are declared but not initialized at the top of the
PHPlot class definition have nothing in this column. They can be considered
to have an initial value of NULL, which is significant for some variables
but not for others.
</para>

<para>
The <emphasis>Reference Function</emphasis> column lists the member
function(s) used to set the variable, if the variable can be set by the
application, else the member function which calculates the variable, if
there is one, else the member function(s) which use the variable, if there
are only a few.
</para>

<para>
Variables which hold color values are initialized to defaults using
<xref linkend="SetDefaultStyles"/> when a PHPlot object is created.
For the default colors, see <xref linkend="conc-colors-elements"/>.
</para>

<para>
&variablelist;
</para>
</sect1>
<pagebreak/>
<sect1 id="dev-var-notes">
<title>Member Variable Notes</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This section contains details on some of the PHPlot class member variables
listed in the previous section.
Remember that all PHPlot class member variables are meant for internal use only.
  </para>
</abstract>

<sect2 id="var-datatypes">
<title>datatypes[]</title>
<para>
The <varname>datatypes[]</varname> array contains information about the
available data types. See <xref linkend="conc-datatypes"/> for more
information about data types.
It is used by <xref linkend="SetDataType"/> to validated the supplied data
type, and by <xref linkend="DecodeDataType"/> to set the flags that
describe the datatype.
</para>

<para>
The goal is to keep the names and details about the data types in this
array only, and minimize other uses of the actual data type names. However,
each plot type drawing function (for example <xref linkend="DrawLines"/>)
also 'knows' about the data types it supports, and specifies the data type
names when calling <xref linkend="CheckDataType"/>.
</para>

<para>
This array was added in PHPlot-6.1.0.
It is a protected static member variable in the PHPlot class, so it must be
accessed as <varname>self::$datatypes</varname> from inside the class (or a
derived class), and not through an instance of the class.
Is not accessible from outside the class or derived classes.
</para>

<para>
The array keys are the data types (for example: 'text-data').
The values are arrays which contain information about the data type.
The second-level array keys correspond to the 'datatype' flag variables,
without the 'datatype_' prefix. A key will be present, with the value
<literal>TRUE</literal>, if the flag should be set for that data type.
The key will be absent if the flag should not be set.
For example: for data type <literal>text-data</literal>, the array contains
one value: <literal>'implied' =&gt; TRUE</literal>. This means that for
data type text-data, the <literal>datatype_implied</literal> flag should be
TRUE (indicating that this data type has implied independent variable
values), and all other flags should be FALSE. In addition to
<literal>implied</literal>, the other possible keys are
<literal>pie_single</literal>, <literal>error_bars</literal>,
<literal>swapped_xy</literal>, and <literal>yz</literal>.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="var-fonts">
<title>fonts[]</title>
<para>
<?dbfo keep-together="always"?> <!-- Prevent PDF break before table -->
The <varname>fonts[]</varname> array contains information about the fonts to
use for text on the plot. The array keys are the element names (such as
<literal>title</literal> or <literal>legend</literal>) as used in
<xref linkend="SetFont"/>, <xref linkend="SetFontGD"/>, or
<xref linkend="SetFontTTF"/>. The array values are arrays which contain
information about the font to use for that element. The keys and values of
the second-level arrays are:

<informaltable>
  <?dbfo table-width="80%"?> <!-- Table width hint for PDF only -->
  <tgroup cols="3">
    <?dbhtml table-summary="fonts[] array elements"?>
<!-- Note: Unable to specify column widths that work in both HTML and PDF.
     For HTML, it only accepts %, and for FO/PDF it only takes *.
     The only work-around is to move longer content out of table cells, so
     HTML can automatically get columns widths that are acceptable.
-->
    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="20*" />
    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="40*" />
    <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="40*" />
    <thead>
      <row>
        <entry>Key</entry>
        <entry>Value for TTF</entry>
        <entry>Value for GD Font</entry>
      </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry>ttf</entry>
        <entry>True for a TrueType font</entry>
        <entry>False for a GD font</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>font</entry>
        <entry>Pathname of the font file</entry>
        <entry>Font number: 1 through 5</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>size</entry>
        <entry>Font point size</entry>
        <entry>Not used</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>height</entry>
        <entry>Height in pixels of an upper-case "E" in the font</entry>
        <entry>Font height in pixels</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>width</entry>
        <entry>Width in pixels of an upper-case "E" in the font</entry>
        <entry>Font width in pixels</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>spacing</entry>
        <entry>Font's built-in inter-line spacing</entry>
        <entry>Not used</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>line_spacing</entry>
        <entry>User-requested inter-line spacing factor.</entry>
        <entry>Same as for TTF</entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</informaltable>
</para>
<para>
For TrueType fonts, the height and width can vary by character. The fonts
array stores a height and width value for the font, but these are only used
for sizing non-text plot elements (such as the legend color boxes). When
PHPlot needs to know the drawn size of a string that will use TTF, it calculates
the exact size of that specific string when drawn with the designated font.
</para>
<para>
GD fonts have fixed character width and height, so the values stored in
the fonts array can be used to calculate text string sizes.
</para>

<para>
The <literal>spacing</literal> key stores the TrueType font's built-in
inter-line spacing. Although TrueType fonts have this information
internally, PHP cannot access it, so PHPlot calculates it by taking the
height of the string "E\nE" and subtracting twice the height of the letter E.
</para>

<para>
The <literal>line_spacing</literal> key stores the user-specified line spacing
adjustment for a text element, if any, from <xref linkend="SetFont"/> or
one of the two related functions. It will be NULL if the spacing was
not set for this element, meaning use the default line spacing.
See <xref linkend="SetLineSpacing"/> for more information on how this is used.
</para>

<para>
Here is an example of part of a fonts array, for the title element:
<programlisting><![CDATA[$plot->fonts['title'] = array(
    'ttf' => FALSE,          // This element uses a GD font
    'font' => 2,             // Use GD font 2
    'height' => 13,          // Provided by GD
    'width' => 6,            // Provided by GD
    'line_spacing' => NULL,  // Use default line spacing
)
]]></programlisting>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="var-label-format">
<title>label_format[]</title>
<para>
The <varname>label_format[]</varname> array contains information about how
text labels should be formatted. This array has 5 entries, with keys 'x',
'y', 'xd', 'yd', and 'p'. The 'x' and 'y' entries are for tick labels, and the
'xd' and 'yd' entries are for data labels. (Note that PHPlot defaults data
label formatting to match tick label formatting, but this is handled in
<xref linkend="CheckLabels"/>, with the tick label format information copied
to the data label format information if necessary.) The 'p' entry is for
pie chart labels, and will only exist for pie charts. (The 'p' entry was
added in PHPlot-5.6.0.)
</para>

<para>
<?dbfo keep-together="always"?> <!-- Prevent PDF break before table -->
The value of each entry in <varname>label_format</varname> is an array
containing formatting information. The arrays are empty by default, meaning
there is no special formatting. If formatting has been enabled, for example
with <xref linkend="SetXLabelType"/>, the arrays can contain the following
keys and values:

<informaltable>
  <?dbfo keep-together="always"?>
  <tgroup cols="3">
    <?dbhtml table-summary="label_format[] array elements"?>
    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="20*" />
    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="20*" />
    <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="60*" />
    <thead>
      <row>
        <entry>Key</entry>
        <entry>Used with type</entry>
        <entry>Value</entry>
      </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry>type</entry>
        <entry></entry>
        <entry>Formatting type: data, time, printf, or custom.</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>precision</entry>
        <entry>data</entry>
        <entry>The number of decimal positions to produce.</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>prefix</entry>
        <entry>data</entry>
        <entry>A prefix string to append to the label (for example, a currency
            sign).</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>suffix</entry>
        <entry>data</entry>
        <entry>A suffix string to append to the label (for example, a currency
           sign or percent sign).
           This replaces data_units_text (which still works too).</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>time_format</entry>
        <entry>time</entry>
        <entry>The date/time format string for the PHP strftime()
            function.</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>printf_format</entry>
        <entry>printf</entry>
        <entry>The format string for the PHP printf() function.</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>custom_callback</entry>
        <entry>custom</entry>
        <entry>The function (or array with object and method name) to call to
            format the label.</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>custom_arg</entry>
        <entry>custom</entry>
        <entry>An additional argument to pass to the custom_callback
            function.</entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</informaltable>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="var-legendpos">
<title>legend_pos[]</title>
<para>
The <varname>legend_pos[]</varname> array contains information about
positioning of the legend. This is set by <xref linkend="SetLegendPosition"/>,
and by the functions which use it (<xref linkend="SetLegendPixels"/> and
<xref linkend="SetLegendWorld"/>).
This was added in PHPlot-5.4.0, replacing scalar variables legend_x_pos,
legend_y_pos, and legend_xy_world.
</para>

<para>
<?dbfo keep-together="always"?> <!-- Prevent PDF break before table -->
The array keys correspond to the arguments to
<xref linkend="SetLegendPosition"/> and are shown in the following table.
<informaltable>
  <tgroup cols="2">
    <?dbhtml table-summary="legend_pos[] array elements"?>
    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="40*" />
    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="60*" />
    <thead>
      <row>
        <entry>Keys</entry>
        <entry>Value</entry>
      </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry>x, y</entry>
        <entry>Relative coordinates of a point on the legend box</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>mode</entry>
        <entry>One of: image, plot, title, or world</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>x_base, y_base</entry>
        <entry>Relative coordinates of a point on the image, plot, or
           title, or world coordinates</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>x_offset, y_offset</entry>
        <entry>Pixel offset to be applied last</entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</informaltable>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="var-plots">
<title>plots[]</title>
<para>
The <varname>plots[]</varname> array contains information about known plot
types. It is used by <xref linkend="FindDataLimits"/>,
<xref linkend="DrawGraph"/>, and other class functions to prepare for and
draw the main portion of the plot.
The goal is to contain the information about each available plot type
in a single place - this array. The actual names of the plot types (for
example 'bars' or 'linepoints') appear only in this array. To simplify
somewhat, adding a new plot type to PHPlot involves adding a new element to
the <varname>plots[]</varname> array, and adding a new function to PHPlot
which draws the 'insides' of the plot.
</para>

<para>
This array was added in PHPlot-5.3.0.
It is a protected static member variable in the PHPlot class, so it must be
accessed as <varname>self::$plots</varname> from inside the class (or a
derived class), and not through an instance of the class.
Is not accessible from outside the class or derived classes.
</para>

<para>
<?dbfo keep-together="always"?> <!-- Prevent PDF break before table -->
The array keys are the plot types (for example: 'bars', 'linepoints').
These must not include upper case letters.
The values are arrays which contain information about the plot type.
The keys and values of the second-level arrays are:

<informaltable>
  <tgroup cols="2">
    <?dbhtml table-summary="plots[] array elements"?>
    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="30*" />
    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="70*" />
    <thead>
      <row>
        <entry>Key</entry>
        <entry>Value</entry>
      </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry>draw_method</entry>
        <entry>
Name of the PHPlot class method (function) to call to draw the 'insides' of
the plot.  This is the only required entry.
        </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry>draw_arg</entry>
        <entry>
Optional argument array to pass to the draw_method function.
        </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry>suppress_axes</entry>
        <entry>
Optional flag indicating that the X axis and Y axis should not be drawn.
Default is FALSE.
        </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry>abs_vals</entry>
        <entry>
Optional flag indicating that the plot type uses the absolute values of data.
Default is FALSE.
        </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry>sum_vals</entry>
        <entry>
Optional flag indicating that the plot type sums up the values in each row.
Default is FALSE.
        </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry>legend_alt_marker</entry>
        <entry>
Optional alternate marker mode for legends: box, shape, or line.
        </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry>adjust_type</entry>
        <entry>
Optional control for adjusting the end of an automatically calculated plot
range (see notes below).
        </entry>
      </row>

    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</informaltable>
</para>

<para>
Only the <literal>draw_method</literal> entry is required.  The named method
is used to draw everything inside the plot area. (That is, everything except
the plot titles, axis lines, tick marks and tick labels, grid lines, and
legend.)
</para>

<para>
The <literal>draw_arg</literal> entry can be used to pass constant
arguments to the <literal>draw_method</literal> method.
If present, this must be an array, and each element of the array is passed to
the drawing method as a separate argument.  If this is not specified, the
drawing method is called with no arguments.  This is generally used to
overload drawing methods, so they handle multiple similar plot types.
</para>

<para>
The <literal>suppress_axes</literal> flag indicates that X and Y axis lines
should not be drawn (used with pie charts, for example).
If omitted, FALSE is used, meaning the axis lines are drawn.
(Before PHPlot-6.0.0 this was called <literal>draw_axes</literal>, with
default TRUE, and FALSE for pie charts.)
</para>

<para>
The two special data processing flags <literal>abs_vals</literal> and
<literal>sum_vals</literal> are used by <xref linkend="FindDataLimits"/>
to indicate how to compute the minimum and maximum data values.
Plot types that ignore sign and take absolute values of the data set
<literal>abs_vals</literal> to TRUE.
Plot types that sum up the data values in each row set
<literal>sum_vals</literal> to TRUE.
The default if omitted for both flags is FALSE, meaning the plot type
uses the values as specified in the data array.

If both <literal>abs_vals</literal> and <literal>sum_vals</literal> are TRUE,
this means the plot type sums up the absolute values from the data array.
(The stackedarea plot type does this.)
</para>

<para>
The optional <literal>legend_alt_marker</literal> entry indicates the
use of an alternate maker shape in legends.
Use <xref linkend="SetLegendUseShapes"/> to select either the primary
mode or the alternate mode for legend shapes. The primary mode is a solid
filled color box. The alternate mode varies with the plot type, according
the the <literal>legend_alt_marker</literal> entry.
Use 'box' for rectangular color boxes. This is the default if the
<literal>legend_alt_marker</literal> key is omitted from the array.
Effectively, this means there is no alternate marker
mode for these plot types, because color boxes are the primary mode.
Use 'shape' for point shape markers, which applies to points plots and similar
types which use point shapes.
Use 'line' for short line segments, which applies to line plots and similar
types.
</para>

<para>
The optional <literal>adjust_type</literal> entry controls adjustments
made to the end of an automatically calculated plot range.
See <xref linkend="TuneXAutoRange"/> and <xref linkend="TuneYAutoRange"/>
for more information.
This is used to indicate when a plot type needs additional space, perhaps
for labels, between the data extrema and the edge of the plot area.
If omitted, the default value 0 is used.
A value of 0 means apply the adjustment for the dependent variable only.
A value of 1 means apply the adjustment for both X and Y, and a value of
2 means do not apply the adjustment to either X or Y.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="var-rangectl">
<title>rangectl[]</title>
<para>
The <varname>rangectl[]</varname> array contains parameters which are used
to control the automatic calculation of the plot area range.
</para>

<para>
<?dbfo keep-together="always"?> <!-- Prevent PDF break before table -->
The array contains 2 arrays, indexed as <literal>'x'</literal> and
<literal>'y'</literal> for X and Y axis parameters respectively.
The keys and values of the second-level arrays are:
<informaltable>
  <tgroup cols="3">
    <?dbhtml table-summary="rangectl[] array elements"?>
    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="30*" />
    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="30*" />
    <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="40*" />
    <thead>
      <row>
        <entry>Key</entry>
        <entry>Default</entry>
        <entry>Description</entry>
      </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry>zero_magnet</entry>
        <entry>0.857142 (Note this is 6/7)</entry>
        <entry>Strength of the <emphasis>zero magnet</emphasis></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>adjust_mode</entry>
        <entry>T</entry>
        <entry>End adjustment mode: R, T, or I</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>adjust_amount</entry>
        <entry>(Dynamic; see <xref linkend="GetRangeEndAdjust"/>)</entry>
        <entry>Amount of end adjustment, as a fraction of the plot range</entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</informaltable>
</para>

<para>
Values in this array are set with
<xref linkend="TuneXAutoRange"/> and <xref linkend="TuneYAutoRange"/>.
For more information see <xref linkend="adv-autorange-params"/>.
The values are used by <xref linkend="CalcPlotRange"/>.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="var-tickctl">
<title>tickctl[]</title>
<para>
The <varname>tickctl[]</varname> array contains parameters which are used
to control the automatic calculation of tick intervals.
</para>

<para>
<?dbfo keep-together="always"?> <!-- Prevent PDF break before table -->
The array contains 2 arrays, indexed as <literal>'x'</literal> and
<literal>'y'</literal> for X and Y axis parameters respectively.
The keys and values of the second-level arrays are:
<informaltable>
  <tgroup cols="3">
    <?dbhtml table-summary="tickctl[] array elements"?>
    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="30*" />
    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="30*" />
    <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="40*" />
    <thead>
      <row>
        <entry>Key</entry>
        <entry>Default</entry>
        <entry>Description</entry>
      </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry>min_ticks</entry>
        <entry>8</entry>
        <entry>Minimum number of tick intervals</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>tick_mode</entry>
        <entry>NULL (calculated)</entry>
        <entry>Tick increment calculation mode: 'decimal', 'binary', or 'date'</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>tick_inc_integer</entry>
        <entry>FALSE</entry>
        <entry>If TRUE, force the tick increment to be a whole number</entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</informaltable>
</para>

<para>
Values in this array are set with
<xref linkend="TuneXAutoTicks"/> and <xref linkend="TuneYAutoTicks"/>.
For more information see <xref linkend="adv-autorange-tick-params"/>.
The values are used by <xref linkend="CalcStep"/>.
</para>

</sect2>


</sect1>

<!-- Note: This used to be another Chapter, since the previous chapter
     is about variables, not constants. But that seemed to confuse
     Docbook and it made a bad 'prev' link in the next page (Appendix 1)
     which skipped over the Constants chapter.  Making it a section of the
     previous chapter instead works around the problem.
-->
<sect1 id="dev-const">
<title>PHPlot Class Constants</title>
<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This section provides information about constants defined in the PHPlot class.
As these are PHP constants, they are accessed without a leading $ and
cannot be expanded inside string values.
  </para>
</abstract>

<para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="const_version" xreflabel="PHPlot::version"/>PHPlot::version</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
The <varname>version</varname> constant contains the PHPlot code version as
a string, for example <literal>"5.4.0"</literal>.
(This was added in PHPlot-5.4.0.)
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
  <term><anchor id="const_version_id" xreflabel="PHPlot::version_id"/>PHPlot::version_id</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
The <varname>version_id</varname> constant contains the PHPlot code version as
an integer, using the conventional formula 10000*major_version +
100*minor_version + patch_version.
This was added in PHPlot-6.0.0 (with value 60000) to make it
possible for the test suite to check for a minimum version.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>
</para>
</sect1>

</chapter>

</part>
