<!-- $Id$
     Installation chapter for PHPlot Reference Manual
-->
<chapter id="install">
<title>PHPlot Installation</title>

<abstract><title></title>
  <para>
This chapter explains how to install PHPlot.
  </para>
</abstract>

<sect1 id="install-prereq">
<title>Prerequisites</title>
<para>
Before you can use PHPlot, you need a recent version of PHP with the GD
extension.
PHPlot-5.8.0 and later require at least PHP-5.3.
(See the README and NEWS files included with the PHPlot distribution
for requirements of other versions.)
In general, you should always use the latest available stable version of PHP5.
</para>

<para>
If you want to display PHPlot charts on a web site, you need a PHP-enabled
web server. You can also use PHPlot with the PHP CLI (command line interface)
without a web server.
</para>

<para>
You need the GD extension to PHP, either built in to PHP or loaded as a
module.
The GD extension to PHP is included with PHP source releases, and is also
included in the binary Windows releases (as a loadable module).
The PHP GD extension uses the GD library (libgd).
A version of the GD library is included with PHP releases, and use of this
version is recommended, but you can also use the PHP GD extension with a
separate GD library (for example, one included with your operating system).
</para>

<para>
If you aren't sure what extensions you have in PHP, create this PHP
script called <filename>phpinfo.php</filename> somewhere in
your web server's document tree:
<programlisting><![CDATA[<?php phpinfo();
]]></programlisting>
Access this page with your browser to view your PHP configuration.
Look for the section labeled 'gd'. If you have no 'gd' section in the
PHP Info output, you don't have the required 'gd' extension.
(The extension is either missing, or the module was not loaded.)
Consult the PHP documentation to find out how to get it loaded.
Here's what the GD section of the PHP Info listing might look like:
<informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/gdinfo.png" scale="58" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
      <phrase>GD section of PHP Info listing</phrase>
    </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
</informalfigure>
</para>

<para>
The text in the 'gd' section of the PHP Info output will tell you what
version of GD you have (you need 2.0 or higher), and what output formats it
supports.
Check the table for <emphasis>PNG Support</emphasis>,
since PNG is the default output format for PHPlot.
If you want to create GIF or JPEG (JPG) format images,
check the table to see if they are available.
If the image formats you want are not available, you will have to rebuild PHP
(or rebuild the GD extension).
</para>

<para>
Another thing to look for in the 'gd' section of the PHP Info output is
<emphasis>FreeType Support</emphasis>. If you have it enabled, you can use
TrueType fonts in PHPlot. If your GD does not have FreeType support
enabled, you can still make decent-looking plots with PHPlot, using the
built-in GD fonts. Note that even if you have FreeType Support enabled,
you need some actual TrueType font files in order to use TrueType fonts
with PHPlot.  PHPlot does not include any TrueType font files.
</para>

<para>
While you have the PHP Info report up, look in the Configuration section
for PHP Core, at the top of the report, and make a note of the
<literal>include_path</literal> setting.
If you have a local include directory in this path, you can use it for
installing PHPlot, as described below.
</para>

<note>
  <para>
Don't leave the <filename>phpinfo.php</filename> file in your web server
document tree, as there may be security implications in the information it
tells people about your web server.
  </para>
</note>

<para>
Once you have a web server with PHP and the GD extension, you are ready to
install PHPlot.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="install-install">
<title>Installing</title>
<para>
Unpack the PHPlot distribution into a convenient directory. PHPlot releases
are available both as ZIP files, and as gzip-compressed TAR files.
Use whichever format is more convenient for you. In the example below, the
TAR format is unpacked.
<screen><![CDATA[$ tar -xvzf phplot-6.*.tar.gz
$ cd phplot-6.*
]]></screen>
(Use the appropriate file and directory (folder) name.)
Check the distribution for README and/or INSTALL files which may contain
newer instructions.
</para>

<para>
Installation of PHPlot simply involves copying the script files somewhere
your PHP application scripts will be able to find them. The scripts are:
<filename>phplot.php</filename>, the main script file,
and <filename>rgb.inc.php</filename>, an optional script file containing a
large color map.
Make sure the protections on these files allow the web server to read them.
For example:
<screen><![CDATA[$ chmod 644 *.php
]]></screen>
</para>

<para>
Then, simply copy the files into a directory where PHP scripts
will be able to include them.
The ideal place is a directory outside your web server
document area, and on your PHP include path (that you noted above in
the PHP Info report). You can add to the include path
in the PHP configuration file; consult the PHP manual for details.
For example, if <filename>/usr/local/share/php</filename> is on
your PHP include path, you can install PHPlot with:
<screen><![CDATA[$ cp phplot.php rgb.inc.php /usr/local/share/php
]]></screen>
</para>

<note>
  <para>
On Windows systems, you can simply download the release ZIP file, expand it
using Windows Explorer, and copy the needed script file(s) out of the
contained <filename>phplot-*</filename> folder into place.
  </para>
</note>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="install-next">
<title>Next Step</title>
<para>
You can test PHPlot with any of the examples in <xref linkend="examples" />,
or by entering this minimal script into a file called (for example)
<filename>plottest.php</filename>.
<programlisting><![CDATA[<?php
require 'phplot.php';
$data = array(array('', 10), array('', 1));
$plot = new PHPlot();
$plot->SetDataValues($data);
$plot->SetTitle('First Test Plot');
$plot->DrawGraph();
]]></programlisting>
Access this script through your browser, and you should see a very simple
plot. Note: Since PHPlot returns image data, not text, you will generally
not see error messages in the output. If a script using PHPlot has a
syntax error, or calls an undefined function, you will get a blank page
returned, and you will probably have to check the web server error log
for the reason.
You might find that debugging your PHPlot applications is easier using
the PHP CLI (command line interface),
as described at the start of <xref linkend="examples" />.
</para>

<para>
If you are installing PHPlot for use by some web application (rather than
to develop your own applications), proceed with that application's setup
instructions. If you want to develop your own applications using PHPlot, you
can start by looking at some of the examples in <xref linkend="examples" />,
or go right to the introductory material in <xref linkend="starting" />.
Experienced programmers may want to skip right to <xref linkend="concepts" />
to learn about PHPlot concepts and features in depth.
</para>
</sect1>

</chapter>
